<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="alltexts.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Life of Margaret Fox, Wife of George Fox, Compiled from her own narrative and
               other sources, with a selection from her epistles, etc.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>A TEI project created for Z656: Digital Publishing Standards and Systems, Spring
               2018. (Indiana University Bloomington, School of Informatics &amp; Computing,
               Department of Information and Library Science. Source text digitized by the Library
               of Congress.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Fox</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main"> The Life of Margaret Fox, Wife of George Fox, Compiled from
                     her Own Narrative and Other Sources, with a Selection from her Epistles,
                     etc.</title>
                  <title type="apa">The life of Margaret Fox, wife of George Fox, compiled from her
                     own narrative and other sources, with a selection from her epistles,
                     etc.</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>ASSOCIATION OF FRIENDS FOR THE DIFFUSION OF RELIGIOUS AND USEFUL
                        KNOWLEDGE</publisher>
                     <date>1859</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>

         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE LIFE OF </titlePart>
               <titlePart> MARGARET FOX,</titlePart>
               <titlePart>WIFE OF GEORGE FOX </titlePart>
               <titlePart> COMPILED FROM HER OWN NARRATIVE AND OTHER SOURCES</titlePart>
               <titlePart>WITH A </titlePart>
               <titlePart> SELECTION FROM HER EPISTLES, ETC. </titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docAuthor> Margaret Fox</docAuthor>

            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>Philadelphia:</pubPlace> PUBLISHED BY THE <publisher> ASSOCIATION OF
                  FRIENDS FOR THE DIFFUSION OF RELIGIOUS AND USEFUL KNOWLEDGE</publisher>, 109 North
               Tenth Street. <date>1859</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>


         <div type="toc">
            <list>
               <item>Preface <ptr target="pgiii"/>
               </item>
               <item>Chapter I. <ptr target="pg5"/>
               </item>
               <item>Chapter II. <ptr target="pg19"/></item>
               <item>Chapter III. <ptr target="pg34"/></item>
               <item>Chapter IV. <ptr target="pg49"/></item>
               <item>Chapter V. <ptr target="pg64"/></item>
               <item>Epistles <ptr target="pg77"/></item>
               <item>Principle Workds <ptr target="pg101"/></item>
               <item>Swarthmore Hall <ptr target="pg110"/></item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pgiii">
            <p>PREFACE.</p>
         </div>
     
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>The Society of Friends has numbered within its ranks many eminent women, who have
               enunciated and explained its doctrines and testimonies, both by their ministry and
               writings; and have illustrated its Christian faith by the consistency of their lives
               and conversation, and their patience under persecution. Amongst these, none shone
               more conspicuously, in the early days of the Society, than the subject of this
               memoir. Having been convinced by the baptizing ministry of George Fox, she became a
               faithful mem- ber of the church; her influence and reputation in the community, as
               well as her ministry and writings, greatly contributing to advance the cause of
               truth. As a preacher of the Gospel, she was fervent and weighty; as a writer, bold,
               earnest and persuasive; in her disposition, charitable and hospitable; and a warm
               sympathizer with the afflicted and persecuted. Her works having been long out of
               print, and almost unknown in this country, it is believed that the following
               compilation, giving a brief account of her life, a selection from her epistles, and a
               few extracts from her other writings, will prove acceptable to the reader.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg5">
            <p>CHAPTER I. 1614-1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterSubtitle">
            <p>HER BIRTH — PARENTAGE — MARRIES THOMAS FELL, AND SET- TLES AT SWARTHMORE — RELIGIOUS
               LIFE — VISITED BY GEORGE FOX — SHE AND HER CHILDREN CONVINCED — DIS- PLEASURE OF HER
               HUSBAND — LETTER FROM R. FARNSWORTH</p>
            <p>JUDGE FELL RECONCILED, AND A MEETING ESTABLISHED</p>
            <p>AT HER HOUSE TESTIMONY OF A. PIERSON AND WILLIAM</p>
            <p>CATON TO THE EXEMPLARY CHARACTER OF THE FAMILY — DEATH OF HER HUSBAND — HIS CHARACTER
               — LETTER OF CONDOLENCE FROM A. PIERSON — THEIR CHILDREN.</p>
         </div>
    
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Margaret Fox was born at Marsh Grange, in the parish of Dalton, in Fournis,
               Lancashire^ Eng- land, in the year 1614. She was the daughter of John Askew, who was
               of an ancient and honourable family • he was honest, pious and charitable, and a man
               of estate and education.</p>
            <p>She was married, in her eighteenth year, to Thomas Fell, of Swarthmore, a
               barrister-at-law, after- wards a justice of the Quorum in his county, a member of
               several Parliaments, vice-chancellor of the county Palatine of Lancaster, and also a
               judge in the circuit of West Chester and North Wales, &amp;c. Strict in- tegrity and
               love of justice, tempered with mercy and moderation, were conspicuous traits in his
               character. In the seventy-sixth year of her age she wrote a short biographical
               sketch, rehearsing some of the principal events of her life, which has been largely
               used in the preparation of this work; in which, speaking of her husband, she says: —
               " We lived together twenty-six years, in which time we had nine children. He was a
               tender and loving husband to me, and a tender father to his children, and one that
               sought after God in the best way that was made known to him. I was about sixteen
               years younger than he, and was one that sought after the best things, being desirous
               to serve God, so that I might be accepted of Him; and was inquiring after the way of
               the Lord, and went often to hear the best ministers that came into our parts, whom we
               fre- quently entertained at our house; many of those that were accounted the most
               serious, godly men, some of whom we then called lecturing ministers; and often had
               prayers and religious exercises in our family. This I hoped I did well in, but often
               feared I was short of the right way; and after this manner I was inquiring and
               seeking about twenty years, when, in 1652, it pleased the Lord, in his infinite mercy
               and goodness, to send George Fox into our country, who declared unto us the eternal
               truth, as it is in Jesus; and by the Word and power of the eternal God, turned many
               from darkness unto light, and from the power of Satan unto God."</p>
            <p>The powerful and awakening nature of the spi- ritual ministry of George Fox, and the
               effect pro- duced by it on her own mind, and his discourse on this occasion, she thus
               describes: —</p>
            <p>"Our house being a place open to entertain ministers and religious people, one of
               George Fox's friends brought him thither, where he staid all night; and the next day
               being a lecture or fast-day, he went to Ulverstone steeple-house, but came not in
               till people were gathered; I and my children had been a long time there before. And
               when they were singing, before the sermon, he came in; and when they had done, he
               stood up, upon a seat or form, and desired ' that he might have liberty to speak f
               and he that was in the pulpit said he might. And the first words that he spoke were
               as followeth: 'He is not a Jew that is one outward, neither is that circumcision
               which is outward; but he is a Jew that is one inward, and that is circumcision which
               is of the heart/ And so he went on and said 'that Christ was the light of the world,
               and lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and that by this light they might
               be gathered to God &amp;c. I stood up in my pew, and wondered at his doctrine; for I
               had never heard such before: and then he went on, and opened the Scriptures, and
               said: ' The Scriptures were the prophet's words, and Christ's and the apos- tles'
               words; and what, as they spoke, they enjoyed and possessed, and had it from the
               Lord:' and said:</p>
            <p>'Then what had any to do with the Scriptures, but as they came to the spirit that
               gave them forth. You will say Christ saith this, and the apostles say this; but what
               canst thou say? Art thou a child of light, and hast walked in the light; and what
               thou speak- eth, is it inwardly from God/ &amp;c. This opened me so, that it cut me
               to the heart; and then I saw clearly we were all wrong. So I sat down in my pew
               again, and cried bitterly; and I cried in my spirit to the Lord: i We are all
               thieves; we are all thieves; <note n="1"> Probably in allusion to John x. 1: "
                  Verily, verily, I say unto you, he that entereth not by the door into the
                  sheepfold, but climbeth up some other way, the same is a thief and a
                  robber."</note> we have taken the Scriptures in words, and know no- thing of them
               in ourselves/ So that served me, that I cannot well tell what he spoke afterwards;
               but he went on declaring against false prophets, priests and deceivers of the people.
               And he came to our house again that night, and spoke in the family amongst the
               servants, and they were all generally convinced. And I was struck into such sadness,
               I knew not what to do, my husband being from home. I saw it was the truth, and I
               could not deny it; and I did as the apostle saith: i I received the truth in the love
               of it f and it was opened to me so clear, that I had never a tittle in my heart
               against it; but I desired the Lord that I might be kept in it, and then I desired no
               greater portion."</p>
            <p>George Fox, in describing the circumstances attending his visit to Swarthmore at this
               time, after relating his controversies with the parish priest, Lam- pitt, and his"
               discourses on religious subjects with M. Fell and her children, in which they were
               measura- bly convinced, says that, " soon after, a day was to be observed for a
               humiliation; and Margaret Fell asked me to go with her to the steeple-house at Ul-
               verstone, for she was not wholly come off from them. I replied: i I must do as I am
               ordered of the Lord. So I left her, and walked into the fields; and the word of the
               Lord came unto me, saying: i Go to the steeple-house after them/ When I came, Lampitt
               was singing with his people; but his spirit was so foul, and the matter they sung so
               unsuitable to their states, that after they had done singing, I was moved of the Lord
               to speak to him and the people. Then, as the Lord opened further, I showed them that
               He was come to teach His people by his spirit, and to bring them off from their old
               ways, religions, churches and worships; for all their religions, worships and ways
               were but taking other men's words; but they were out of the life and spirit which
               those were in who gave them forth. Then cried out one Justice Sawrey: 'Take him
               away;' but Judge Fell's wife said to the officers: i Let him alone; why may he not
               speak, as well as any other V Lampitt, also, the priest, in deceit said: i Let him
               speak/ So at length, when I had declared a pretty while, Justice Sawrey caused the
               constable to put me out; and then I spake to the people in the grave-yard."</p>
            <p>Margaret Fell continues: "And when I and my children, and a great part of our
               servants, were so convinced and converted unto God, my husband was not at home, being
               gone to London. When he came home, and found us the most part of his family- changed
               from our former principles and persuasions, which he left us in, he was much
               surprised at our sudden change ) for some envious people, our neigh- bours, went and
               met him, and informed him that we had entertained such men as had taken us off from
               going to church, which he was very much concerned at, and seemed much troubled.</p>
            <p>And it so happened that Richard Farnsworth, and some other Friends (that came into
               our parts a little after George Fox), were then at our house and they discoursed with
               him, and did persuade him to be still, and weigh things before he did anything
               hastily, and his spirit was somewhat calmed. And after he had heard them speak
               awhile, he was better satisfied. I desired them to stay, and not go away, for George
               Fox will come this evening. And I would have had my husband to have heard them all,
               and satisfied himself further about them, because they had so prepossessed him
               against them, of such dangerous, fearful things. And then he was pretty moderate and
               quiet; and his dinner being ready, he went to it, and I went in and sat me down by
               him. And whilst I was sitting, the power of the Lord seized upon me; and he was
               struck with amazement, and knew not what to think. And the chil- dren were all quiet
               and still, and grown sober, and could not play on their music, that they were learn-
               ing; and all these things made him quiet."</p>
            <p>MARGARET FOX. 11</p>
            <p>"At night, George Fox came; and after supper, as my husband was sitting in the
               parlor, I asked if he might come in? and he said 'Yes' So George, without any
               compliment, walked into the room, and began to speak presently; and the family, and
               James Naylor, and Richard Farnsworth, came in; and he spoke very excellently, as ever
               I heard him, and opened Christ's and the apostle's practices: and if all England had
               been there, I thought they could not deny the truth of these things."</p>
            <p>George Fox relates: "Soon after Judge Fell being come home, Margaret his wife
               desiring me to return thither, aiid I feeling freedom of the Lord so to do, went back
               to Swarthmore. I found the priests, and professors, and Justice Sawrey, had much in-
               censed Judge Fell and Captain Sands against the truth by their lies; I answered all
               his objections, and so thoroughly satisfied him by the Scriptures, that he was
               convinced in his judgment. After we had discoursed a pretty while together, he was
               satis- fied, and came to see, by the openings of the spirit of God in his heart, over
               air the priests and teachers in the world, and did not go to hear them for some years
               before he died; for he knew it was the truth I declared, and that Christ was the
               teacher of his people, and their Saviour."</p>
            <p>The following letter, addressed to Margaret Fell by Richard Farnsworth, a few months
               after, may serve to show the continued interest he took in her convincement and
               establishment in the truth: —</p>

            <p>"Balhie, Yorkshire, 12th month, 1652. Dear Sister: —</p>
            <p>Mind to stand in the council of the Lord, which will keep down everything that would
               be exalted, and will not suffer thee to conform to any- thing but that which is pure.
               Oh! be faithful, be faithful to what thou knowest; and stand perfect in the will of
               the Lord; and the Lord will keep thee, in His own power to Himself, and arm thee
               every way with His love and power. Stand in His council, and it will discover all the
               consultations of the enemy; and will scatter all imaginations, and will not suffer
               them to take place in thee, being but obe- dient to Him. Love not the world, but mind
               that which would draw thee to live in the pure obedience of Him who is pure; and
               standing in the pure fear, it will take away all slavish fears, and it will not
               suffer thee to conform to the world in anything; but thou wilt be preserved in
               obedience to the Lord in what he doth require; for the fear of the Lord keepeth the
               heart clean; and it will keep thee clean, and open to receive the teachings of the
               Father. Oh! stand fast in the liberty wherewith Christ has set thee free, and it will
               keep thee from the entan- glements of the world; and thy preservation will be, in
               standing in the council of the Lord, who is the mighty Counsellor, the everlasting
               Prince of peace; who will lead thee and guide thee into the everlast- ing kingdom of
               the Father, where there is peace and joy, rest, quietness and assurance forever! Give
               thyself up wholly to the Lord, who will preserve thee in faithfulness and purity; and
               the everlasting Lord God Almighty keep thee, and all the rest of our dear Friends, in
               the power of His love, and in the power of His truth, perfect in His will ) that ye
               may grow from strength to strength, and be established in the everlasting truth; and
               that He alone may be glori- fied, who is Lord of lords, and King of kings; to whom be
               glory, and honour, and praise, and thanks, for ever and ever ! Amen.</p>
            <p>I received thy letter, which did much rejoice me. When thy letter, with James and
               George, came, I was then gone towards Derbyshire, where I met with a gathered church.
               I have been in much ser- vice since I came from you. Friends are much em- boldened
               and courageous, who have had great oppo- sition and persecution here away; but all is
               at a stand; the enemy is much in silence 5 and the Lord carries on His own work, much
               to His own praise; to Him alone be glory, and honour, for ever and ever !</p>
            <p>My dear, love in the Lord presents itself to you all, to thy son George, and to thy
               daughters, and to all those thy servants in the truth of God; and the Lord cause them
               all to grow up into the truth, that He may be exalted amongst you all. Ah! my dear
               hearts, prize the love and mercy of the Lord, and daily mind your growth into that
               which is eternal; and the everlasting love and power of the Lord keep you all in
               faithfulness to Him in what you know. Keep in the cross, and purity will grow. The
               safest way is in the cross; take up the cross daily; mind to be guided by that which
               crosseth your own wills, and it will bring every idle word, thought and deed to
               judgment in you; and so the old man will be crucified, with the affections and lusts
               thereof; and you shall find the Lord to sit as a refiner, to judge out all the old
               leaven, the old nature; and so the new man will be raised up; and Christ, the power
               of God, will rule and reign in righteousness in you, who is the King of saints; to
               Him alone be all praise and thanks forevermore! Amen!"</p>
            <p>Although Judge Fell did not openly unite with Friends, or attend their meetings, he
               was very favour- able to their views, and generally sat in an adjoining room, where
               he could hear, without appearing to join in their worship. Some Friends, in his
               presence, speaking of the difficulty in obtaining a place to hold their meetings in
               that part of the country, he promptly and generously offered them his own house,
               saying: " You may meet here, if you will;" and notice being given, u there was a good
               large meeting there the next first-day," which was the first held at Swarthmore,
               where a meeting was established, and continued from 1652 to 1690. The room appro-
               priated for this purpose was the large hall on the ground-floor, at one end of which,
               within the space of a bay window, the floor is raised two steps. In this place, it is
               said, George Fox and his wife usually took their seats, and the other ministering
               Friends, when present. From this window George Fox often preached to the people
               assembled in the adjoining orchard, when they were unable, from their numbers, to
               meet within.</p>
            <p>George Fox's fame, spreading with his doctrine, usually caused a large company to
               assemble to hear him, when he visited Swarthmore. At one time, Judge Fell, upon
               returning home, rinding his stables filled with the horses of these strange guests,
               com- plained to his wife of the large accession of new comers, saying, if this
               continued, they would soon be eaten out, and have no provender left for themselves.
               To this she pleasantly replied, that charity doth not impoverish; and notwithstanding
               all this extra con- sumption, she fully believed that, at the end of the year, he
               would have no cause to regret their hospi- tality. And so it proved, for the same
               year the crop of hay was so abundant, that they had not only plenty for themselves,
               but a large surplus to sell.</p>
            <p>The example of this excellent family doubtless exercised a powerful influence on the
               minds of many who came within the sphere of its influence, inviting them to come
               taste and handle for themselves of the good Word of life, of which they had been made
               par- takers, by yielding obedience to the requirings of truth. Several of their
               household became preachers of righteousness in word and conversation, and were
               instrumental in turning many from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan to
               God. Anthony Pierson, in a letter dated in 1653, thus describes the impressions which
               a visit to Swarthmore produced on his mind: " Oh! how gracious the Lord was to me in
               carrying me to Judge Fell's, to see the wonders of His power and wisdom; a family
               walking in the fear of the Lord, conversing daily with Him, cruci- fied to the world,
               and living only to God. I was so confounded, all my knowledge and wisdom became
               folly; my mouth was stopped, my conscience con- vinced, and the secrets of my heart
               were made mani- fest, and that Lord was discovered to be near, whom I ignorantly
               worshipped. I have seen at Judge FelFs, and have been informed from that precious
               soul his consort, in some measure what those things mean, which before I counted the
               overflowing of giddy brains. Dear heart, pity and pray for me, and let all
               obligations of former friendship be discharged, in well wishes to the soul of the old
               family friend, that he may partake with them of your heavenly possession."</p>
            <p>In confirmation of this, is the testimony of William Caton, an inmate of the family.
               He says: —</p>
            <p>"Oh! the love which in that day abounded among us, especially in that family! and oh
               ! the freshness of the power of the Lord God, which then was amongst us; and the zeal
               for Him and His truth, the comfort and refreshment which we had from His presence,
               the nearness and dearness that was amongst us one towards another, the openings and
               revelations which we then had! my heart is affected with the remembrance of them at
               this very day. And hence came that worthy family to be so renowned in the nation, the
               fame of . which spread much among Friends; and the power and presence of the Lord
               being so much there with us, it was as a means to induce many, even from afar, to
               come thither so that at one time there would have been Friends out of five or six
               counties, all which tended to the augmenting of my refreshment. And on the other hand
               was I cherished and encouraged in the way of life by my entirely beloved friend
               Margaret Fell, who as a tender-hearted nursing mother cared for me, and was as tender
               of me, as if I had been one of her own children. Oh! the kindness, the respect and
               friend- ship which she showed me, ought never to be for- gotten by me."</p>
            <p>Margaret Fell continues, speaking of her husband: u He lived about six years after I
               was convinced, in which time it pleased the Lord to visit him with sickness, wherein
               he became more than usually loving and kind to our friends called Quakers, having
               been a merciful man to the Lord's people. I and many other Friends were well
               satisfied, the Lord in mercy received him to Himself."</p>
            <p>His death occurred in the eighth month, 1658, he being about sixty years of age,
               leaving one son and seven daughters. <note n="2"><p>The son's name was George; the
                     daughters, Margaret, married to John Rous; Sarah, to William Mead; Mary, to
                     Thomas Lower; Susanna, to William Ingram; Rachel, to</p>
                  <p>Daniel Abraham; Isabel, to Yeomans, afterwards to</p>
                  <p>Abraham Morris; and Bridget, to John Draper. These marriages all occurred after
                     his death.</p>
                  <p>John Rous suffered severe persecutions in New England, and in addition to many
                     cruel whippings, had his right ear cut off. He was a native of Barbadoes,
                     subsequently settled near London. William Mead was the companion of William
                     Penn at the time of their persecution and celebrated trial at the Old Baily,
                     familiar to all readers of Friends' history.</p></note></p>


            <p>William Perm, speaking of him, says: " Being a just and wise nian, and seeing in his
               own wife and family a full confutation of all the popular clamors against the way of
               truth, he covered them what he could, and freely opened his doors, and gave up his
               house to his wife and her friends, not valuing the reproach of ignorant or
               evil-minded people; which I here mention to his and her honour. That house was, for
               some years at first, till the truth had opened its way in the southern parts of the
               island, an eminent receptacle of this people."</p>
            <p>Alexander Parker thus condoles with her on the death of her husband, and bears
               testimony to his worth: " Dear Sister, be thou comforted and re- freshed; though an
               outward stay be taken from thee, the Lord, I know, will never leave thee nor forsake
               thee: thy house is not left desolate, but the Grod of Jacob will be thy refuge, and
               the Lord thy Maker is thy husband. It was but very lately I heard of the laying down
               of the body of thy husband, and truly it did at first sadden my spirit, knowing his
               dear love and tender care over the Lord's lambs."</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg19">
            <p>CHAPTER II. 1658-1662.</p>
         </div>
    
         <div type="chapterSubtitle">
            <p>LETTERS TO CROMWELL LETTER FROM A. RIGGE — GEORGE FOX APPREHENDED AT HER HOUSE HER
               ACCOUNT OF HIS APPREHENSION GOES TO LONDON INTERVIEW WITH KING</p>
            <p>CHARLES II. LETTER AND ADDRESSES TO HIM AND THE PARLIAMENT INSURRECTION OF THE FIFTH
               MONARCHY</p>
            <p>MEN — SOLICITS AND OBTAINS THE DISCHARGE OF G. FOX</p>
            <p>SEVERAL LETTERS TO THE KING, DUKE OF YORK, ETO.</p>
            <p>VISITS COL. HACKER IN PRISON — LETTER TO HER CHILDREN</p>
            <p>RETURNS TO LONDON ANOTHER INTERVIEW WITH THE KING RESPECTING THE IMPRISONMENT OF
               FRIENDS — RETURNS HOME LETTER TO THE KING LETTER FROM F. HOWGILL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>This devoted woman, soon after her convincenient, felt called to plead the cause of
               the persecuted and oppressed before the rulers of the land. She fear- lessly
               approached the monarchs, and those in power, at various times during the course of
               her life, and laid before them the sufferings of Friends, explained their principles,
               and both by word and writing warned them of the consequences that would be likely to
               fol- low; that the righteous judgments of the Lord would be against such, who were
               persecuting others for conscience' sake. Her services in this way were of the most
               persevering and undaunted kind, and manifested her to be one in spirit and courage
               with her friend, George Fox. About this period, she addressed four letters to the
               Protector, Oliver Cromwell; in the second she bears witness to the spiritual worship
               of God, and to His mighty day, and teaching of His people Himself, and against all
               the outward formal worships which are without the spirit of truth, and of their
               overthrow; and against all the dark forms, and shadows, and false coverings, which he
               had been under; charging him, in the presence of God, not to give way to the men of
               the world, to make laws over the consciences of his ser- vants, and to beware of
               hearkening to evil counsel- lors, that would make a prey upon the people for their
               own ends, lest he brought guilt, plagues, and woe upon himself."</p>
            <p>Ambrose Rigge thus bears testimony to the usefulness and worth of M. Fell, at this
               time, in the church: —</p>
            <p>'Binscombe, in Surry, 9th mo. (11th mo.), 1659.</p>
            <p>Dear Sister —</p>
            <p>Often art thou in my remembrance, in my labour and travel in the vineyard of the
               Lord, which is grown sweet and pleasant to walk in, to the praise of God. I received
               thy lines in Hampshire, when I was in much weakness of body, by which I was much
               strengthened and refreshed; and truly, dear sister, I hope in the Lord, through His
               strength, we shall be clear of all; but our trials are many, especially among false
               brethren, which as for the particulars at present I shall not commit to paper. Oh!
               dear sis- ter, if it were not the living power of God, it could never abide all the
               blows that come against it; but in all this we faint not, but can truly say, our
               strength is renewed every morning — glory to God on high.</p>
            <p>My love is dear to thee, beyond what can be com- mitted to paper, for the truth's
               sake, and thy care over the flock of God; for which God will thee re- ward. So, with
               my dear love to all thy dear chil- dren and servants in the truth, I remain</p>
            <p>Thy dear brother in the labour of the Gospel, Ambrose Rigge."</p>
            <p>In the year 1660, George Fox was apprehended at her house, and committed to Lancaster
               prison. Gough, the historian, relates, that "Margaret Fell considering the forcible
               entry and searching of her house, and arresting of her guest there, as a viola- tion
               of the liberty of the subject, and an injury offered to her, published the following
               brief narrative of his apprehension: </p>
            <p>"To all magistrates, concerning the wrong taking up and imprisoning George Fox at
               Lancaster:</p>
            <p>I do inform the governors of this nation, that Henry Porter, Mayor of Lancaster, sent
               a warrant with four constables to my house, for which he had no authority nor order.
               They searched my house, and apprehended George Fox in it, who was not guilty of the
               breach of any law, or of any offence against any in the nation. And they had him
               taken before the said Henry Porter, there was bail offered, what he would demand for
               his appearance, to answer what could be laid to his charge: but he (contrary to law,
               if he had taken him lawfully) denied to accept of any bail, and clapt him up in close
               prison. After he was in prison a copy of the mittimus was demanded, and which ought
               not to be denied to any prisoner, that so he may see what is laid to his charge; but
               it was denied him, a copy he could not have, only they were suffered to read it over,
               and every thing there charged against him was utterly false; he was not guilty of any
               one charge in it, as will be proved, and manifested to the nation. So let the
               governors consider it. I am concerned in this thing, inasmuch as he was apprehended
               in my house; and if he be guilty, I am so too. So I desire to have this searched
               out.</p>
            <p>Margaret Fell."</p>
            <p>She further determined on a journey to London, to solicit the King's protection, and
               lay the circum- stances of George Fox's imprisonment before him.</p>
            <p>Her narrative proceeds: "In the year 1660, King Charles the Second came into England,
               and within two weeks after, I was moved of the Lord to go to London, to speak to the
               King concerning the truth, and the sufferers for it, for there were then many
               hundreds of our Friends in prison in the three nations of England, Scotland and
               Ireland, which were put in by former powers. I spake often to the King, and wrote
               many papers and letters unto him, and many books were given by our Friends to the
               Parlia- ment, and great service was done at that time. And they were fully informed
               of our peaceable principles and practices. I staid in London at that time one year
               and three months, doing service for the Lord, in visiting Friends' meetings, and
               giving papers and letters to the King and council, whenever there was occasion. And I
               wrote and gave papers and letters to every one of the family several times, viz., to
               the King, to the Dukes of York and Gloucester, and to the Queen mother, to the
               Princess of Orange, and to the Queen of Bohemia. I was moved of the Lord to visit
               them all, and to write unto them, and did give them many books and papers, and did
               lay our principles and doctrines before them, and desired that they let us have
               discourse with their priests, preachers and teachers, and if they could prove us
               erroneous, then let them manifest it; but if our prin- ciples and doctrines be found
               according to the doc- trine of Christ and the Apostles and saints in primi- tive
               times, then let us have our liberty. But we could never get any of them to meet with
               our Friends. Nevertheless they were very quiet, and we had great liberty, and had our
               meetings very peace- ably for the first half year after the King came in, until the
               Fifth Monarchy men raised an insurrection and tumult in the city of London, and then
               all our meetings were disturbed, and Friends taken up; which if they had not been, we
               were informed the King had intended to have given us liberty. For at that very time,
               there was an order signed by the King and council for the Quakers' liberty, and just
               when it should have gone to the press, the Fifth Monarchy men <note n="3">pTheir
                  leader was Thomas Venner, a wne cooper, who, in his little conventicle in Coleman
                  street, warmed his admirers with passionate expectations of a fifth universal
                  monarchy, under the personal reign of King Jesus upon earth, and that the saints
                  were to take the kingdom to themselves. To introduce this imaginary kingdom, they
                  marched out of their meeting-house towards St. Paul's churchyard, on Sunday,
                  January 6, 1661, to the number of about fifty men, well armed, with a resolution
                  to subvert the present government, or die in the attempt. This mad insurrection
                  gave the court a handle for breaking through the late declaration of indulgence,
                  within three months after it was published.' , — Neale.</note> arose, and then our
               Friends were very hardly used, and taken up at their meetings generally, even until
               many prisons throughout the nation were filled with them. Many a time did I go to the
               King about them, who promised me always that they should be set at liberty; we had
               several in the council friendly to us, and we gave many papers to them; and with much
               ado, and attendance at that time, about a quarter of a year after their first taking
               Friends to prison, a general proclamation from the King and council was granted, for
               setting the Quakers at liberty. Then I had free- dom in spirit to return home to
               visit my children and family."</p>
            <p>By the solicitations of M. Fell and Anne Curtis (whose father had suffered death for
               endeavouring to bring in the King), they obtained, at this time, an order for the
               removal of Gr. Fox to Lon- don; he was brought up by habeas corpus, before the court
               of the King's bench; whence the matter was referred ta the King and council. No
               accuser appearing, to criminate him, he was honourably dis- charged, after an
               imprisonment of twenty weeks.</p>
            <p>In Margaret Fell's letters to King Charles the Second, and the Dukes of York and
               Gloucester, soon after their return to the kingdom, she " affectionately warns them
               in the sight of the Lord, the heart- searcher, not to slight the tenders of His love,
               lest they should he hardened; wishing them to consider the goodness of the Lord in
               their several preserva- tions, and restoration out of their troubles, into the
               desired nation, throne and kingdom of their father, and not to take the glory and
               honour unto them- selves; but to let the Lord have the glory thereof, who restored
               them without the shedding of blood, or loss of lives. Acquainting them, how that God
               had a suffering people in the nation, which he hath owned, and will own, and reproved
               and overthrown powers for their sakes whom he has blessed. Signi- fying, also, that
               God had brought the King to the throne to try him, what he and they would do for His
               people, desiring them not to forget His benefits and mercies towards them, and that
               their hands might be kept out of blood and persecution; for when the innocent were
               wronged and persecuted, God will plead for and stand by them," &amp;c. Intimating "
               she was moved of the Lord to write to them beforehand, that they might not be found
               actors against God and his people } also warning them to take heed whom they let come
               near them, lest they should be betrayed by dissemblers, or malicious and temporizing
               spirits who have turned with every power for their own ends."</p>
            <p>In her second letter to the King, she desires that he would " Take care for the
               nation as for his own family, that every one might enjoy his particular right and
               property, and liberty of conscience; seeing God is delivering His people from under
               oppressors, that they may serve Him in freeness of spirit who hath heard the cry of
               the oppressed, and His ears are open to the prayers of the innocent. And that,
               therefore, it would be good for the King, that his ears should not be shut, lest his
               heart should grow hard, that he should not slight what they say unto him, who have a
               testimony for the Lord, and He will bear them witness, when He comes to make in-
               quisition for blood."</p>
            <p>In her third letter to the King, delivered by her own hands, on account of his
               proclamation for bring- ing to trial those who had been instrumental in the death of
               his father, she says: " Since God brought him into this nation in love and mercy
               without shed- ding of blood, or revengings, she wishes that he would consider this
               and show mercy; seeing the Lord saith to the merciful, I will show myself merci- ful,
               but to the froward I will show myself froward. Advising him not to look out at those
               that would in- cense him to revenge, which is not the will of God, nor good for the
               King, whose best way is to show mercy and forgiveness, and commit his cause to the
               God of heaven; and let his heart be inclined unto love and mercy, and to grant
               liberty to the tender consciences of the people; where God's throne is, there no
               plots, or evil intentions, or secret conspira- cies should ever prevail against him,"
               &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The following letter she addressed to the King upon the death of the Duke of
               Gloucester: </p>
            <p>"The Lord is come very near thee. Oh! that thou wouldst consider it, and see His
               hand, that thereby thou mayst learn righteousness, and do justly, love mercy, and
               walk humbly with the Lord, that so thy throne may be established; and that thou
               wouldst see the Lord testifying, that He doth not love pride, vanity and vain glory;
               that now, in the very time of your joy, he hath turned it into mourn- ing. The God of
               power give you to understand His will and mind, that thou mayst make Him thy joy, who
               hath the life and breath of all men in His hand."</p>
            <p>During her sojourn in London, she paid a visit to Col. Hacker, a day or two before
               his execution, he being one of the judges of King Charles the First, and now
               condemned for the part he took in that transaction; he also having been a very
               violent per- secutor of George Fox a few years before. She re- minded him of what he
               had formerly done against the innocent; he remembered it, and said he knew well to
               whom she alluded, and had trouble on him for it.</p>
            <p>It is related of her, that "as a tender mother, being sensible of the exercise and
               trial of her dear children, for her long absence from them, and family, she wrote
               many tender and consolatory letters to them for their encouragement in the truth, and
               satisfaction in the Lord on her behalf; excusing her long absence, as being so deeply
               engaged in His fear to clear her conscience, and for His suffering people's sake.
               Intimating to them how desirable it would be to her to return home to her dear and
               beloved chil- dren, so soon as the Lord pleased to clear her from her long and
               laborious attending, on behalf of His oppressed people."</p>
            <p>The following appears to be one of the letters alluded to: —</p>
            <p>"London, 25th of 8th mo. (10th mo.) 1660.</p>
            <p>My dearly beloved lambs and babes — My love is to you all; and my prayer to the Lord
               is for you all, that in His arm and power you may be kept in the bosom of His love,
               there to be nursed and cherished up to eternal life.</p>
            <p>Gr. F. is now freed, blessed be the Lord God — whose arm and power alone hath done it
               — after he had appeared before the judge who sent for him; then he appeared before
               the Lord Chief Justice of England in his chamber; and the next day he ap- peared
               before them all in open court, in the King's bench; and all this after the King had
               granted an order to set him free; but they would not set him free till he had
               appeared in all these places, to see if any thing would come against him. It was of
               great service for the truth.</p>
            <p>I cannot write at £&gt;resent punctually the time of my return, for I do feel that I
               am not yet clear of this place; but do still wait for the Lord's will and pleasure,
               and in his time to be manifested to me; and may you rest satisfied in that, for there
               is ever- lasting peace, and there you will enjoy me. I do not know how suddenly the
               Lord may give me my free- dom to come home; but when it is, I shall embrace it
               lovingly. Let me hear of the little ones, how it is with them all (you mention little
               of them when you write) ) and my desire is to hear of you all, and of your well being
               in the Lord. It may be that you have heard ere this, that James Xaylor hath finished
               his natural life, and hath laid down this body of earth about three-score miles off
               London.</p>
            <p>So no more, but my love in the Lord Jesus is with you; and as soon as the Lord gives
               me leave, I shall return. The eternal arm of the Almighty be with you. M. F."</p>
            <p>" I staid at home about nine months, and then was moved of the Lord to go to London
               again, not knowing what might be the matter or business that I should go for. At
               Warrington, I met with an act of Parlia- ment made against the Quakers for refusing
               oaths. And when I came to London, I heard the King had gone to meet the Queen, and to
               be married to her at Hampton Court. At this time Friends' meetings at London were
               much troubled with soldiers, pulling Friends out of their meetings, and beating them
               with their muskets and swords; insomuch that several were wounded and bruised by
               them; and many were cast into prison, through which many lost their lives; and all
               this being done to a peaceable people, only for worshipping God, as they in
               conscience were per- suaded. Then I saw the King and Duke of York at Hampton Court,
               and I wrote several letters to them, and therein gave them to understand what
               desperate and dangerous work there was in London; and how the soldiers came in with
               lighted matches, and drawn swords among Friends, when they were met in the fear and
               dread of the Lord to worship Him; and if they would not stop that cruel persecution,
               it was very like that more innocent blood would be shed, and that would witness
               against their actions, and lie upon them, and the nation. And within some cer- tain
               days after, they beat some Friends so cruelly at the Bull and Mouth (meeting) that
               two died thereof.</p>
            <p>The King told me that his soldiers did not trouble us, nor should they, and said the
               city soldiers were not his, and they would do as they pleased with them; and after a
               little time they were more mode- rate, and the King promised me that he would set
               those at liberty that were in prison; and when he brought his Queen to London, he set
               them at liberty.</p>
            <p>And then I came home again, when I had staid about four months in and about
               London."</p>
            <p>The following is the substance of a letter written by her and presented to King
               Charles the Second at Hamp- ton Court, upon the renewal of the persecution under the
               law for " The preventing mischiefs and dangers that may arise "from certain persons
               called Quakers, and others, refusing to take lawful oaths: </p>
            <p>"King Charles — Often has the desire of my heart been to God for thee, that thou
               mightest be preserved out of persecuting the saints and people of God, who hath been
               gracious and long suffering, whilst moderation hath in some measure been kept to
               tender consciences; and certainly that promise that thou mad'st in true simplicity,
               as I do believe, was then in thy heart, that thou wouldst give liberty to tender
               consciences, I am assured it is upon record in the sight of the Lord God; and thou
               art bound unto Him in thy conscience to perform. And therefore is my heart affected
               with the danger that thou in- currest; seeing merciless men are set to work to come
               into the meetings of God's people, with swords, pis- tols and muskets, as if it were
               against thieves or open professed enemies. It is strongly on my heart once more to
               give thee warning to take care of these things, to take a little view of them betimes
               before it is too late. You have made an act against us, for what cause the Lord
               knows, we being harm- less and innocent, and tender towards you, although our
               sufferings have been great; but since you have made a law, it is unreasonable you
               should exceed it in severity. These things, with many more, are laid upon me from the
               Lord to lay before thee, who hath put power in thy hand to see righteousness and
               equity acted in the kingdom; that you may not provoke the Lord is the desire of my
               heart, who am a true and faithful lover of thy soul."</p>
            <p>The following beautiful letter was addressed to her in London by Francis Howgill, who
               subsequently ended his days in prison, for the testimony of the truth: —</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>"Grayrigg, 29th of 7 th mo. (9th mo.), 1661. Dear Margaret —</p>
            <p>In Him, who has become a place of broad rivers and streams unto us, and the portion
               of our cup, and the lot of our inheritance, do I most dearly salute thee.</p>
            <p>The former days are not forgotten by me, nor the years past, when we were all made to
               drink of one cup, and were baptized into the death and suffering of Christ: and were
               made to drink it willingly, knowing it was our portion allotted unto us of the Lord,
               which we could not pass, but must drink thereof. And though it was irksome and
               grievous unto us, when our strength was but small, yet God, out of His infinite love
               and mercy, strengthened us to bear, and to suffer, and to deny that which hid
               immortality and life from us. And He bore us up in His arms, and made us to endure
               with patience the sufferings and the death; that so we might ob- tain the
               resurrection of the dead : which indeed was a blessed time; though for a moment it
               seemed grievous. But now, having obtained the resurrec- tion of the dead, being
               baptized into the resurrection and into the life, more blessedness is known, even
               spiritual blessings, which God hath given us to enjoy in heavenly places in Christ
               Jesus: that like as we suffered one for" another, and one with another, so we might
               be made to rejoice one with another, and for another, and in Him alone; in whom all
               our fresh springs are, and from whom our joy and gladness and consolation spring. He
               hath opened the springs of the great deep, and hath made life spring up, whereby His
               little ones are refreshed, and the young men strengthened, and the ancient and
               honourable confirmed and established. Holy and revered be His name forevermore, who
               is exalting His glorious mountain above the top of all the earth; and making
               Jerusalem the praise and glory and admiration of the whole earth. And let me tell
               thee, I am no more weary than the first day the sickle was put into the harvest; when
               we went out sowing the seed weeping and in tears: but seeing sheaves brought home,
               and full loads into the barn, and full draughts caught in the net, it hath made me
               look beyond fainting — blessed be the Lord.</p>
            <p>I am glad thou stay est so long in that city (London), in which we have had many a
               burden and weary day: but that fruit is brought forth unto God, plenteously
               countervails all, and makes me forget travail. I have been northward in Northum-
               berland, Bishoprick, and upon the east sea, and back to York: truly the garden for
               the most part is very pleasant, and gives a goodly smell, now when the south wind
               blows upon it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dearly farewell in the holy covenant of life,</salute>
               <signed>Francis Howgill."</signed></closer>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg34">
            <p>CHAPTER III. 1662-1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterSubtitle">
            <p>PERFORMS A RELIGIOUS VISIT IN SEVERAL COUNTIES — MEETS WITH GEORGE FOX — THEIR ARREST
               AND IMPRISONMENT IN LANCASTER CASTLE HER TRIAL — TESTIMONY AGAINST</p>
            <p>SWEARING — PREMUNIRED, AND REMANDED TO PRISON — LETTER FROM HER DAUGHTER — LETTER TO
               HER SON-IN-LAW AND WIFE — INEFFECTUAL EFFORTS TO OBTAIN HER RELEASE</p>
            <p>THE HARDSHIPS AND PRIVATIONS OF HER IMPRISONMENT</p>
            <p>EXPOSTULATORY LETTER TO THE KING — DESCRIPTION OF LANCASTER CASTLE — HER RELEASE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>In the year 1663, in company with one of her daughters, she performed a religious
               journey of about one thousand miles, visiting Friends in Somer- setshire, Devonshire
               and Dorsetshire to Bristol, from thence to Yorkshire, into Northumberland and West-
               moreland. In the course of their travels they met with George Fox, who accompanied
               them home, soon after which he was arrested and committed to Lan- caster castle.</p>
            <p>She says: " About a month after the same justices sent for me to Ulverston, and when
               I came there they asked me several questions, and seemed to be offended at me for
               keeping a meeting at my house, and said they would tender me the oath of allegiance.
               I answered they knew I could not swear, and why should they send for me from my own
               house, where I was about my lawful occasions, to ensnare me? What had I done? They
               said if I would not keep meet- ings at my house, they would not tender me the oath. I
               told them I should not deny my faith and principles for any thing they could do unto
               me; and whilst it pleased the Lord to let me have a house, I would endeavour to
               worship him in it. So they caused the oath to be read, and tendered it unto me; and I
               refused it, telling them, I could not take any oath for conscience' sake, Christ
               Jesus having forbid it. They then made a mittimus and commit- ted me prisoner to
               Lancaster Castle, and there George Fox and I remained in prison until the next
               assizes; and then they indicted us upon the statute for denying the oath of
               allegiance; for they tendered it to us both again at the assizes; but they said to
               me, if I would not keep a meeting at my house, I should be set at liberty. But I
               answered the judge that I rather chose a prison for obeying God, than my liberty for
               obeying men contrary to my conscience. So we were called several times before them at
               that assizes, and the indictments were found against us. The next assizes we came to
               trial, and George Fox's indictment was found to be dated wrong, both in the day of
               the month, and in the year of the King's reign, so that it was quashed; but mine they
               would not allow the errors that were found in it to make it void, although there were
               several; so they passed the sentence of premunire upon me, which was, that I should
               be out of the King's protection, and forfeit all my estate, real and personal, to the
               King, and be imprisoned for life. But the great God of heaven and earth so supported
               my spirit under this severe sen- tence, that I was not terrified, but gave this
               answer to Judge Turner, who gave this sentence, Although 1 am out of the King's
               protection, yet I am not out of the protection of the Almighty God: so there I re-
               mained in prison twenty months, before I could get so much favour of the sheriff, as
               to go to my own house; which then I did for a little time, and re- turned to prison
               again."</p>
            <p>Whilst before the judges, she bore this clear and noble testimony against swearing,
               and vindicated herself from all cause of offence: —</p>
            <p>"I am here this day upon the account of my con- science, and not for any evil, or
               wrong done to any man, but for obeying Christ's doctrine and com- mands, who hath
               said in the Scriptures: i That God is a spirit, and that His worship is in spirit and
               truth :' and for keeping meetings in the unity of this spirit. Now you profess
               yourselves to be Chris- tians, and you own the Scriptures to be true; and for the
               obedience of the plain words of Scripture, and for the testimony of my conscience, am
               I here.</p>
            <p>I say this to the oath, as I have said in this place before now, Christ Jesus has
               commanded me not to swear at all; and that is the only cause and no other; the
               righteous Judge of heaven and earth knows, before whose throne of jus- tice you must
               all appear one day; and His eye sees us all, and beholds us at this present time, and
               hears and sees all our words and actions: and therefore every one ought to be
               serious; for the place of judgment is weighty. And this I do testify to you here,
               where the Lord's eye beholds us all, that for the matter or substance of the oath,
               and the end for which it was intended, I do own one part and deny the other. That is
               to say, I do own truth, and faithfulness, and obedience to the King, in all his just
               and lawful demands and commands. I do also deny all plottings and contrivings against
               the King, and all Popish supremacy, and conspiracy: and I can no more transgress
               against King Charles in these things, than I can disobey Christ Jesus' commands. And
               by the same power, and by virtue of the same word, which has commanded not to swear
               at all, the same doth bind me in my conscience, that I can neither plot nor contrive
               against the King, nor do him nor any man upon the earth any wrong and I do not deny
               this oath only, because it is the oath of allegiance; but I deny it, because it is an
               oath, and because Christ Jesus has said, Swear not at all, neither hy heaven, nor hy
               earth, nor any other oath; and if I might gain the whole world for swear- ing of an
               oath, I could not 5 and whatever I have to lose this day, for not swearing, I am
               ready to offer up."</p>
            <p>One of the justices observed: "Mrs. Fell, you may with a good conscience put in
               security to have no more meetings at your house, if you cannot take the oath."</p>
            <p>"Wilt thou make it good," said she, "that I may with a safe conscience make an
               engagement to for- bear meetings, for fear of losing my liberty and estate? Wilt not
               thou and all here judge me, that it was for saving my estate and liberty that I did
               it? And should I not, in this, deny my testimony; and would not this defile my
               conscience?"</p>
            <p>Considerable effort was made by some of her friends in London to prevent the sentence
               of premunire being passed upon her, and some of her children applied to the King in
               her behalf; but without any effect. The following is a letter from one of her
               daughters on the subject: —</p>
         </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>"Mile End Green, near London, 1 27th 4th mo., 1664. </p>
               <p>Endeared and tender-hearted Mother: —</p>
               <p>My duty and very dear love is freely given and remembered unto thee, as also my
                  very dear love is to dear George Fox. This is chiefly to let thee understand that
                  yesterday sister and I went to White Hall; where we spoke to the King, and told
                  him if he would please to signify something to the judges, before they went their
                  circuit, to release you; other- wise it would be past, for the time drew very near
                  of the assizes. He said he would release you, if we would promise you would not go
                  to meetings. Sister said we could make no such engagement; for the meeting had
                  been kept many years, and never had done any harm. He said, cannot your mother
                  keep within her own family, as she may have five persons present, but she must
                  have such tumultuous meet- ings? We said she hath no such meetings, they are only
                  her neighbors that come. The King said there were some Quakers in the last plot.
                  Sister said that could not be proved. He said he had letters about it, and their
                  names. So Chifines <note n="4"> One of the pages.</note> bid us come on the fourth
                  day; and we intend to go to-morrow. I was there about a week since, and told the
                  King, that now the assizes drew very near, if he did not do something for thee,
                  they would run thee into a premunire, and get thy estate from thee and thy
                  children; and I desired him to take it into considera- tion. He was then very
                  loving to me, and said he would take it into consideration; and he said, ' they
                  shall not have her estate from her :' he took me by the hand as soon as he came
                  near me. I also spoke to Prince Rupert, and desired him to put the King in mind of
                  it: and he said he would do what he could in it; and went then to the King and
                  spoke to him. Prince Rupert hath always been very loving to Friends ) and hath
                  often spoken to the King about you.</p>
               <p>Sister gives the renewed remembrance of her entire love to thee and dear Gr. F.,
                  as also doth my brother; I suppose sisters Isabel and Sarah will be gone: remember
                  me to sisters Susanna and Rachel.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>I am thy dutiful and obedient daughter,</salute>
                  <signed>Mary Fell."</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterSection">
               <p>The following letter, written by M. Fell, when in prison, to her son-in-law, John
                  Rouse, and his wife, after she had been premunired, shows, that having been deeply
                  taught in the school of Christ, and strengthened by Him, she had learned, like the
                  Apostle Paul, that in whatsoever state she found herself, therewith to be content:
                  —</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>"Lancaster Castle, 1st 8th mo. (10th mo.*), 1664.</p>
               <p>"As I have often said to thee, give up to be crossed; that is the way to please
                  the Lord, and to follow Him in His own will and way, whose way is the best. Let
                  nothing enter thy mind concerning anything about me, for I am well contented in
                  the work of the Lord. I know your care and tenderness were not wanting to Friends;
                  and so be all satisfied in the will of the Lord God. I hope in the Lord that you
                  are all together, ere this come to you. Be all satisfied and content with the will
                  of the Lord; and let neither murmuring nor repining enter any of your minds; and
                  let not sorrow fill your hearts, for we have all cause to rejoice in the Lord
                  evermore, and I most of all.</p>
               <p>Colonel Kirby causes our bonds to be . renewed and straightened more and more: and
                  they lock up G. F. under pretence of an order that should come from London. Get
                  this enclosed letter of G. F/s sent to Gilbert Latey, that G. Whitehead and they
                  may draw out what they see convenient.</p>
               <closer><signed>Margaret Fell."</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterSection">
               <p>Some attempts were afterwards made to obtain her release, or at least some
                  mitigation of the rigours of her imprisonment, but with no better success. Gril-
                  berty Latey, in, one of his letters, giving an account of an interview he had with
                  Lord D'Aubigny on her behalf, says: " That neither the King nor chancellor would
                  do anything at all for us. Neither could any man be heard to speak for us. Then I
                  told him of the unjustness of thy imprisonment, and of the bad- ness of the jury,
                  and its being contrary to law, and that thou desired nothing but a fair prison,
                  and that the thieves and murderers had more liberty than thee, and that thou wast
                  locked up in a bad room, and Friends not suffered to come to speak to thee; and I
                  told him I had a paper of it, and desired that he would hand it. He told me he was
                  sorry with all his heart, but he would tell me no lie; he was sure nothing could
                  be done, and he believed they did it on purpose to vex us; and so I parted with
                  him; for he said he could do nothing, for all the clergy were against us, and
                  nothing could be done at all, neither did he care to meddle with the paper at all;
                  so I was fain to leave him."</p>
               <p>Gough, the historian, remarks: " Such rigorous imprisonment as these people,
                  particularly George Fox and Margaret Fell, were subject to, being in smoky rooms,
                  in such bad condition that the rain came in upon them in abundance, was more than
                  suf- ficient punishment for petty criminals, and an evi- dence of the unfeeling
                  malice of their persecutors needlessly to expose Margaret Fell in particular to
                  such hardships, a woman of estate, the widow of a judge, and a man of consequence
                  in the country, who had been used to comfortable accommodations in her own house,
                  and was every way on a level with her persecutors, except the possession of power.
                  But all the hardships she suffered, in being arbitrarily forced from her home and
                  family, without cause or crimina- tion, and hurried to this dismal jail, was not a
                  suffi- cient gratification of the groundless enmity of these magistrates, until
                  they went the furthest lengths they could go, by prosecuting her to a premunire,
                  realizing the proverb, summum jus, summa injuria: the execution of perverted law
                  is accumulated injury" She earnestly expostulated with the King, on the injustice
                  of the law authorizing the banishment of Friends, reminding him of her former
                  interview with him, and the rigours of her own imprisonment, in a letter addressed
                  to him u from my prison at Lancas- ter Castle, the 6th day of the 6th month,
                  1666," some, extracts from which are here inserted:</p>
               <p>"King Charles: —</p>
               <p>I desire thee to read this over, which may be for thy satisfaction and profit.</p>
               <p>In the fear of the Lord God stand still, and con- sider what thou and you have
                  been doing these six years, since the Lord brought you peaceably into this realm,
                  and made you rulers over this people. The righteous eye of the Almighty hath been
                  over you, and hath seen all your doings and actions.</p>
               <p>What laws have you made or changed, save such as have laid oppression and bondage
                  on the con- sciences of Grod's people, and that of no less penalty than banishment
                  out of their native country f The greatest crime that you could find with the
                  people of God was, that they obeyed and worshipped Christ Jesus: so that the
                  greatest stroke that hath appeared of your justice hath been upon such as you
                  counted offenders for worshipping of God, insomuch that several of your judges of
                  the land have several times said, in open court, to any that did confess they met
                  to worship the Lord God, that that was crime enough, whereby they could proceed to
                  banishment. And when it was asked in open court, whether it was now become a
                  transgression or a crime in England to wor- ship God? He that was then Chief
                  Justice of Eng- land answered: i Yes, yes/ Oh ! wonderful, let this be chronicled
                  in England for after ages, that all magistrates may dread and fear so to affront
                  the Almighty; except they dare say they are stronger than he.</p>
               <p>And all this hath been without any just cause given at any time by that people,
                  which was the ob- ject of this law; so that men, that had but the least measure of
                  righteousness and equity, could never have proceeded on to have inflicted such a
                  height of punishment, without some just ground.</p>
               <p>And all that was ever pretended, was but suspi- cion, which can never be
                  paralleled; to be prose-- cuted to such a height of suffering without a just
                  ground given, although occasion hath been con- tinually sought and watched for,
                  but never found; but the Lord has preserved His people innocent and harmless; and
                  therefore is He engaged to plead their cause, into whose hand it is wholly given
                  and committed.</p>
               <p>I desire you also to consider seriously, in the fear of the Lord, what effects and
                  fruits these things have brought forth.</p>
               <p>I believe it hath brought hundreds of God's people to their graves; it hath also
                  rendered this realm, and the governors of it, cruel, in the eyes of all people,
                  both within its own body, and in other nations; besides the guilt of innocent
                  blood lies upon this kingdom.</p>
               <p>Since which time, the Lord in His judgment hath taken many thousands of its people
                  away by His two judgments, pestilence and sword.</p>
               <p>And before any of this was, when you first entered into this kingdom, I was sent
                  of the Lord to you, to inform you truly of the state and condition of our people;
                  and when I came before thee, King, I told thee I was come to thee on behalf of an
                  inno- cent, harmless, peaceable people; which words I would then, and ever since,
                  and should at this day seal with my blood, if I were put to it. And thy answer was
                  to me, if they he peaceable they shall he protected.</p>
               <p>I also wrote to thee several times concerning our faith and principles, how that
                  we could not swear for conscience' sake; neither could we take up arms, nor plot,
                  nor contrive to do any man wrong nor injury, much less the King. I also told you,
                  that we must worship God, for God required it of us.</p>
               <p>We did likewise give you many of our books, which contained our faith, and
                  principles and doc- trine, that thereby we might be tried by the Scrip- tures of
                  Truth (which all of you do profess), whether our principles were erroneous or no;
                  and to that pur- pose we gave our books to the King and Parliament, and to the
                  bishops and ministers, both ecclesiastical and civil. All this, with much more, I
                  wrote to thee, and warned thee of (I can truly say in the fear of the Lord), in
                  much love and tenderness to thee. And now I may say unto thee, for which of these
                  things hast thou kept me in prison three long win- ters, in a place not fit for
                  people to lie in; sometimes for wind, and storm, and rain, and sometimes for
                  smoke; so that it is much that I am alive, but that the power and goodness of Grod
                  hath been with me. I was kept a year and seven months in this prison, before I was
                  suffered to see the house that was mine, or children or family, except they came
                  to me over two dangerous sands in the cold winter, when they came with much danger
                  of their lives, but since the last assizes I have had a little more respect from
                  this sheriff, than formerly from others. And in all this I am very well satisfied;
                  and praise the Lord, who counts me worthy to suffer for His sake.</p>
               <p>And now after all my sufferings, in the same love that I visited thee in the
                  beginning, I desire thee once more to fear the Lord God, by whom Kings rule, and
                  Princes decree justice; ivho sets up one, and puMs down another, at His
                  pleasure.</p>
               <p>And let not the guilt of the burthen of the breach of that word that passed from
                  thee at Breda, lie upon thy conscience, but as thou promised when thou wast in
                  distress, and also renewed it many times since, that thou wouldst give liberty to
                  tender consciences; in the fear of the Lord perform it, and purge thy conscience
                  of it; and hearken not to wicked counsel- lors, that have stopped it in thee all
                  this time; for they will bear none of thy burden for thee, when the Lord pleads
                  for breach of covenant with Him and His people; I know it hath been often in thy
                  heart to perform it, and thou hast seen what fruit the want of it hath brought
                  forth. So if thou lovest thy eter- nal peace and comfort with the Lord, try what
                  the performance of it will bring forth, thou wilt thereby see thou hast hearkened
                  to wrong counsellors. And every mortal man hath but a moment in this life, either
                  to serve, fear and honour the Lord, and therein to receive mercy from Him; or else
                  to transgress, sin, disobey, and dishonour Him, and receive the judgment of
                  eternal misery.</p>
               <p>So none of you know how long, or how short your day may be; therefore fear not
                  man, that can kill the body; but fear the Lord, who, when he hath killed the body,
                  can cast the soul and body into hell; yea, I say unto you fear Him.</p>
               <p>From a true lover of all your souls (though a suf- ferer by you), and the desire
                  of my heart is, that you may take these things into consideration betime, be- fore
                  it be too late, and set open the prison doors, and let the innocent go free, and
                  that will take part of the burden and guilt off you, lest the door of mercy be
                  shut against you."</p>

               <p>Lancaster Castle, the prison of Margaret Fell, in its present forni, was founded
                  by John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster, in the 14th century. This castle and its
                  predecessor have been noted strongholds, fa- mous in British history from the time
                  of the Romans to the days of Cromwell and the Pretender. A recent writer thus
                  describes the castle, and the room occu- pied by George Fox: " He who penetrates
                  within the enclosure of the castle will wonder at the kind of life which kings and
                  princes must have led in the days of its erection. Here are the same rooms of John
                  of Gaunt, visited sometimes by his father, Edward the Third — small, stately,
                  strong apartments, having few windows in the exterior, and these narrowed to the
                  smallest possible dimensions — well fitted to serve as the prisons they have since
                  become. Fox's room was in the donjon, and the window of what was his resi- dence
                  during many long, dreary months is conspicu- ous over the greater part of the
                  ancient town. It was evidently, at one period, a room of considerable size, but in
                  Fox's day it was old and ruinous. He could scarcely walk across his apartment,
                  because of the dilapidated state of the floor. The smoke that came from the other
                  prisons was so dense, that sometimes a burning candle was scarcely visible, and he
                  was in imminent danger of being choked; and the turnkey was with difficulty
                  persuaded to unlock one of the upper doors, in order to let out the smoke. In wet
                  weather it rained upon his bed. The inconveniences of his prison affected Fox to
                  such a degree, during a cold and prolonged winter, that his body became swollen,
                  and his limbs benumbed. When he was brought up at the March assizes, 1665, he was
                  so weak that he could scarcely stand or move."</p>
               <p>"Nor were Fox's friends in this neighbourhood allowed to escape. Many of his
                  followers, and amongst them Margaret Fell, at whose house he had been ap-
                  prehended, were also confined in the castle, where an apartment exists, still
                  called the Quaker's room, be- cause it was the scene of the sufferings of many of
                  these oppressed and unresisting Christians." <note n="5"> At one time there were
                     4500 Friends in prison in Eng- land and Wales. In 1662, 20 died in different
                     prisons in London, and 7 more after their liberation, from ill treat- ment. In
                     1664, 25 died; and in 1665, 52 more. The num- ber that perished in this way
                     throughout the whole kingdom amounted to 369. For a full account of the
                     cruelties prac- tised against the early Friends, the reader is referred to two
                     folio volumes entitled "Besse's Sufferings"</note></p>
               <p>Having endured an imprisonment of about four years, M. Fell was at length set at
                  liberty by an order of the King and council, in the year 1668.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg49">
               <p>CHAPTER IV. 1668-1690.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterSubtitle">
               <p>VISITS IMPRISONED FRIENDS — HER MARRIAGE WITH GEORGE FOX AT BRISTOL AGAIN
                  IMPRISONED ON THE OLD PREMUNIRE HER HUSBAND AND TWO OF HER CHILDREN OBTAIN</p>
               <p>AN ORDER FOR HER DISCHARGE WHICH IS DISREGARDED</p>
               <p>SHE OBTAINS A FREE DISCHARGE UNDER THE GREAT SEAL,</p>
               <p>RELEASING HER AND HER ESTATE FROM THE PREMUNIRE</p>
               <p>VISITS LONDON TO TAKE LEAVE OF HER HUSBAND, WHO GOES TO AMERICA HIS RETURN, AND
                  IMPRISONMENT IN WOR- CESTER JAIL — HE IS PREMUNIRED HER EFFORTS IN HIS BEHALF HIS
                  RELEASE, AND RETURN TO SWARTHMORE</p>
               <p>LETTER TO THOMAS LOWER RETURNS TO LONDON — VISITS</p>
               <p>THE KING HIS DEATH INTERVIEW WITH KING JAMES</p>
               <p>FRESH IMPRISONMENT — EPISTLE TO WOMEN FRIENDS OF LONDON.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <p>Shortly after her release, "she was moved of the Lord" to make an extended journey
                  through many of the counties of England, visiting most of the Friends that were
                  imprisoned in the nation, and spending a number of weeks in London and
                  Bristol.</p>
               <p>It was on her return from this visit that she again met with George Fox, and
                  remarks: </p>
               <p>"It was eleven years after my former husband's decease; and Gr. Fox being then
                  returned from visit- ing Friends in Ireland; at Bristol he declared his intentions
                  of marriage with me; and there was also our marriage solemnized, in a public
                  meeting of many Friends, who were our witnesses." </p>

               <p>George Fox, in his journal, gives the following re- lation of his marriage. Before
                  proceeding therein he was careful that the rights of her children should not
                  suffer, and had their free consent, for, said he, " I would have all things done
                  plainly, for I sought not any advantage to myself." <note n="6">In confirmation of
                     this, and showing the justice and conscientiousness that characterized George
                     Fox, in regard to property, and of his opinions being in advance of those then
                     prevailing on the subject, the following circumstance, related in his journal,
                     will serve to illustrate. Being pro- secuted for tithes against his wife's
                     estate at Swarth- more, he and William Mead, her son-in-law, appeared be- fore
                     the court, "when," he says, " William Mead told the judges that I had engaged
                     never to meddle with my wife's estate. The judges would hardly believe that any
                     man would do so; whereupon he showed them the writing under my hand and seal;
                     at which they wondered." — Fox's Jour- nal, vol. ii. p. 302.</note></p>
               <p>"I had seen from the Lord a considerable time before, that I should take Margaret
                  Fell to be my wife; and when I first mentioned it to her, she felt the answer of
                  life from God thereunto. But though the Lord had opened this thing to me, yet I
                  had not received a command from Him for the accomplishing of it then. Wherefore I
                  let the thing rest, and went on in the work and service of the Lord, according as
                  he led me; travelling in this nation and Ireland. But now being at Bristol, and
                  finding Margaret Fell there, it opened in me from the Lord that the thing should
                  be accomplished. And so our intention of marriage was laid before Friends, both
                  privately and publicly, to their full satisfaction, many of whom gave testimony
                  that it was of God. Afterwards a meeting being appointed on purpose for the
                  accomplishing thereof, in the public meeting-house at Broad Mead, in Bristol, we
                  took each other in mar- riage ) and the Lord joined us together in honourable
                  marriage, in the everlasting covenant and immortal Seed of life." <note n="7"
                        ><p>The following is a copy of her marriage certificate: — " These are to
                        signify unto all whom this may concern that on the eighteenth day of the
                        eighth month in the year one thousand, six hundred sixty nine, George Fox
                        and Mar- garett ffell propounded their intentions of joininge together in
                        the honourable marriage, in the covenant of God in Mens meetinge, at
                        Broadmead, within the Citty of Bristoll (hav- ing before made mention of
                        such their intentions to several ffriends,) on the behalf of which there
                        were several testimo- nies given, both by the children and relations of the
                        said Margarett, then present, and several others, in the power of the Lord,
                        both of men and women, declaring their satis- faction, and approbation of
                        their declared intention of mar- riage. And likewise at another meetinge
                        both of men and women, at the place aforesaide, on the twenty first day of
                        the month and year aforesaide, the said George Fox and Mar- garett ffell did
                        againe publish their intention of joininge to- gether in the honourable
                        marriage in the covenant of God, unto which, there were againe many livinge
                        testimonies borne by the relations and ffriends then present, both of Men
                        and Women. And the same intentions of Marriage beinge againe published by
                        Dennis Hollister at our public meetinge-place aforesaide, on the two and
                        twentyeth day of the month and year aforesaide, and then againe, a public
                        testimony was given to the same, that it was of God who had brought it to
                        passe. </p>
                     <p>And for the full accomplishment of the aforesaide propo- sal, and approved
                        intention, at a publicke meetinge both of men and women ffriends, appointed
                        on purpose for the same thinge, at the place aforesaide, and on the twenty
                        seventh day of the month and year aforesaide, according to the law and
                        ordinance of God, and the example and good order of His people, mentioned in
                        the Scriptures of Truth, who tooke each other before witnesses, and the
                        Elders of the people, as Laban appointed a meetinge, at the marriage of
                        Jacob, and as a meetinge was appointed on purpose, when Boaz and Ruth tooke
                        each other, and also as it was in Canaan, where Christ and his disciples
                        went to a marriage. The saide George Fox did solemnly, in the presence of
                        God, and us his people, declare that he tooke the saide Margarett ffell in
                        the everlasting power and covenent of God which is from everlasting to
                        everlasting, and in the honourable mar- riage, to be his bride, and his
                        wife. And likewise the saide Margarett did solemnly declare that, in the
                        everlastinge power of the mighty God, and in the unalterable word, and in
                        the presence of God, His Angells and his holy assembly, she tooke the saide
                        George Fox to be her husband, unto which marriage, many livinge testimonies
                        were borne in the sence of the power and presence of the livinge God, mani-
                        fested in the said assembly; of which, we, whose names are here subscribed
                        are witnesses.</p>
                     <p>Signed by 92 men and women Friends." — Friends' Re- view, vol. i. p.
                        270.</p></note></p>

               <p>Her narrative proceeds: "Soon after I came home, there came another order to cast
                  me into prison again; and the sheriff of Lancashire sent his bailiff, and pulled
                  me out of my own house, and had me to prison at Lancaster Castle, where I
                  continued a whole year; and most of that time I was sick and weakly. And after
                  some time my husband endeavoured to get me out of prison; and a discharge at last
                  was got, under the great seal, and I was set at -liberty."</p>
               <p>This imprisonment was upon the old premunire, from which she had been discharged
                  the year before. As soon as George Fox reached London after hear- ing of her fresh
                  incarceration, he sent Mary Lower and Sarah Fell (her children) to the King, to
                  strive to obtain an order for her discharge, which with some difficulty was
                  procured. They carried it to Lan- caster, together with the following letter from
                  G. Fox:— </p>
               <p>"My dear heart in the truth and life, that changeth not: —</p>
               <p>It was upon me that Mary Lower and Sarah should go to the King concerning thy
                  imprisonment; and to Kirby, that the power of the Lord might appear over them all
                  in thy deliverance. They went; and then they thought to have come down; but it was
                  upon me to stay them a little longer, that they might follow the business till it
                  was effected, which it now is and is here sent. The late declara- tion of mine has
                  been very serviceable, people being generally satisfied with it.</p>
               <p>So no more but my love in the Holy Seed, George Fox."</p>
               <p>This second intimation of the King's will and pleasure respecting her, was
                  presented to the sheriff by her two daughters; but her old enemies found means, by
                  some informality in the document, to evade even this command.</p>
               <p>Her husband therefore renewed his solicitations for her release; which was at
                  length effected by means of Martha Fisher and another female Friend, who obtained
                  a second interview with the King, and informed him of all their difficulties. The
                  King then granted a free discharge under the great seal, and released both her,
                  and her estate from the penalties of the sentence of premunire, under which she
                  had been suffering for more than five years.</p>
               <p>The condescending interference of King Charles, in behalf of Margaret Fox shows,
                  that he was averse to these violent measures against his peaceable non- conforming
                  subjects, and that he would probably have adhered to his proclamation from Breda,
                  promising religious toleration, had he not been driven by his necessities, and
                  extravagance, to concede these arbi- trary measures to the high church party, for
                  the sake of obtaining supplies.</p>
               <p>She went up to London soon after, to take leave of her husband, then about
                  embarking for America. He was absent two years; she again met him, on his return,
                  at Bristol, whence they proceeded to Lon- don, and staid there some time, when
                  they took leave of their friends, and proceeded homewards, in company with her
                  daughter Rachel, stopping at Bickmansworth, on a visit to William Penn and his
                  family, where they were joined by her son-in-law, Thomas Lower. Upon leaving
                  Bickmansworth, they continued their journey through Oxfordshire, visiting Friends'
                  meetings as they proceeded, and at Treding- ton, in Worcestshire, they attended a
                  meeting of about two hundred persons, held in a barn; the meet- ing having quietly
                  dispersed, and they haying retired into the house of John Halford, George Fox and
                  Thomas Lower were arrested and committed to Wor- cester jail: Gr. Fox being
                  afterwards premunired by the court there, and continued in confinement, she went
                  to him, and had a conference with the judges, and also with the King, endeavouring
                  to obtain his release. The case was subsequently removed by habeas corpus to the
                  King's bench bar, where Judge Hale pronounced the indictment illegal and void, and
                  he was discharged. They returned together to Swarthmore, he being much weakened in
                  body, his health having suffered severely in consequence of his long imprisonment.
                  He continued at home about one and twenty months, before he was sufficiently
                  recovered to resume his travels, being the longest pe- riod he remained with his
                  wife since their marriage.</p>
               <p>Persecution and distraints still continued, whereby Friends were much distressed
                  and impoverished. She says, in speaking of the difficulties they encoun- tered in
                  these respects: —</p>
               <p>"When my husband was at London, it being a time of great persecution by informers,
                  the justices of our country were very severe, and much bent against me, because I
                  kept a meeting at Swarthmore Hall; so they did not fine the house as his, he being
                  absent, but as mine; and fined me £20 for the house, and £20 for speaking in the
                  meeting; and the second time £40 for speaking; and also other Friends for
                  speaking, £20 for the first, and £40 for the second time: those that were not
                  able, they fined others for them, and made great spoil among Friends, by
                  distraining their goods, sometimes for less than half the value; they took thirty
                  head of cattle from me. Their intentions were to ruin and weary us out, and enrich
                  themselves ; but the Lord prevented them."</p>
               <p>Her son-in-law, Thomas Lower, being premunired and imprisoned, she wrote him the
                  subjoined com- forting letter. He was u a physician of London," says Besse, " and
                  visiting George Fox when he was imprisoned in Cornwall, asked him many questions
                  concerning religion, and received such clear answers from Gr. Fox, that he said i
                  his words were as a flash of lightning, they ran so through him/ adding, i he had
                  never met with a man of such wisdom and pene- tration in his life/ By these means
                  he became fully convinced of the doctrine of truth, which he after- wards made a
                  public profession of." He subse- quently married Mary Fell.</p>
               <p>"To Thomas Lower and his fellow-sufferers for the testimony of Jesus, when they
                  were premunired, and prisoners in Lauceston Jail: —</p>
               <p>Dear Son Lower: —</p>
               <p>In the dear and precious blessed unity of the eternal Spirit, and fellowship of
                  the gospel of peace, in this is my heart and souls love remembered unto thee, and
                  to all thy dear brethren and fellow-prisoners with thee, that suffer for the
                  testimony of Jesus, my soul's desire is to the powerful God for you all, that you
                  may be more than conquerors in Christ Jesus, who is the great King, and Lord over
                  all, and hath all power in heaven and earth in His hands, and all the inhabitants
                  of the earth are but as grasshoppers before Him; and therefore with hearts and
                  courage may His servants and children suffer for Him, with- out fear or fainting,
                  under those that have but power over the outward man. The Lord preserve you in the
                  dominion over them all; and I am glad to hear in every letter that comes from
                  thee, that ye are well satisfied and content. And I know certainly, the Lord will
                  never be wanting to you, as ye keep faith- ful and true, and single-hearted to
                  Him; His eye beholds and sees all that His and your enemies can do unto you, and a
                  just and righteous reward from Him they will surely receive.</p>
               <p>And my dear love is unto thee, in that which never changes, which gives peace, and
                  content, and faith to look over that which changes.</p>
               <p>Thy dear mother in the Lord,</p>
               <p>M. Fox.</p>
               <p>Swarthmore, 28th of 7th mo., 1683/'</p>
               <p> I was moved of the Lord to go to London, in the seventieth year of my age; and
                  the word was in me, that as I had gone to King Charles, when he first came into
                  England, so I should go, and bear to him my last testimony, and let him know how
                  they did abuse us, to enrich themselves: a paper was drawn up, to give a true and
                  certain account how they dealt with me, and other Friends. It was upon my mind, to
                  go first unto the Duke of York; and I wrote a short paper to him, to acquaint him,
                  that as he had sometimes formerly spoke in my behalf to the King, my request was,
                  that he would now do the like for me, or words to that effect. I went with this
                  paper to James' house; and after long waiting, I got to speak to him. But some let
                  him know, that it was I that had been with him and his brother, soon after they
                  came into England. I gave him my little paper, and asked him if he did not
                  remember me? He said, I do remember you. Then I desired him to speak to the King
                  for us, for we were under great sufferings, and our persecutors were so severe,
                  that it looked as if they intended to make a prey upon us; he said he could not
                  help, but he would speak to the King. The next day, with much ado, I got to the
                  King, and had my great paper, which was the relation of our sufferings, to present
                  to him; but he was so rough and angry, that he would not take it; but I gave
                  several copies to his nobles. Afterwards I went to Judge Jeffreys, and told him of
                  our suffer- ings; for he had been in the North country with us, a little before,
                  and he told me we might speak to the King. I answered it was very hard to get to
                  the King; he said, i give me a paper, and I will speak to him;' but said, 'your
                  papers are too long, give me a short one, and I will speak to him: so I wrote a
                  little paper from myself, to this effect: —</p>

               <p>King Charles: — Thou and thy magistrates put very great and cruel sufferings upon
                  us; but this I must say unto thee, if you make our sufferings to death itself, we
                  shall not, nor dare not, but confess Christ Jesus before men, lest He should deny
                  us be- fore His Father which is in heaven."</p>
               <p>"There were some more words, but this was the substance: Jeffreys read it, and
                  said he would give it him; we gave papers to several of those that waited on him,
                  and they gave us some encouragement, that we should be helped; so we expected and
                  waited for it. About a week or two after, in the beginning of the 12th month,
                  George Whitehead and I were going to one of the lords, who had promised George
                  that he would speak to the King for us: we went to his lodgings early in the
                  morning, thinking to speak with him before he went out; but his servants told us
                  he was not within, being gone to the King, who was not well. Then we came forth
                  into Whitehall court; but all the gates were shut, that we could not get forth. So
                  we waited, and walked up and down; and several came from the King, and said, he
                  could not stand; others said, he could not speak. Then, after some hours waiting,
                  we got through Scotland-yard, and came away; the King continued sick until the
                  sixth day after, and then he died. So this confirmed that word which God put into
                  my heart, that I was sent to hear my last testimony to the King"</p>
               <p>"Then James, Duke of York, was proclaimed King, and about two weeks after, I went
                  to him, and gave hirn a paper to this effect: —</p>
               <p>King James — I have waited here some months, until this change is come, and now I
                  would return home; but I cannot live 'peaceably there, except I have a word from
                  thee, to give a check to my persecutors.</p>
               <p>I spoke to him to the same purpose. He said unto me, go home, go home. So after a
                  few weeks I went home.</p>
               <p>And a little while after, William Kirby, a justice, one of our greatest
                  persecutors, met with my son-in- law, Daniel Abraham, upon the road, and said to
                  him, tell your mother that now the government will be settled again, and if you
                  keep meetings, you must expect the same again. My son answered him, we must keep
                  meetings, unless you take our lives. Then William Kirby said, we will not take
                  your lives, but whilst you have anything, we will take it. So I wrote a letter to
                  King James, in which I said, Thou bids' t me come home, and so I am; but as I said
                  to thee, I could not live peaceably, so it is like to be; and then I hinted in my
                  letter W. Kirby's discourse with my son. And I desired of the King, to let me have
                  something from him, that I might live peace- ably at my house.</p>
               <p>This letter was delivered to him, and as I heard, he carried it to the council,
                  and it was read; and some of the council said, she desires a protection, that she
                  may live peaceably at her own house; and that some made answer, they could give no
                  protection to an individual: however, I do suppose they gave our persecutors a
                  private caution, for they troubled us no more; but, if that had not been, it is
                  likely they had a mind to begin anew upon us; for a little before the time of the
                  informers, they brought that law upon us, concerning twelve pence a Sunday, so
                  called; and they carried me, and my son and daughter Abraham, to Lancaster prison,
                  and kept us there about three weeks. And when they considered, that they could not
                  fine me, nor my house, when I was in prison, then they let us go home, and soon
                  after they did fine us both for the house, and for speaking as before hinted.</p>
               <p>And thus have they troubled and persecuted us divers ways; but the Lord God
                  Almighty hath pre- served me, and us, until this day; glorious praises be given to
                  him forevermore.</p>
               <p>And the Lord hath given me such strength and ability, that I have been at London,
                  to see my dear husband and children and relatives and friends there in 1690, being
                  the seventy-sixth year of my age; and I was very well satisfied, refreshed and
                  comforted in my journey, and found Friends in much love, praises be returned to
                  the unchangeable God forever. This being nine times that I have been to London,
                  upon the Lord's and His truth's account</p>
               <p>The company of her two daughters, the wives of John Rouse and William Mead, the
                  former residing at Kingston on Thames, and the latter at Goose's in Essex, while
                  on her visits to London, was doubtless very comforting to her, and a great
                  satisfaction to them. These were also favorite resorts of Gr. Fox when in that
                  neighbourhood.</p>
               <p>After returning to her home, she wrote the following epistle to the Women's
                  Meeting in London: —</p>
               <p>"Dear Sisters: —</p>
               <p>In the eternal blessed truth, into which we are be- gotten, and in which we stand,
                  and are preserved, as we keep in it, and are guided by it: in this is my dear and
                  unchangeable love remembered unto you all; acknowledging your dear and tender
                  love, when I was with you, in which my heart was rejoiced, to feel the ancient
                  love and unity of the eternal spirit amongst you; and my soul was and is refreshed
                  in my journey, in visiting my dear husband and chil- dren, and you my dear
                  Friends. And now I am returned to my own house and family, where I find all well;
                  praised and honoured be my Heavenly Father.</p>
               <p>And dear Friends our engagements are great unto the Lord, and he is dear and
                  faithful unto us; and blessed and happy are all they that are dear and faithful
                  unto Him. And those that keep single and chaste unto Him need not fear evil
                  tidings, nor what man can do, for He that hath all power in heaven and earth in
                  His hand, will surely keep His own church and family, those that worship Him,
                  within the measuring line, that measures the temple, and the altar, and those that
                  worship therein, they are kept safe, as in the hollow of His hand.</p>

               <p>And so, dear Friends, my heart and soul was so much comforted and refreshed,
                  amongst you, that I could not but signify the remembrance of my dear love unto
                  you; and also my acknowledgment of your dear love and tenderness to my dear
                  husband; for which I doubt not, but the Lord doth and will reward you; into whose
                  hand and arm and power I commit you.</p>
               <p>M. Fox.</p>
               <p>Swarthmore, 10th of oth month, 1690."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg64">
               <p>CHAPTER V. 1690-1702.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterSubtitle">
               <p>DEATH OF GEORGE FOX — AGAIN GOES TO LONDON — ADDRESS TO KING WILLIAM — HER DEATH,
                  AND DYING SAYINGS — TESTIMONY OF HER CHILDREN, AND OTHER FRIENDS, TO HER CHARACTER
                  — BURIED AT SWARTHMORE.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <p>In the latter part of the year 1690, her husband, who had been in a declining
                  state of health for several years previous, died at the house of Henry G-ouldney,
                  in London, after a few days' sickness, in much contentment and peace. " It fell to
                  the lot of William Penn," says Clarkson, "to communicate this event to his wife."
                  " I am to be," says he, "the teller to thee of sorrowful tidings, in some
                  respects, which is this, that thy dear husband, and my beloved and dear friend,
                  finished his glorious testimony this night about half an hour after nine, being
                  sensible to the last breath. Oh! he is gone, and left us in the storm that is over
                  our heads, surely in great mercy to him, but as an evidence to us of sorrow to
                  come: a prince, indeed, is fallen in Israel to-day; he died as he lived, a lamb,
                  minding the things of God and His church to the last, in an universal spirit."</p>
               <p>They had been married about twenty-one years, and during that period he had passed
                  but a small part of the time with her, his various religious engagements keeping
                  him almost constantly away from Swarthmore.</p>

               <p>This circumstance probably gave rise to some censorious remarks, -for his wife, in
                  speaking of it, says: "And though the Lord had provided him with an out- ward
                  habitation, he was not willing to stay in it, be- cause it was so remote and far
                  from London, where his service mostly lay. And my concern for God and His holy and
                  eternal truth was then in the north, where God had placed and set me; and like-
                  wise for the ordering and governing of my children and family; so that we were
                  willing both of us to live apart some years upon God's account and His truth's
                  service, and to deny ourselves of that comfort which we might have had in being
                  together, for the sake and service of the Lord and His truth. And if any took
                  occasion, or judged hard of us, because of that, the Lord will judge them; for we
                  were innocent. And for my own part I was willing to make many long journeys for
                  taking away all occasion of evil thoughts; and although I lived two hundred miles
                  from London, yet have I been nine times there, upon the Lord's and His truth's
                  account; and of all the times I was in London, this last time was most comfort-
                  able, the Lord was pleased to give me strength and ability to travel that great
                  journey, being seventy- six years of age, to see my dear husband, who was better
                  in health and strength than many times I had seen him before. I look upon it, that
                  the Lord's special hand was in it, that I should go then; for he lived but about
                  half a year after I left him; which makes me admire the wisdom and goodness of God
                  in ordering my journey at that time." </p>

               <p>In connection with this subject, it should be remembered that George Fox, during
                  his married life, was almost incessantly engaged in zealously propo- gating his
                  views of Christian faith, and in establish- ing the religious society that grew
                  out of them. As a Gospel minister he visited North America and the West India
                  Islands; was twice in Holland, and other parts of the continent of Europe, beside
                  long and laborious journeys in his native land, enduring also an imprisonment of
                  fourteen months in Worcester jail.</p>
               <p>Whilst his great mission remained unaccomplished, he contentedly relinquished the
                  ease of a comfortable home, and the society of an interesting family. His industry
                  and zeal were remarkable, love to God and love to man, and the interests of the
                  beloved people, whom the Lord had enabled him to call from the barren and desolate
                  mountains of an empty profes- sion, to come and sit under their own vine and fig-
                  tree, where none could make them afraid, were the powerful incentives that
                  governed his conduct; and in the performance of his duty to his Divine Master, he
                  was made willing to forsake not only houses and lands, but wife also, for His sake
                  and the gospel.</p>
               <p>At the expense of much time and patience, he fre- quently appeared before the
                  Kings, Parliaments and Judges, in order to lay before them appeals for jus- tice,
                  mercy and moderation. He was also engaged with others in forming those excellent
                  rules of disci- pline intended for the government of the society, in defending its
                  doctrines from the arguments and cavils of opponents and apostates, and in writing
                  and publishing books for these and other purposes.</p>
               <p>London being the metropolis of the kingdom, the yearly meeting convening there,
                  and many of the leading and influential Friends residing in that city, George Fox
                  was necessarily much there in attending to the secular interests of the
                  society.</p>
               <p>The facilities for travelling of the present day strikingly contrast with the
                  times we are now considering, scarcely any public conveyances being then in use.
                  Stage-coaches were but just coming into existence in the reign of Charles the
                  Second, and were slow, inconvenient and clumsy vehicles, with difficulty going the
                  distance between Oxford and London in daylight, which is now performed in a little
                  more than an hour. Travelling on horseback was commonly and almost universally
                  practised; private carriages were used chiefly by the wealthier classes; and
                  wagons carrying merchandise to different parts of the country also accommodated a
                  few of the poorer sort of people. The state of the roads, also, at this period,
                  formed a serious obstacle to the comfort of travelling, many of them being so much
                  out of repair as to be almost impassable, and often- times infested with
                  highwaymen; so that a journey of two hundred miles, beset with these difficulties,
                  may form a very important reason why he was so much absent from home at this
                  time.</p>
               <p>It appears M. Fox again visited London, under religious concern, in the year 1698.
                  At that time she addressed the following letter to King William, which was
                  delivered to him by her daughter, Susan Ingram: —</p>
               <p>"To King William: —</p>
               <p>It hath pleased Almighty God to bring me unto this place, two hundred miles from
                  my dwelling, in my old age (being entered into the eighty-fifth year of my age),
                  to bear my testimony for that eternal truth, which I and many more are made
                  partakers of, praised be the Lord; and I am not free and clear to return to my
                  habitation, until I have cleared my- self unto this government. I was exercised in
                  this manner the first year King Charles the Second came to the crown, and laboured
                  amongst them a whole year, to acquaint them, and give them to understand our
                  principles, in giving letters and papers unto them for that end. And great opposi-
                  tion we had, both from church and state, yet it pleased God to cause them to give
                  us some liberty to worship Him, though sometimes under great sufferings.</p>
               <p>And now I am to acquaint King William, that we have been a people about forty-six
                  years, and have lived under several reigns, and we have suf- fered very much, as
                  it is well-known to the nation of England, even to the death of several hundreds
                  by imprisonment and other hardships, and yet we were never found in transgression
                  of any just or righteous law, but only upon account of our con- sciences towards
                  God; that was the cause of our suf- fering, and not for evil or wrong done to any
                  man or government; for our principle which we testify of is the Light of Jesus
                  Christ, and His eternal spirit, which leads into all truth and righteousness, but
                  not into any untruth or evil actions. And if any bear- ing the same name amongst
                  us have transgressed against the precious truth and royal law of liberty, we do
                  with the same spirit judge and condemn them wherever they are found. And we do
                  deny all plottings and contrivings against the government, and all false and
                  underhand dealing; and we live in that principle which is righteous, just and
                  true; for God is a God of truth, and blessed are all they that fear Him, and walk
                  in His truth. And now God has placed thee over us, in this government, who hast
                  been very moderate and merciful to us, and we live very comfortably under thee and
                  it, and do enjoy our meetings quietly, which formerly we were much disturbed in,
                  which was a great suffering upon us; and God has blessed thy government, and
                  prospered thy undertakings; for which the King and we have cause to bless His holy
                  name, who is a God of peace, and His Son is Prince of peace, who now has given us
                  peace and tranquillity, for which we praise His holy name; and thy gentle govern-
                  ment and clemency, and gracious acts, God hath and will reward thee for. And as we
                  abide in that just and righteous principle of the eternal God,, by which we ought
                  all to be guided, I hope the government shall never hear worse of us; but that we
                  shall rather be a blessing than grievance to it and the nation; for so it will be
                  as we continue in the blessed truth; in which I pray God for thy preservation, who
                  am His servant, and thy faithful subject.</p>
               <p>Margaret Fox. London, 24tth of 4th month, 1698"</p>
               <p>She died at Swarthmore, the 23d of the 2d month, 1702, in the eighty-eighth year
                  of her age, having survived her husband about eleven years.</p>
               <p>Her children say: "The blessed God of heaven and earth preserved her understanding
                  to the last; and in the time of her sickness, she was in a sweet frame of spirit,
                  and uttered many heavenly expres- sions near her conclusion in this world, which
                  some of us were eye and ear witnesses of; and we believe she is inheriting a
                  heavenly mansion, prepared by the Lord Jesus Christ, for all his faithful
                  followers."</p>
               <p>Thomas Pockrey, who visited her shortly before her decease, upon querying how she
                  found herself, she answered: "Very weak in body, but alive in God :" he also heard
                  her speak many comfortable and excellent words, thus: "The Lord is with me, and I
                  am with the Lord, and in Him only will I trust and commit all to the divine
                  providence of the Lord, both concerning my children and grand-chil- dren, and all
                  things they do enjoy from Him, both in spirituals and naturals, who is the God of
                  all the mercies and blessings to His people, throughout all generations: to Him be
                  glorious praises forever. Amen."</p>
               <p>Her daughter expressing what a blessed mother she had been to her children, and
                  whole posterity, she answered very sweetly: u Cleave to me, and yon will not do
                  wrong, for I am joined to the Lord."</p>
               <p>At another time she said: "Oh! my sweet Lord, into thy bosom do I commit myself
                  freely; not desiring to live in this troublesome and painful world; it is all
                  nothing to me; for my Maker is my husband."</p>
               <p>"Come, come, pray let us join the Lord, and be of one spirit, join to the eternal
                  God, and be of one spirit."</p>
               <p>At another time: "Come, Lord Jesus, I am freely given up to Thy will."</p>
               <p>Again she said: "I freely forgive all people upon the face of the whole earth, for
                  any wrong done to me, as freely as I desire to be forgiven."</p>
               <p>And seeing her children sorrowful, she said: " Be quiet; for I am as comfortable,
                  and well in spirit, as ever I was." And a little before her close, to her daughter
                  Rachel: "Take me in thy arms, I am in peace."</p>
               <p>She was interred in the burial-ground belonging to Swarthmore meeting-house, the
                  27th of 2d month, many Friends out of several counties being present. Thomas Camm,
                  who attended her funeral, remarks: "The Lord did eminently appear with us, and
                  many testimonies were borne to the honour of the truth, and great satisfaction to
                  many there, of great quality and degree in the world; and to the comfort and
                  edification of all the upright to God; to whom belongs the praise of all His
                  wonderful works and marvellous loving kindness extended and multiplied, unto and
                  upon His people, in and through our Lord Jesus Christ, world without end.
                  Amem"</p>
               <p>In the testimony of her children, concerning her, they say: " The Lord so
                  increased her growth in the blessed truth, that she became a mother in Israel, and
                  was very exemplary and serviceable in the church of Christ, strengthening the
                  weak, and supporting the feeble. And a great care was upon her, and she was very
                  diligent in speaking, and promoting the truth of our Lord Jesus Christ, both in
                  this nation (where she travelled much), and to other nations by epistles: which
                  care she performed and continued for many years, until the truth had made a larger
                  entrance in the nations; discountenancing and reproving all false appearances,
                  which would have made a show of that which they were not."</p>
               <p>"And the Lord made her a preacher of righteous- ness, both in a public testimony
                  for the truth, and in her life and conversation. And she continued her zeal and
                  constancy to and for the truth, in her diligent attending of weekly, quarterly,
                  monthly, and other meetings for worship, in which she was truly exemplary, to very
                  near the conclusion. And also, she was raised up, and preserved a noble and
                  valiant sufferer for the truth, and its innocent testi- mony ) so she spared no
                  labour nor pains, in travel- ling to visit those that were under confinement for
                  the sake thereof, and was a comfort and strength to them therein."</p>

               <p>Thomas Camm testifies of her: "And as she freely denied and despised the glory of
                  this fading world, for Christ's and the truth's sake, God gave her honour, and a
                  name amongst the righteous, with qualifications many ways for a considerable
                  service in His church, in which she shined as a morning star, being filled with
                  real wisdom and understand- ing, for the propagation of truth and righteousness;
                  of a clear discerning of spirits, and the working of the enemy, to draw from the
                  life and power of truth, into a liberty that genders to bondage, and to separation
                  and breach of unity amongst Friends, appearing firm and zealous against the same,
                  to the comfort and help of many; fervent and living in her ministry, and in
                  supplications and prayers to Almighty God, to the edifying and building up many in
                  that most precious faith, which gives victory over the world. Not only a great and
                  exemplary sufferer for the truth, but a visitor and sympa- thizer with all the
                  faithful in their sufferings, zealously labouring and endeavouring with such as
                  were in authority for their relief, as being afflicted with the afflicted, and
                  mourning with those that mourned, trusting in the Arm of God's power, which is the
                  support of the righteous.</p>
               <p>She never spared herself, nor doubted of good success, in her manifold labours on
                  truth's account; both in her ministry abroad in most places in this nation, and
                  other services: but approved herself such in zeal that needed not to be ashamed of
                  her work and service for the Lord, His Truth, and people in her time, which she
                  performed with all sincerity, and is now rewarded with the full fruition of
                  eternal life, and peace with her God, whom she loved, feared and served with an
                  upright heart, every way faith- fully, while God was pleased to give her strength
                  and ability to perform the same."</p>
               <p>George Whitehead says: "She had a godly care upon her for the sober and virtuous
                  education of her children and offspring; and the Lord blessed and answered her
                  therein in a good measure, and no doubt blessed them the more for her sake, as
                  well as for their own salvation, for which she chiefly tra- vailed in spirit, and
                  earnestly sought the Lord in their behalf, beyond all temporal blessings."</p>
               <p>Beside the epistles addressed to Friends by M. Fox, she maintained an extensive
                  correspondence with many of the leading and eminent persons in the society, in all
                  parts of the nation. Numerous letters addressed to her are preserved in the
                  Swarthmore collection, relating principally to the difficulties and persecutions
                  under which many of its members suf- fered, and the various applications made to
                  the monarchs, the Parliament and magistrates for re- dress. It is very remarkable
                  to observe the respect with which she was regarded by the early Friends, and the
                  affectionate terms in which they addressed her.</p>
               <p>Edward Burrough styles her: " Dear Sister, who art a fruitful branch in the living
                  vine, and a plea- sant plant in the garden of God."</p>
               <p>And Alexander Parker: "Dearly beloved sister,</p>

               <p>dearly do I salute thee. Our life is one; our joy one, our suffering one; our food
                  and raiment one; eating both of one bread, and drinking both of one cup in the
                  Father's house, where there is bread enough, and wells of living water to refresh
                  the ten- der plants; where the babes are nourished and fed with the milk, and
                  receive their meat in due sea- son; where there is joy and rejoicing in the
                  presence of the Lord, and pleasures forevermore; which only those do enjoy, who
                  have followed the Lamb through many tribulations and fiery trials and temptations,
                  and have overcome by the blood of the Lamb, and their garments washed white and
                  clean. Hallelujah! praises to His glorious name forever, who has called and chosen
                  us, and made us partakers of the divine nature; and hath redeemed us from the
                  world and the pollutions of it: to be witnesses of His powerful name; and in His
                  power and free love, hath He sent us abroad into the world, to turn others from
                  darkness and their vain conversation; that they may have union with us in the
                  light of His Son, and praise and glorify His eternal Majesty for- ever and
                  forevermore."</p>
               <p>How much she was beloved by her immediate connections will appear from the
                  following extract from a memorial of her by her sons-in-law, after her death:
                  —</p>
               <p>"And as for us, who are her sons-in-law, we can- not but give our testimony of our
                  sense of her worthiness, and we account ourselves happy, and it is a singular
                  mercy to us, that the Lord gave us wives of the daughters of such a worthy person,
                  and that we are partakers of their virtuous education, whereby they are made a
                  blessing to us &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Indeed, she appears to have been regarded as a nursing mother in the church, both
                  spiritually and temporally, visiting Friends in prison, entertaining them at her
                  house, and freely dispensing of her sub- stance for their comfort and support.</p>
               <p>Thus having faithfully served her generation according to the will of her Heavenly
                  Father, she has passed, we doubt not, to the fruition of that glorious reward
                  promised to the righteous, to those who, through much tribulation, have washed
                  their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>EPISTLES.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg77">
               <p>PREFACE TO MARGARET FOX'S EPISTLES,</p>
               <p>WRITTEN BY HERSELF.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>Friendly Reader: —</opener>
               <p>The following epistles were written at the first ap- pearance of truth among us,
                  when we were young in it: the light of Christ being our first principle, our minds
                  beiag turned to it, and it having be- come our teacher, leader and guider, we saw
                  per- fectly that there was no safety, nor preservation out of sin and
                  transgression, but as we obeyed the light, and followed it in our hearts and con-
                  sciences, it leading out of sin, transgression and iniquity: so as we waited in
                  it, and dwelt in it, we came to witness a washing and cleansing, by the blood of
                  Jesus. And so we came to discern, be- tween the precious and the vile, and between
                  the holy, and the unclean, and between the chaff, and the wheat; and between those
                  that served God, and those that served Him not. And when we came to this sight,
                  and knowledge, and discerning, then we became very zealous for God, and for His
                  truth, and for the preservation of His people in the truth; and our hearts became
                  tender, and we had a pity for all people's souls that remained in darkness. We
                  were moved of the Lord to write often to Friends, and our testimony was very much
                  to the light of Christ in the conscience; because we saw that was the way, and
                  there was no other; for Christ Jesus said, I am the Light; He also said, I am the
                  way, the truth, and the life; and there is none that can come to the Father, but
                  by me.</p>
               <p>And so we received His Testimony, and could set to our seals that this was true.
                  And then we saw the great concern that lay upon this, which is the salvation of
                  poor people's souls. And we knowing as Christ said, they that hated the Light it
                  was their condemnation; and also those that obeyed it, it would bring them to
                  Christ their salvation; this made us very importunate with all people, both
                  Friends and others, to direct them to the Light, and obey it.</p>
               <p>And also there being such a body of darkness, which warred against it; for people
                  having lived in darkness, out of the knowledge of the Light, it was such a new
                  doctrine to them, that there was a mighty war in people's minds against it; and
                  the priests and professors setting themselves against it, calling it a natural
                  light; and some said it was a dim light, and some scoffingly called it a dark
                  lantern, and others said it was not sufficient to condemn: so in their dark
                  imaginations they fought against it. And very much we had to do in the beginning
                  to get people convinced of the Truth, and of the sufficiency of it; and also those
                  that were convinced, to keep them in obedience to it. But the Lord's arm and power
                  car- ried on His awn work, notwithstanding all the oppo- sition of the power of
                  darkness; glory and praises be to His holy name forever.</p>
               <p>Here are a few epistles preserved, but many more are wanting, the copies being
                  lost, with many other papers and letters that might have been serviceable; but in
                  love to all people, we bring those that we have to open view; that if the Lord
                  give a blessing to them, they may be serviceable hereafter, as they have been to
                  many heretofore. The Truth is one and the same always; and though ages and genera-
                  tions pass away, and one generation goes and another comes, yet the Word, and
                  Power, and Spirit of the living God endures forever, and is the same, and never
                  changes.</p>
               <p>And so, reader, cleave to the blessed Light and Truth of the living God, that He
                  hath placed in thy heart, and believe in it, and hearken to it, and obey it, and
                  it will lead thee in the path that we have gone, and then thou wilt see, and feel,
                  and under- stand what we have gone through; and thou wilt come to be a witness of
                  the living God and His Truth, which will be peace and comfort to thy soul.</p>
               <p>The Lord God Almighty open thy heart, and enlighten the eye of thy understanding,
                  that thou mayest come to have unity with all the saints in light.</p>

               <p>Friends, whom the Lord God hath called unto the light which is eternal, which the
                  Lord God has sent, to bring His seed out of bondage, and out of the house of
                  darkness, from under Pharaoh, and his task-masters, which has so long been held
                  under the dark power and mystery of iniquity. The Lord God of life and power hath
                  visited you, and sent His ser- vants to awaken you, and to raise you from the
                  dead, that Christ might give you life, who is now come and coming to redeem
                  Israel, and to divide the Red Sea, and to overturn Pharaoh and his host. Stand,
                  still (I say unto you) and see the salvation of God, and in the fear of the living
                  God wait low in your own measure of grace, and harken diligently unto that, that
                  your souls may live. And this you must do, if ever you witness the living God; so
                  in the name and power of the Lord Jesus Christ, at whose name every knee shall
                  bow, and every tongue confess, beware how you spend your money for that which is
                  not bread, and your labour for that which perisheth; it is the diligent hand that
                  maketh rich, but the idle, slothful and negligent, suffer want. And beware of
                  going from your Guide, which keepeth you low and tender, and prize the love of God
                  that ever He should visit you; and beware that you do not requite Him evil for
                  good, for He is a jealous God, and will not clear the guilty; it is the low, and
                  the meek, and humble that the Lord God teacheth, it is the broken and contrite
                  spirit, that God will not de- spise. And He, who is the high and lofty one, that
                  inhabiteth eternity, dwelleth in the hearts of the humble.</p>
               <p>But all who are got up in their imaginations, the Lord God will scatter, and the
                  proud, the high, and the lofty, the Lord doth resist; and this you shall witness,
                  the Lord feeds the hungry, but the rich is sent empty away. And they who thirst
                  and breathe after righteousness, such the Lord satis- fieth. So read, and with the
                  eternal light examine and search, and try what it is that you thirst after;
                  whether it be righteousness, purity and holiness, for these will the Lord satisfy;
                  and whoever is not thus seeking, shall never receive satisfaction from the Lord
                  God; but wrath, and terror, and horror, shall fall upon that which is contrary to
                  this. So, as you love your eternal peace, and the redemption of your souls, keep
                  low in your measure of the living testi- mony which cometh from the living God,
                  which is one in all, in its measure one; there is no divi- sion, no rent, but all
                  one. And this gathers your hearts together, and this knits and unites unto the
                  body, where the unity is; and who gathers not here, scatters abroad; and he that
                  is not with us here, is against us. So examine, and try whether you are gathering
                  now or scattering abroad, with the Light which is eternal, which is one in all.
                  Examine and try your own selves, I charge you, as you will answer it before the
                  Lord God; come down and stoop to the yoke of Christ, which is easy, and take His
                  yoke upon you, and His burden which is light; and beware of starting from under
                  the yoke of obedi- ence, or pulling away the shoulder; for the Lord God requires
                  not only sacrifice, but obedience, which is better. And that mind that looks
                  outward, from the measure enjoyed, and joins to anything without, contrary to the
                  freedom of the spirit within, that mind is for judgment. The eternal spirit of God
                  is one in all, and that which divides one from another, is for judgment, for where
                  division is, that is of the kingdom that cannot stand. So read where you are, for
                  if you are in that which is divided, you cannot stand. So in love and tenderness
                  to your souls, I warn and charge you from the Lord, keep in the light, which is
                  one, in the power, which is one, in the measure of life made manifest in you,
                  which is one. And here is no division, nor separation, but a gathering and a
                  knitting. And if you love the light, then you come to the light to be proved, and
                  tried whether your works be wrought in God. But that which hates the light, turns
                  from the light, and that shall be condemned by the light forever. And though you
                  may turn from the light, where the unity is, and you may turn from the eternal
                  truth; but from the witness of God in your consciences, (which he hath placed in
                  you, which beareth wit- ness for the living God,) you can never fly; that shall
                  pursue you wherever you go. And they who turn out from the light, their
                  resurrection is to condenmation, and on the left hand they are put among the
                  goats, and shall have their portion with hypo- crites and unbelievers; and this
                  shall be witnessed forever.</p>
               <p>And this I was moved of the Lord, to write to you, in love and tenderness to the
                  measure of God in you, with which I have unity, which will witness for me forever;
                  and this is in love to your souls. So the Lord God of life and power keep you
                  alive in that, which He hath placed in you, to His everlast- ing glory: for a
                  sweet savour we are unto God, both in them that are saved, and in them that
                  perish. And beware how you draw back from the everlasting truth, that the Lord God
                  hath tendered to you, which you shall eternally witness to be of God: for he that
                  draweth back, my soul hath no pleasure in him, saith God. That which we have
                  heard, and have seen, and felt, and our hands have handled, even the Word of life
                  which hath been declared unto you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>From one who desires the good of all souls.</salute>
                  <signed>Margaret Fell.</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>AN EPISTLE TO CONVINCED FRIENDS, IN 1656.</p>
               <p>Dear Friends, brethren and sisters in the eternal light, by which we are gathered,
                  which is our teacher and leader: which light conieth from our Lord Jesus Christ,
                  the Captain of our salvation, in whom is life, and this life is the light of men;
                  who has laid down His life for His sheep, and who gives unto His sheep eternal
                  life; and this life is in His Son: your righteousness is of me, saith the Lord;
                  and this is the heritage of the saints: this you are made partakers of, who walk
                  in the light, and dwell in the light, you shall have the light of life, and come
                  to know the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom He hath sent, who is come a light
                  into the world: he that believes in Him, shall not walk in darkness, shall not
                  perish, but have everlasting life. And this is the Father's free love, to send His
                  only begotten Son into the world, who is hated and rejected of men, but chosen of
                  God and precious, who is become the head of our corner: glory eternal be to the
                  living God! on Him are we built, in Him are we rooted and grounded: he is our
                  foundation and root, we His offspring, on whom we stand fast, unmovable. This is
                  the corner stone, which all the builders refuse and disallow; but on this rock is
                  the whole church built, which is made of living stones, elect and precious, the
                  spiritual temple, whose maker and builder is God. And now we haying an high priest
                  over the household of God, let us draw near with a true heart, in full assurance
                  of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and our bodies
                  washed with pure water. Wherefore return to the shepherd of your souls, an
                  unchangeable priest which is made with an oath forever, after the order of
                  Melchisedeck, who is made surety of a better tes- tament, who needeth not daily to
                  offer sacrifice, but he hath offered one sacrifice, and forever is set down at the
                  right hand of God, from henceforth expecting until his enemies be made his
                  footstool. For by one offering he hath perfected forever them that are sanctified;
                  and of this the Holy Ghost is a witness to us in the fulfilling of the everlasting
                  promise of the Lord God, who hath said, I will put my laics in their hearts, and
                  in their minds will I write them.</p>
               <p>Now, dear brethren, of this bear witness, and of the truth and faithfulness of the
                  Lord God, you may set to your seals, all who abide in the light, and de- part from
                  iniquity, who name this name, which is better than other names: to which every
                  knee shall bow, and every tongue confess. And now that ye are made partakers of a
                  living, pure, eternal, immor- tal principle, which came from the living God, by
                  which you may enter into the holiest, by the blood of Jesus, by this new and
                  living way, which He hath consecrated for us through the veil (that is to say),
                  His flesh: therefore hold fast the profession of your faith without wavering, for
                  faithful is He that hath promised; and in the straight and narrow way that leads
                  to life pass on, that through the straight gate you may enter, which few there be
                  that find. Oh! in the eternal light (which is one in all) which leads up to the
                  Father of light; and in the measure of light received from the Father and fountain
                  of light and life, all wait, and dwell; and to the life raised by the immortal
                  "Word of life, join your minds; and pass from death to life, that so you may come
                  to know and witness the true love that is to the brethren, where unity is, whereby
                  you all may know that you are true disciples; in that you love one another; and
                  here you fulfil the whole law, and keep the new commandment, which your Lord and
                  Master has commanded.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dearly beloved brethren, consider what ye are called to, and what ye
                  are made to partake of, even of a living, and pure and holy priesthood, a peculiar
                  people ye are, and of the holy nation, and of the Koyal Seed. Now with the light
                  which is eternal, which searches, tries, examines, weighs, and makes all things
                  manifest of what sort they are; let it search and try you, how you grow up in the
                  eternal and immortal birth, and do not de- ceive your souls: For except you be
                  born again, of water and of the spirit, ye cannot enter. Now see whether ye can
                  read this in the light; and whether ye know, and see, and witness this in your own
                  particulars, yea or nay; and see whether you are not like Nicodemus, who said. How
                  can these things he? and whether ye are not ignorant of this.</p>
               <p>Therefore come down to the witness of God, and deal plainly with your own souls;
                  and let the judge which stands at the door, pass sentence upon you. Let the time
                  past suffice, that you have hid the talent in the earth, which you have received
                  from the Lord to profit withal. And let the earth give up her dead, and the sea
                  give up her dead, and hell give up her dead, and let all come to judgment; and let
                  death and hell be cast into the lake; and freely give up that which is for the
                  sword to the sword; and that which is for the fire, to the fire; so those who are
                  dead in sin, may arise. For what avails it else, for you to take the profession
                  and form of the living truth? For if the dead rise not, ye are yet in your sins,
                  and your faith is vain. Therefore see what you are doing: for it is not the sayer,
                  but he that daeth the tvill of my Father; and many shall be called and few chosen.
                  Now see with the light which is eternal, that ye are not only of the many which
                  are called, but of the few which are chosen; and give all diligence not to make
                  only your calling, but your election sure. And Friends, your day of calling is
                  come; ye are called out of the world, and separated from the world, by the call of
                  the living God: the light calls out of Sodom and Egypt, where the many are.
                  Therefore do not deceive yourselves, for ye are some of the many that are called;
                  and ye are made partakers of that which calls continually, the voice behind, which
                  cries, This is the way, walk in it; why will ye die? Now consider, how you hearken
                  to this holy call, how you are obedient to it, how you are subject, and how you
                  are taught and guided, by the measure of God's spirit; for all the children of the
                  Lord are taught of the Lord, and in righteousness are they established. Now search
                  with the light, which is eternal, whether ye are established in righteousness and
                  purity; if ye are not, then mind the teachings of the Lord, for he that walks in
                  the light, as he is in the light, the blood of Jesus cleanseth from all sin. Now
                  examine whether ye are cleansed, whether ye are purged, whether ye are washed; for
                  if ye walk in the light, then ye wit- ness cleansing and washing.</p>
               <p>Beware of betraying the just and the innocent in you (I warn and charge you, as
                  you will answer it to the Lord) with a form and profession of the truth, without
                  the life, and so betray your own souls; but to the pure eternal principle of the
                  Lord Go4 turn, and keep your minds unto this, which is given unto you, for the
                  redeeming and ransoming of your souls from the captivity and bondage of sin and
                  cor- ruption; and hearken diligently to that of God that your souls may live; and
                  that you may see your Saviour, who saves His people from their sins, and so
                  witness the salvation of your souls. Ye are made partakers of the free grace of
                  God, which brings sal- vation; so let it be your teacher and leader. And beware of
                  turning this grace into wantonness, which is able to save your souls; but receive
                  with meek- ness the ingrafted Word, that the milk thereof ye may witness, and as
                  new-born babes, desire that you may grow thereby; and so the Word that is nigh, in
                  the heart, which is the Word of faith which we preach; which Word was in the
                  beginning (by which the heaven and earth were made), which we have heard, which we
                  have seen, which our hands have handled, this we declare unto you. And to the
                  measure of this in you, am I made manifest; and my joy and life is, that you would
                  take heed to your own measures received, and be true and faithful to that which is
                  able to save your souls; that eternal pure redemption ye may come to witness, and
                  the unity of the faith, &amp;c, and so joining to the body, which holdeth the
                  head, from which the living virtue is received, you may grow up as lively plants
                  in the garden of God, which he is dress- ing, watering, and pruning, that to Him
                  fruit may be brought forth, who is the Lord of the vine- yard, and the husbandman,
                  who purgeth every plant that beareth fruit, that it may bring forth more fruit;
                  and every branch that beareth not fruit, he taketh away. Now see with the eternal
                  light, whe- ther you bring forth fruit unto God; for every tree is known by its
                  fruit; and every branch, which the Lord planteth, brings forth fruit (not only
                  leaves, but fruit). Now search, whether you bring forth fruit or leaves; for that
                  tree, that is in the garden, and brings forth nothing but leaves, is to be cut
                  down.</p>
               <p>Friends, deal plainly with yourselves, and let the eternal light search you, and
                  try you, for the good of your souls; for this will deal plainly with you; it will
                  rip you up, lay you open, and make all manifest that lodgeth in you; the secret
                  subtilty of the enemy of your souls, this eternal searcher and tryer will make
                  manifest. Therefore all come to this, and be searched, judged, led and guided; for
                  to this you must stand or fall; and if you turn from this, it is a swift witness
                  against the adulterer and sorcerer, and from it you cannot flee; in this I have
                  cleared my conscience; for the good of your souls I have written, who desires that
                  you all might be where I am, that so we might all be one. And so the Lord God of
                  life and power keep you in His fear, that the Lord God you may serve and honour;
                  that your hearts may be kept clean, and the secrets of the Lord ye may come to
                  know, which none* shall ever know, but those that fear Him; and this ye shall
                  eternally witness. And therefore I say again, fear the Lord God, that so the pure
                  wisdom ye may come to learn; for dreadful and terrible is the Lord God; and the
                  day of the vengeance of our God is come, in which He renders to every one
                  according to his deeds; the backslider, the revolter, the disobedient ones, the
                  careless, the slothful, and those whose minds are at liberty, and will not abide
                  in the cross of Christ; all these shall receive according to their deeds.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dear Friends, abide in the cross, and keep your minds to that which is
                  pure; so that you may come to witness the enmity slain, the hand- writing of
                  ordinances blotted out, and nailed to the cross, and you crucified to the world,
                  and the world to you; and consider one another, and provoke one another to love
                  and to good works ) not forsaking the assembling of yourselves, but exhorting one
                  another, and so much the more, as you see the day approach- ing. And dwell in love
                  and unity, in the pure eter- nal light; there is your fellowship, there is your
                  cleansing and washing. And here is the mystery to all the disobedient ones. And
                  the everlasting God, of light, life and power, keep you all faithful to your own
                  measure; that so the resurrection and the life ye may witness, and the living
                  bread ye may feed on, which, whosoever eateth of, shall never die. So G-od
                  Almighty be with you, and preserve you all faithful in Christ Jesus.</p>
               <p>From your dear sister in the unchangeable love of Christ, who desires the good of
                  all your souls.</p>
               <closer><signed>Margaret Fell.</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>AN EPISTLE TO FRIENDS, 1657.</p>
               <p>Dear Brethren and Sisters, who are gathered in the light of Christ Jesus, the
                  fountain of all light, and life, from whence light comes, from whence life comes,
                  from whence power comes; which re- deems out of nations, kindreds, people and
                  tongues, to be kings and priests unto God, to reign with Him upon the earth. This
                  is the possession of the saints who dwell in the light, that leads them into the
                  life and fountain from whence it comes; here is the unity of the spirit, and bond
                  of peace, which never can be broken. Here the pure language and worship of the
                  Lord is, with one heart, one con- sent, and one soul, where there is no division;
                  but the pure path of life is known, the way of holiness, where the unclean cannot
                  pass, where the presence of the Lord is, wherein is fulness of joy, and plea-
                  sures for evermore. Now that every one may read his name here, in the unchangeable
                  life is this written, that the pure life in all may prevail, and that the poor may
                  receive the gospel; which is glad tidings of great joy to the oppressed and heavy
                  laden, which groan under the bondage of corruption, and cry for deliverance; the
                  cry whereof, is entered into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth; and he hath
                  determined in the thoughts of His heart, that the deliverer shall come from Zion,
                  and the captivity of His people will He bring back, and salvation will come unto
                  Israel; so that Jacob shall rejoice, and Israel shall be glad, glory, everlasting
                  glory be unto His ever- lasting arm forever; by which He gets unto Himself a name
                  and victory even to the astonishment of the heathen, and to the confounding of His
                  enemies, and to the recovering, raising and quickening of many who were dead in
                  sins. And though He hath been a God unknown, now is He arisen in His light, which
                  shineth in the conscience, and He hath caused it to shine out of darkness, and it
                  hath shined in the heart; which gives the light of the knowledge of the glory of
                  God, in the face of Jesus Christ His Son.</p>
               <p>And now unto them who have long sat in darkness, and under the shadow of death,
                  even unto them hath this light shined, who were sometime darkness, but now are
                  they light in the Lord, who were dead in trespasses and sins, even them hath He
                  quick- ened together with Christ, glory and praises be unto Him forever. Now dear
                  friends in this quickening spirit, wherewith you are quickened out of the sleep
                  and death of corruption, where Christ hath given you light, walk in Him, learn of
                  Him, who is lowly, who is meek; and be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to
                  wrath, and keep down and baulk that part which receives a prejudice; search
                  narrowly, and beware that you receive it not from a wrong spirit, for that will
                  wrong the innocent; and the simplicity both in yourselves and others; it is hard
                  to know the spiritual wickedness in high places, and it is with the spiritual
                  weapons of the living God, that you can wrestle with the principalities and powers
                  of spiritual wicked- ness; and it is the brightness of His coming, and the spirit
                  of His mouth, that can reveal the man of sin, the son of perdition, that sitteth
                  in the temple of God, exalted above all that is called God, showing himself as
                  God. This is narrow and deep to discern between him that showeth himself as God,
                  and is not, and him that is the true image indeed.</p>
               <p>Dear Friends, this I write unto you in tender and in dear love to the Seed of God
                  in you all, for which my soul travails; knowing and being acquainted with the
                  danger of this spirit, which measures itself by itself, which the Apostle said was
                  not wise, for such will boast of things without their measure, and will boast of
                  other men's lines. Now that ye may know, and feel the life and power of every
                  spirit; knowing the pure life in yourselves, you will come to savour it in others;
                  and that which savours of the death, will be death to the life, in the fear of the
                  Lord God. Beware of stifling the pure birth of God in you, and of wronging the
                  pure innocent seed in you, which God is coming to plead the cause of in all flesh
                  in this day. And beware that you join not with God's enemies, either in yourselves
                  or others; but join with God's pure witness and testimony, and there will be your
                  peace. And here you will know Him, who is the life, and the resurrection; he that
                  believes in Him, though he were dead, yet shall he live; and there is no other
                  name under heaven, whereby any shall be saved, than by that name, which is better
                  than every name; to which every knee shall bow, and every tongue confess; but
                  there are none that know this name, but he that hath the white stone, in which it
                  is written.</p>
               <closer><salute>From a true friend of the Seed of God in all
                     nations.</salute><signed> Margaret Fell.</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>AN EPISTLE TO FRIENDS, 1659.</p>
               <p>My dearly beloved Brethren and Sisters, in the everlasting truth, and eternal
                  love, and power of an endless life, into which we were begotten, and have been
                  nursed up, and kept in, as living stones growing up in the temple of the living
                  God; the same power and arm is present with you, and owns you; therefore keep in
                  it, and let your faith stand in the power and life of God in every particular; and
                  in that book of life will you read me near, as if pre- sent, in the everlasting
                  covenant and bond of peace, which is never to be broken; and in that love of Jesus
                  Christ, which none can separate us from, height nor depth, life nor death. The
                  eternal God keep you, who brought again our Lord Jesus Christ from the dead,
                  through the blood of the everlasting covenant; and by His blood wash you, and
                  cleanse you from all sin, and all that would separate from God \ that you may have
                  fellowship one with another in the eternal light and life, and there I leave you;
                  and to the Word of His eternal power I commit you, and commend you to His eternal
                  Arm, which is able to save your souls, and to keep you up to Himself. M. F.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>AN EPISTLE TO FKIENDS IN IRELAND, IN 1661.</p>
               <p>My dear love in the Lord God Almighty is unto you all, which never changeth, but
                  endures for- evermore; which love as it is lived in, preserves and keeps to the
                  Lord God and His commandments, laws and statutes; which love is the fulfilling of
                  the whole law of God, and answers to all commands, in thought, word and action.
                  And this keeps clean, low and in- nocent, and moulds us into its own frame and
                  temper, and so brings to be a new lump, leavened into the bowels of everlasting
                  love, which reacheth unto all, and ex- tends unto all, even unto enemies. Oh!
                  blessed and happy are all they that are come into this sweet being of universal
                  love, which would have all to be saved, and come to the knowledge of the truth.
                  This is the image and nature of the blessed God, that holds forth His tender hand,
                  and everlasting love, unto all people, nations, languages, kindreds and tongues,
                  who is no respecter of persons, but every nation that fears God, and worketh
                  righteousness, is ac- cepted with Him, whose call is to every one that thirsteth,
                  come, and whosoever is athirst, let him come and drink of the water of life
                  freely. Oh! the infinite love and bowels of everlasting life and fulness that
                  dwells in His blessed bosom, righteousness and peace is the habitation of His
                  throne. Oh! my dear lambs, let the issues of life be kept open, that issueth into
                  your souls, from this blessed fountain, that you may feel it always open unto you,
                  and you open unto it, that you may always feel it fresh and new, flowing into your
                  souls. So will you feel the word of the Lord God sweeter unto you than the honey,
                  or the honey-comb; and so will you come truly to know, that man liveth not by
                  bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth from the Lord God; here stands the
                  life of men, and so to do the will of the Lord God, will be meat and drink unto
                  you, and will be more delightful than your ordinary food; and then will not
                  sufferings, trials and hardships be strange unto you; knowing that the Captain of
                  your salvation, who is gone before you, is made perfect through sufferings; who in
                  the days of His flesh, when He had offered up prayers and supplications; with
                  strong crying and tears unto Him that was able to save Him, because He feared;
                  though He was a Son, yet learned He obedience by the things which He suffered, and
                  so must all that follow His steps; the servants are not greater than their Lord;
                  and blessed and happy are all they that learn this lesson in the power of God, not
                  only to believe on Him, but also to suffer for His sake; for they who suffer for
                  Him, shall also reign over their enemies with Him; and in His power will they
                  subdue and conquer at the last, for the Lamb and His followers shall have the
                  victory.</p>
               <p>And so, my dearly beloved, be strong in the Lord and in the power of His might,
                  and be faithful, and bold, and true to your Maker, and he will be a hus- band unto
                  you, and set your feet upon the rock most sure, that if the storms beat, and the
                  tempests blow, yet you will not be shaken, for He that keepeth you is greater than
                  all, and none is able to pluck you out of His hand. Into whose arm and power I
                  commit you, everlastingly to dwell and abide with the Lord God, with whom all
                  things are possible. The God of love, whose mercies fail not, preserve and keep
                  you all, and nurse you up in His own bosom, to His own praise and glory, that you
                  may be a people saved by the Lord.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>From your dear friend and sister,</salute>
                  <signed>M. Fell.</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg101">
               <p>PRINCIPAL WORKS</p>
               <p>MARGARET FOX.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <p>Her principal works are: "A Call to the Jews out of Babylon" addressed to
                  Mannassah Ben Israel, a famous Jewish Rabbi, then in England.</p>
               <p>"A Testimony of the Touch Stone for all Professors, &amp;c, to try their ground
                  and foundation by;" both published in 1656.</p>
               <p>"A Loving Salutation to the Seed of Abraham among the Jews," &amp;c.</p>
               <p>" Women's Speaking justified, proved and allowed by the Scriptures, all such as
                  speak by the spirit and power of the Lord Jesus," &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And "A Touch Stone, or Trial by the Scriptures of the Priests, Bishops and
                  Ministers who have called themselves Ministers of the Gospel," &amp;c.; besides
                  numerous others of minor importance.</p>
               <p>In " A Touch Stone, or Trial by the Scriptures," &amp;c, she thus describes the
                  nature, design and effect of true spiritual worship, and Christian ministry, which
                  she contrasts with the dry, formal worship which so much prevailed among the
                  professors of religion in that day: —</p>
               <p>"Christ when he spake to the woman of Samaria, and she told him that their fathers
                  worshipped in that mountain of Samaria, Jesus saith unto her, Wo- man believe me,
                  the hour cometh, when ye shall nei- ther in this mountain, nor yet at Jerusalem,
                  worship the Father; but the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worshippers
                  shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth, for the Father seeketh such to
                  worship Him; God is a spirit, and they that worship Him must worship Him in spirit
                  and in truth: and to this purpose Jesus spake unto Nicodemus, who came unto Him by
                  night, when He said unto him, Verily, verily I say unto thee, except a man be born
                  again, he cannot see the kingdom of God. At which words Nicodemus wondered; but
                  Jesus answered, Except a man be born of water and the spirit, he cannot enter into
                  the kingdom of God. That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is
                  born of the spirit is spirit. Marvel not that I said unto thee, ye must be born
                  again; the wind bloweth where it listeth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And to this purpose was the man, whose name was John, sent of God, to bear witness
                  of Christ Jesus the light, that all men through him might believe. He was not that
                  light, but was sent to bear witness of that light, that was the true light, which
                  lighteth every man that cometh into the world. He was in the world, and the world
                  was made by Him. Which was born not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of
                  the will of man, but of God. John bore wit- ness of Him^ and cried, saying, This
                  is He of whom I spake, He that cometh after me, is preferred before me; and of His
                  fulness have we all received grace for grace.</p>
               <p>And to bring people to this light and spirit of the the Lord within them, did
                  Christ Jesus and all His holy apostles endeavour by their preaching; there- fore
                  said Jesus Christ unto Nicodemus, We speak what we know, and testify what we have
                  seen, and ye receive not our witness. This is the condemnation that light is come
                  into the world, and men love dark- ness rather than light, because their deeds are
                  evil. For every one that doeth evil hateth the light, lest his deeds should be
                  reproved; but he that doeth truth, cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made
                  manifest, that they are wrought in God. This is Christ's doctrine and worship.</p>
               <p>"And when He was preaching among His disci- ples, and the Scribes and Pharisees
                  heard Him, and many believed among the chief, but they did not confess Him,
                  because of the Pharisees, lest they should be put out of the synagogue; Jesus
                  cried out among them, and said, He that believeth in me, believeth not in me, but
                  in Him that sent me. I am come a light into the world, that whosoever be- lieveth
                  in me, should not abide in darkness. And if any man hear my words, and believe
                  not, I judge him not, for I came not to judge the world, but to save the world. He
                  that rejecteth me, and re- ceiveth not my words, hath One that judgeth him; the
                  word that I have spoken shall judge him at the last day.</p>
               <p>"And Christ told the Pharisees that the kingdom of God came not by observation;
                  but the kingdom of God was within them. And when He sent forth His disciples, He
                  saith, As ye go, preach, saying the kingdom of God is at hand. Also when He sent
                  out the seventy, He said, Heal the sick that are therein; and say the kingdom of
                  God is nigh unto you. And we also see by the epistles of the apostles, which are
                  left upon record, after what manner of doctrine and exhortation they spake unto
                  the people. . . .</p>
               <p>"When Peter speaketh of his beloved brother Paul and of his epistles, which he had
                  written, and what he spake; some things, he saith, are hard to be understood,
                  which they that are unlearned and un- stable wrest, as they do also the other
                  Scriptures, unto their own destruction. So they that have not the inspiration of
                  the Almighty, and motion of the Spirit of the Lord God, the same that gave forth
                  the Scriptures, when they come to interpret them, and give meanings to them, being
                  unlearned therein, they just wrest them to their own destruction, and therefore
                  they do not profit the people at all. These be they who separate themselves; men
                  that are sen- sual, not having the Spirit. . . .</p>
               <p>"Also the Apostle Paul in Romans, where he is speaking of his heart's desire and
                  prayer to God for Israel, he tells them, That Christ is the end of the law to
                  every one that belie veth. For, saith he, the righteousness of faith speaketh in
                  this wise, say not in thy heart who shall ascend into heaven, that is to bring
                  Christ .down from above? or who shall descend into the deep, that is to bring
                  Christ up again from the dead? But what saith it? The Word is nigh thee, even in
                  thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is the word of faith which we preach.</p>
               <p>"And when he wrote to the Hebrews he rehearseth the new covenant, that the
                  prophets Isaiah and Jeremiah had prophesied of, and saith, this is the cove- nant
                  that I will make with them after those days, saith the Lord, I will put my laws
                  into their hearts, and in their minds will I write them. These, with many more
                  places of Scripture, might be instanced of the apostles, how they ministered both
                  in preach- ing and writing.</p>
               <p>"And in the first epistle of John, he saith, That which was from the beginning,
                  which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, and our hands have handled
                  of the Word of life: this we de- clare unto you, that ye may have fellowship with
                  us; and truly our fellowship is with the Father, and with His Son Jesus Christ.
                  Here was a right minister of God, that would have had those he wrote to, be in
                  fellowship with him, who was in fellow- ship with the Father and with the Son; and
                  there- fore he saith unto them, these things I write unto you, that your joy may
                  be full. This then is the message which we have heard from him, and de- clared
                  unto you, that God is light, and in Him is no darkness at all. If we say we have
                  fellowship with Him and walk in darkness, we lie and do not the truth; but if we
                  walk in the light, as He is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and
                  the blood of Jesus Christ His Son cleanseth us from all sin. And again, the same
                  apostle saith, A new commandment I write unto you; which thing is true in him and
                  in you; because the darkness is past, and the true light now shineth. Let that,
                  therefore, abide in you which ye have heard from the beginning. If that which ye
                  have heard from the beginning shall abide in you, ye shall also con- tinue in the
                  Son, and in the Father. These things have I written unto you, concerning them that
                  seduce you; but the anointing, which ye have received of Him, abideth in you; and
                  ye need not that any man teach you, but as the same anointing teacheth you of all
                  things, and is truth, and no lie; even as He hath taught you ye shall abide in
                  Him: For ye have an unction from the Holy One, and ye know all things."</p>
               <p>In "A Testimony of the Touch Stone for all Pro- fessors, and all forms and
                  gathered Churches, &amp;c, to try their ground and foundation by," she directs
                  them to the light of Christ in themselves as a sure guide to holiness. A few
                  extracts are given, to show her manner of treating the subject.</p>
               <p>" Now is the light of the glorious gospel risen, and beautiful upon the mountains
                  are the feet of them that bring glad tidings of this gospel, that publish peace,
                  that say unto Zion, thy King reigneth. To all who desire to know the way to Zion
                  doth this voice cry to turn their faces to the light of Jesus Christ, who came
                  riding upon an ass' colt, to the joy and rejoicing of all Zion's children.
                  Therefore turn again all yon who are wandering from mountain to hill, seeking rest
                  but finding none. Turn to the light in every one of your consciences; this is the
                  word of faith which we preach, which Moses taught Israel, and the apostle Paul the
                  Romans, which is nigh in the mouth, and in the heart. Here is your teacher, if you
                  hearken to the pure light, which shows you the deceit of your hearts and your
                  unclean thoughts, from which proceeds uncleanness which the light makes manifest,
                  which will rip you up and reprove you in secret. The Lord God of life and power is
                  fulfilling His everlasting covenant in this His day, He is writing His law in the
                  heart and put- ting it in the inward parts, that none need say know the Lord, but
                  all who turn to the measure of God shall know Him, from the least to the greatest
                  of them. And by no other way or name under heaven shall ye know the living God,
                  but by this pure light and law written in the heart. Here will ye come to witness
                  the Lord to be your God, and your King, and your Law-giver, which all the
                  professions of the world are ignorant of; therefore to this pure mea- sure of God
                  in your inward parts have your minds, that ye may come to witness cleansing and
                  purging within, that ye may come to see the uncleanness which proceeds out of the
                  heart, which defiles the man. For out of the heart cometh evil thoughts, murders,
                  adulteries, fornications, thefts, false testi- mony, slanders; these are the
                  things which defile a man.</p>

               <p>And now you teachers and professors who look without you, and turn from this,
                  which should cleanse within, how do you look that that which is without you,
                  should cleanse from this uncleanness within? Let that of Grod in your consciences
                  see how you can be cleansed by this, when ye turn from it. But if ye turn to the
                  light which makes these things manifest, and dwell and abide in it, then will ye
                  abstain from them, and so come to witness cleansing. For he that walketh in the
                  light, as God is in the light, the blood of Jesus cleanseth from all sin. And
                  Christ Jesus saith, A good man out of the good treasure of his heart, bringeth
                  forth that which is good; and an evil man out of the evil treasure of his heart,
                  bringeth forth that which is evil; for out of the abundance of his heart his mouth
                  speaketh. And why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say?
                  Whosoever cometh to me and heareth my sayings, and doeth them, I will show you to
                  whom he is like; he is like a man which built an house and digged deep, and laid
                  the foundation on a rock, and when the floods arose, the streams beat violently
                  upon the house, and could not shake it, for it was built upon a rock. But he that
                  heareth and doeth not, is like a man, that without a foundation built an house
                  upon the earth, against which the streams did beat violently, and immediately it
                  fell, and the fall of that house was great.</p>
               <p>Now professors here's your building, eternally you shall witness this parable
                  fulfilled upon you, the tempest and storms are coming, your house will be beaten"
                  down, it cannot stand, for you have been sayers a long time and not doers of the
                  word; your bouse which you have built is without founda- tion, it is not founded
                  upon the rock Christ Jesus. Ye who deny the light, He sayeth unto you, Why call ye
                  me Lord, and do not the things which I say ? upon Him shall ye be beaten to
                  pieces, and all your profession. It is known and seen, ye are made mani- fest, ye
                  cannot hide yourselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg110">
               <p>SWARTHMORE HALL.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <p>The following description, of the present state and appearance of Swarthmore Hall,
                  is taken from Armistead's Select Miscellanies: —</p>
               <p>"The Hall, though still a building of considerable size, is no longer what it once
                  was ; a large portion having become ruinated has been altogether re- moved; the
                  oriel window from which George Fox preached to the people in the orchard still
                  remains, and it is believed the owner of the property is bound to accommodate any
                  travelling Friend with a bed. The hospitality of the Friends of Ulverston,
                  however, prevents this right being demanded; and no instance has been known within
                  memory, of any Friend exercising his privilege. The old bedstead bequeathed by
                  George Fox, used to be kept here, and may possibly still remain. The room in which
                  Friends held their meetings for the first forty years, and which were generally
                  graced with the attend- ance of George or Margaret Fox, and others of the
                  society's parents in Christ, remains in its pristine state, having an embrasured
                  window, and a raised dais at one end, which served for a minister's gallery.</p>
               <p>The situation of the Hall is somewhat singular and picturesque. Eastward of it, to
                  the bay of Morecambe, extends a tract of rich champaign country, rivalling for
                  beauty, wood and fertility any county in England; the Swarthmore Hall estate for-
                  merly comprised much of this. Westward extends the bleak tract of Swarthmoor
                  recently enclosed, but still strongly contrasting with the rich pasture of the
                  opposite view. Northward may be discerned the town of Ulverston, and beyond the
                  pointed mountains of Coniston and the Lake district. The immediate neighbourhood
                  of the Hall is occupied by an ancient grove of forest trees, partially screening
                  from view the barren common, while at the foot of the orchard is a woody dell,
                  through which a stream murmurs over its pebbly bed.</p>
               <p>The meeting-house is a solitary building, a quarter of a mile from the Hall; it is
                  entered in the good old-fashioned way, through a porch, with a bench on each side,
                  and over the door the inscription: Ex dono G. F., 1688 (the gift of George Fox,
                  1688). It is commonly supposed he used to attend this meet- ing. Such, however, is
                  not the case; he never sat in it, being in the south of England from its comple-
                  tion until his decease. It was, however, built at his cost, and on land given by
                  him — the only piece of land he ever possessed in England. On entering the passage
                  leading forward from the porch, two black ebony pillars, plain and slender, are
                  seen, one on each side, supporting the ceiling. They are some- times called George
                  Fox's bed-posts, and rightly so, being the posts of the bedstead mentioned before.
                  It was considered the best way of preserving the two principal posts, as well as
                  to bring them under the notice of strangers, to place them in this situation. Then there are also two
                  massive arm-chairs, of solid oak, adorned with carved work; they belonged to
                  George Fox and his wife, and were removed hither from the Hall.</p>
               <p>Adjoining the meeting-house is the burial-ground, which is somewhat modern. The
                  old burial-ground lies at Sunbreak, about a mile and a half distant, and is to
                  many a spot of peculiar and intense interest. It is at the edge of a barren moor,
                  the higher part of which consists of naked limestone, and at the highest point of
                  all is the remains of a beacon. About a third of a mile south of this beacon,
                  where the culti- vated land begins, is a small enclosure, surrounded with an eight
                  foot wall, and entered by a low, narrow door. This, for about the first seventy
                  years of the society's existence, was the burial-place belonging to Swarthmore
                  meeting.</p>
               <p>Here lie the remains of many that braved persecution and suffering for
                  conscience' sake, and so ob- tained for us the privileges we enjoy. Many valiants
                  in the cause of truth have here been laid, when freed from the troubles of time;
                  amongst them lie the re- mains of Margaret Fox, emphatically a mother in Israel,
                  whose sufferings were rendered more poignant from previous affluence, her body
                  imprisoned, and her estate premunired, yet her noble spirit remained unbroken."
                  </p>
               <p>THE END</p>
              
            </div>
   
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
