<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> Observations on the Visiting, Superintendence, and Government of Female
               Prisoners</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>A TEI project created for Z656: Digital Publishing Standards and Systems, Spring
               2018. (Indiana University Bloomington, School of Informatics &amp; Computing,
               Department of Information and Library Science. Book digitized by Google from the
               library of Harvard University and uploaded to the Internet Archive by user tpb.
               Reproduction of original from Goldsmiths' Library, University of London.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                        <surname>Fri</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main"> Observations on the Visiting, Superintendence, and Government
                     of Female Prisoners </title>
                  <title type="apa">Observations on the visiting, superintendence, and government of
                     female prisoners</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher> HATCHARD &amp; SON</publisher>
                     <date>1827</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle rendition="center">
               <titlePart> OBSERVATIONS</titlePart>
               <titlePart>ON THE </titlePart>
               <titlePart>VISITING, SUPERINTENDENCE, AND GOVERNMENT, </titlePart>
               <titlePart> of </titlePart>
               <titlePart> FEMALE PRISONERS. </titlePart>

            </docTitle>
            <docAuthor> BY ELIZABETH FRY </docAuthor>

            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace> London:</pubPlace> PUBLISHED By <publisher> JOHN AND ARTHUR ARCH,
                  CORNHILL;</publisher>
               <publisher> HATCHARD &amp; SON, PICCADILLY; </publisher> AND <publisher> BT S.
                  'WILKIN, NORWICH. </publisher>
               <date>1827</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>

         <div type="toc">

            <head> TABLE OF CONTENTS. </head>
            <list rendition="smallcaps">


               <item> CHAP. I. Introductory remarks <ptr target="pg1"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. II. On the formation of ladies' committees for visiting and
                  superintending Females in Prison <ptr target="pg10"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. III. On the Method of Proceeding in a Prison, After the Formation of a
                  Visiting Committee, and on the Proper Deportment of the Visiters <ptr
                     target="pg15"/>
               </item>

               <item> CHAP. IV. On Female Officers in Prisons <ptr target="pg26"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. V. On separate prisons for females, and on inspection and
                     classification<ptr target="pg31"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. VI. On instruction <ptr target="pg40"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. VII. On employment <ptr target="pg48"/>
               </item>

               <item> CHAP. VIII. On medical attendance, diet, clothing and bedding, and firing <ptr
                     target="pg54"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. IX. On the Attention Required by Female Criminals on Their Leaving Prison
                     <ptr target="pg63"/>
               </item>

               <item>CHAP. X. Conclusion <ptr target="pg67"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg1">
            <p>CHAPTER 1.</p>
            <p>INTRODUCTORY REMARKS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Well knowing my incompetency for the task of writing for the public, I have felt
               consid- erable reluctance in sending to the press the following brief observations
               respecting the principles and plans adopted by the British Ladies' Society for
               visiting f^isons : but, my long experience of the nature and effects of the system
               pursued by that Society, and the numerous applications made to me for farther
               explanation and information on this interest- ing subject, induce me to make an
               attempt, on which^ I should not otherwise have ventured. Before, however, I endeavour
               to develop the system of the British Society, I wish to make a few general remarks,
               which have long impressed me, respecting my own sex, and the place which I believe it
               to be their duty and privilege to fill in the scale of soci- ety. I rejoice to see
               the day in which so many women of every rank, instead of spend- ing their time in
               trifling and unprofitable pur- suits, are engaged in works of usefulness and charity.
               Earnestly is it to be desired that the number of these valuable labourers in the
               cause of virtue and humanity may be in- creased, and that all of us may be made sen-
               sible of the infinite importance of redeeming the time, of turning our talents to
               account, and of becoming the faithful, humble, devo^ ted, followers of a crucified
               Lord, who went about DOING GOOD.</p>
            <p>Far be it from me to attempt to persuade women to forsake their right province. My
               only desire is, that they should^// that pro^ vince well; and, although their
               calling, in many respects, materially differs from that of the other sex, and may not
               perhaps be so ex- alted an one — yet a minute obiiervation will prove that,if
               adequately fulfilled, it has nearly, if not quite, an equal influence on society at
               large.</p>

            <p>No person will deny the importance at- tached to the character and conduct of a
               woman, in all her domestic and social rela- tions, when she is filling the station of
               a daughter, a sister, a wife, a mother, or a mis- tress of a family. But it is a
               dangerous error to suppose that the duties of females end here. Their gentleness,
               their natural sympathy with the afflicted, their quickness of discernment, their
               openness to religious impressions, are points of character (not un- usually to be
               found in our sex) which evi- dently qualify them, within their own pecu- liar
               province, for a far more extensive field of usefulness.</p>
            <p>In endeavouring to direct the attention of the female part of society to such objects
               of Christian charity as they are most calculated to benefit, I may now observe that
               no per- sons appear to me to possess so strong a claim on their compassion, and on
               their pious exertions, as the helpless, the ignorant, the afflicted, or the depraved,
               of their awn sex. It is almost needless to remark, that a mul- titude of such persons
               may be found in many of our public institutions.</p>

            <p>During the last ten years much attention has been successfully bestowed by women on
               the female inmates of our prisons; and many a poor prisoner, under their fostering
               care, has become completely changed,— rescued from a condition of depravity and
               wretched- ness, and restored to happiness, as a useful and respectable member of the
               community. Most desirable is it that such efforts should be pursued with patient
               perseverance where- ever they have been already made, and that they should be
               gradually extended to all the prisons in the kingdom.</p>
            <p>But a similar care is evidently required for our hospitals, our lunatic asylums, and
               our workhouses. It is quite obvious, that there are departments in all such
               institutions which ought to be under the especial super- intendence of females. Were
               ladies to make a practice of regula^'ly visiting them, a most important check would
               be obtained on a variety of abuses, which are far too apt to creep into the
               management of these estab- lishments. Such a practice would be the means, not only of
               essentially contributing to the welfare of the afflicted sufferers, but of materially
               aiding those gentlemen, on, whom devolves the government or care of the institntions.
               The Roman Catholic ladies, in many parts of the continent of Europe, have set us, in
               this respect, a bright and useful example; and the result of their care and
               attention, especially in the hospitals, has been found, in a high degree, salutary
               and beneficial. Nor have similar effects failed to be produced in the comparatively
               soli- tary instances in which women, in our own country, have been in the habit of
               regularly visiting the public abodes of poverty or disease.</p>
            <p>While I would direct the attention of my own sex (in whose usefulness I take a very
               lively interest) to the importance of theii visiting and superintending the females
               in our public institutions, I am far indeed from desiring to discourage them in other
               and more private walks of Christian charity. Among the most interesting exertions of
               female benevolence, will ever be numbered the visiting of the poor in their own
               habita- tions, the necessary attention to the supply of their temporal and spiritual
               wants, and above all, the diligent promotio*^ of the edu- cation of their children;
               but the economical arrangement of time, and more especially a suitable division of
               labor, will enable the benevolent females of any place or district to accomplish,
               without material difficulty, all their charitable objects. Regard ought always to be
               had to the age and circumstances of individuals. For example, a young lady may be
               well employed in attending to a school, or in visiting a sick neighbour, who would be
               very far less suitable than the more elderly and experienced for the care of the
               hospital, the workhouse, the asylum » or the prison; and yet, the one service will in
               time form an admirable preparation for the other.</p>
            <p>Much may be accomplished by the unmi af forces. — If, in every parish or district,
               such ladies, as desire to make the best use of their time, would occasionally meet
               together, in order to consider the condition of their neighbourhood, and would then
               divide them- selves and allot the labours of Christian love to the several parties
               respectively, according to their suitability for different objects, the employment of
               but a small portion of their time would enable them to effect more exten- sive good
               than could previously have been thought possible; and, instead of being inca-
               pacitated for their domestic duties, they would often return to those duties,
               refreshed in spi- rit, and stimulated to perform them with in- ci*eased cheerfulness,
               propriety, and diligence. To revert, for a short time, to the subject of our public
               institutions, although I feel it a delicate matter so earnestly to insist on the
               point, I must now express my conviction, that few persons are aware of the degree in
               which the female departments of them stand in need of the superintending care of
               judi- cious ladies. So great are the abuses which exist in some of those
               establishments, that modest women dare not run the risk to which they would be
               exposed, did they attempt to derive from them the relief which they re-^ quire. I
               would have this subject occupy the serious consideration of the benevolent part of
               the community. All reflecting per- sons will surely unite in the sentiment, that the
               female,placed in the prison for her crimes, in the hospital for her sickness, in the
               asylum for her insanity, or in the workhouse for her poverty, possesses no hght or
               common claim on the pity and attention of those of her own sex, who, through the
               bounty of a kind Pro- vidence, are able " to do good, and to com- municate'*</p>
            <p>May the attention of women be more and more directed to these labors of love; and may
               the- time quickly arrive, when there shall not exist, in this realm, a single public
               in^ stitution of the kind, in which the degraded or afflicted females who may happen
               to be its inmates shall not enjoy the efficacious su^ perintendence of the pious and
               benevolent of THEIR OWN sex!</p>
            <p>Having expressed my general views re- specting the importance and right application
               of the benevolent exertions of women in aid of the unfortunate of their own sex, I
               may now proceed to offer to the reader a few remarks respecting the system pursued
               and recommended by the members of the British Ladies' Society in visiting and
               superintend- ing the female inmates of our prisons. My observations, and the advice
               which I shall venture to offer, will be found to relate to the following successive
               points. Mrst, the formation of Ladies' Committees, Se- condlt/y the proper deportment
               of the visiters towards the prisoners and towards the offi- cers of the prison.
               Thirdly, the necessity of employing female officers in gaols, and their proper
               character. Fourthly , classifica- tion and inspection. Fifthly, instruction. Sixthly,
               employment. Seventhly, medical aid, food, clothing, and bedding. And, last- ly, the
               attention required in the care of cri- minals after their dismissal from prison.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pf10">
            <p>CHAPTER II.</p>
            <p>ON THE FORMATION OF LADIES' COMMITTEES FOR VISITING AND SUPERINTENDING FEMALES IN
               PRISON.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Highly desirable as it is that even indivi- dual women, who can obtain no coadjutors
               in the work, should devote part of their time to the important object of visiting
               prisons, there are many obvious reasons why the formation of regular committees for
               the purpose, wherever found possible is greatly preferable.</p>
            <p>In the first place, since our life and health are uncertain, and even our abode
               frequently liable to change, the association of two or more persons in the
               prosecution of such ob- jects is indispensable to their being steadily and constantly
               pursued: thus, when one labourer fails, the work will not cease, and others will be
               ready to supply her place.</p>
            <p>There are, secondly, a variety of engagements for those who undertake the care of
               female prisoners; and these engagements will be found suited to a variety of persons.
               For instance, one may attend to the employ- ment, a second to the classification, a
               third to the instruction, of the prisoners: while, in the conducting of certain parts
               of the system — such particularly as appertain to the religious improvement of the
               prisoners — all the visiters will unite.</p>
            <p>In the third place, where there are several visiters no individual among them is
               requir- ed to give up for the object more than a very limited portion of time. 'If,
               for example, there are seven ladies on the committee, the prison may be properly
               attended to, if each visiter will devote to the purpose a part of one morning only in
               the week.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a committee will often arrive at sounder and wiser conclusions on any
               practical question than an individual would be likely to form. The ladies who compose
               such a committee may mutually assist each other's judgment, and support one another
               in their respective exertions.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the business in hand, under the care of a regular and judicious committee,
               will be generally conducted with greater order, method, and regularity, than will
               probably attach to the efforts of any solitary individual.</p>
            <p>And lastly, when representations are to be made, or requests preferred, to
               magistrates or other persons in authority, the delibera- tion and sanction of a
               committee will give them their due weight.</p>
            <p>On these grounds I would strongly advise any lady, who is disposed to enter upon the
               important work of visiting a prison, to look round, in the first instance, for
               persons who may unite with her in its prosecution; and my experience leads me to
               believe that there are few, if any, prisons in the kingdom, in the neighbourhood of
               which some benevo-- lent ladies may not be found, who will be both able and willing
               to engage in this in- teresting task* When ladies have thus united for the purpose,
               it will of course be necessary^ before they proceed to put their plan in execution,
               to obtain the sanction of the magistrates under whose authority the prison is placed.
               And here I would remark that, since persons of rank and inflnence in society are
               often able, from their peculiar situation, to remove difficulties which might
               otherwise be insuperable, some lady in the neighbourhood, of this description, ought
               to be invited to act as patroness or president of the committee. Much advantage will
               also arise from a regular yearly correspond- ence with the committee of the British
               Society in London.</p>
            <p>The following resolutions are recommend- ed by that society, as proper to be adopted
               by local associations:</p>
            <p>I. That we form onrselves into an association, in connexion with *' the British
               Society of Ladies/' for the purpose of promoting^ the reformation of the female
               prisoners in the jails of this town (or city) and its immediate vicinity, and that it
               be denominated "The Prison Association."</p>
            <p>II. That the concerns of this association shall be conducted by a committee, to be
               chosen annually, consisting of a treasurer, secretary, and not less than six other
               members, eligible to reappointment.</p>
            <p>III. That the committee meet monthly, on some day, to be fixed by themselves, and
               that three members be competent to transact business.</p>

            <p>IV. That the committee appoint six visiters for the moDth, inserting in the minate of
               appoint- ment the day on which each is expected to attend; and that a class-book be
               provided, in which the visiters are to notice the conduct of the women, as a gaide in
               the distribution of prizes.</p>
            <p>V. That a code of Rules for the regulation of the conduct of the prisoners be hung up
               in every ward of the prison, and read to the women once a week.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg15">
            <p>CHAPTER III.</p>

            <p>ON THE METHOD OF PROCEEDING IN A PRISON, AFTER THE FORMATION OF A VISITING COMMITTEE,
               AND ON THE PROPER DEPORTMENT OF THE VISITERS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>When a Ladies' Association for visiting any particular prison has been formed, and
               when the sanction of the Magistrates has been obtained for their undertaking, the
               Commit- tee (consisting probably of but a few, and those judicious, individuals) will
               of course take an early opportunity of meeting in the females* department of the
               prison. They will then call the prisoners together, and explain to them their motives
               and views in undertaking to assist and superintend them* They will express their
               sympathy with them under their afflicting circumstances, soothe them with words of
               gentleness and kindness, and endeavour to hold up, in strong colours, the danger and
               misery of vice, the beauty o holiness and the innumerable advantages which attach to
               a life of sobriety, industry, honesty, and virtue. When the attention of the
               prisoners has been thus engaged, and their better feeHngs excited, it will be
               necessary to propose a series of rules for their future conduct. To these rules they
               may be expected, in the 6rst place, to give their deliberate and voluntary assent;
               and secondly, to consider themselves fiiraly bound to adhere to them, during their
               con- tinuance in prison. Experience has amply proved, that when prisoners are
               tenderly treated, there is a general willingness to sub* mit to such regulations as
               the ladies who visit them may propose for their conduct and improvement.</p>
            <p>The following rules, which were unani* mously adopted in the prison of Newgate, when
               the Association of Visiters was formed^ for the benefit of its female inmates, will
               afford some notion of the general system pursued by the visiters, and of the conduct
               enjoined on the objects of their care.</p>

            <p>RULES FOR REGULATING CHG CONDUCT OF THf! FEMALE PRISONERS IN NEWGATE.</p>
            <p>I. The Matron, on behalf of '*The Association for the Improvement of the Female
               Prisoners in Newgate," has the general superintendence of them, both with respect to
               their conduct and the various kinds of work procured for them, of which dhe is
               required to keep an exact account.</p>
            <p>II. The women, being divided into classes, a monitor, chosen from among the most
               orderly, is intrusted with the particular oversight of each class; and each woman is
               required to wear con- stantly a ticket, denoting the class to which she belongs, and
               her place therein.</p>
            <p>III. One of the most suitable for the office is appointed as keeper of the Women's
               Yard, to pre- vent any disorder there, to inform her fellow-pri- soners, in a proper
               manner, when their friends come to visit them, and to take care that they do not
               spend any time at the grating, (the place where their friends meet them) except
               whilst with their friends.</p>
            <p>IV. No begging is allowed. If money should be offered to the women by any of those
               who regularly visit the prison, they are to decline accepting it; but they may, in a
               respectful manner, direct to the box placed between the gates for receiving
               donations, which, ata suitable time, are divided amongst them.</p>

            <p>V. They are enjoined carefully to guard against every thing that is likely to
               occasion quarrelling or disagreement; not upbraiding one another on ac- count of any
               previous conduct or circumstances; but rather, by.a peaceable and orderly demeanor,
               endeavouring to promote each other s comfort and improvement.</p>
            <p>VI. Swearing, or in any manner taking the "Sacred Name" in vain <note n="1"> See
                  Exod. xx. 7, and 2 Tim. ii, 19. f See 2 Tim. iii, 16, 17.</note>, — all bad words,
               immoral conversation, and indecent behaviour, are to be especially avoided.</p>
            <p>VII. Card-playing, and all other gaming; as also plays, novels, and other pernicious
               books, with all immoral songs, are strictly prohibited.</p>
            <p>VIII. The women are required to attend in the work-room every forenoon (except when
               the cha- pel is open for them), and occasionally in the even- ing, to hear a portion
               of the Holy Scriptures: for which purpose, on the first ringing of the bell, ten
               minutes before the reading commences, the moni- tors are to collect them in their
               respective wards^ that all may be ready at the second ringing, when they are to
               proceed in regular order (each monitor conducting her class) to take their seats, in
               silence; retiring afterwards with the same quietness and regularity.</p>
            <p>IX. Cleanliness, both in their persons and apartments, is particalarly required of
               all the women; also that they be careful to avoid increasing each other's
               difficulties in this respect. And the pledging of any article of apparel is strictly
               forbidden.</p>
            <p>X. The monitors are expected not only to take charge of their own particular classes,
               but also, as they have opportunity, to extend a watchful care over all their fellow-
               prisoners. And they are re- quired (besides applying to the matron whenever her
               interference may appear necessary) to make a regular and faithful report to the
               visiters in at^ tendance, whether or not these rules have been duly observed.</p>
            <p>XI. If a monitor transgress any of the rules, she is to be dismissed from her office,
               and one more orderly selected to take her place.</p>
            <p>XII. Any woman who may consider herself ill- treated by a monitor has full liberty,
               in a civil, quiet manner, to represent her case to a visiter, or the matron : but any
               refractory or unbeeoming beha- viour towards a monitor, who is properly exercis- ing
               her office, must be accounted a serious offence.</p>
            <p>For the encouragement of the women in endea- vouring to conduct themselves well, the
               Association distribute, several times in the year, to all those who prove deserving,
               some useful article, as a reward.</p>
            <p>The great object which the visiters ought always to keep in view is, the reformation
               of the prisoners : and to this principal end all their plans must be subservient. In
               endea- vouring to effect this good purpose, it will of course devolve upon them to
               instruct thie un- lettered in useful elementary knowledge, to bring all to a
               practical acquaintance with Holy Writ, and to train these unfortunate females to
               habits of cleanliness, order, and regular industry. These several objectM mast be
               pursued according to the circum- stances which may attach to any particular prison or
               association; and judicious visiters will seldom be at a loss respecting the pro- per
               application of their efforts in order to ob- tain the results which may be desired. I
               wish, however^ to take the opportunity afforded me, by the present section, of
               throwing out a few hints respecting the general deport- ment desirable in the
               visiters themselves, both towards the prisoners abd towards those persons in
               authority, under whose su- perintending care the prison is placed.</p>
            <p>Much depends on the spirit in which the visiter enters upon her work. It must be the
               spirit, not of judgment, but of mercy.</p>

            <p>She must not say in her hearty / am more holy than thou; but must rather keep in
               perpetual remembrance, that all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God" —
               that, therefore, great pity is doe from ns even to the greatest transgressors among
               our fellow-creatures — and that, in meekness and love, we ought to labor for their
               restoration. The good principle in the hearts of many abandoned persons may be
               compared to the few remaining sparks of a nearly extinguish- tA fire. By means of the
               utmost care and attention, united with the most gentle treat- ment, these may yet be
               fanned into a flame, but, under the operation of a rough and vio- lent hand, they
               will presently disappear, and be lost for ever.</p>
            <p>In our conduct towards these unfortunate females, kindness, gentleness, and true hu-
               mility, ought ever to be united with serenity and firmness. Nor will it be safe ever
               to descend, in our intercourse with them, to familiarity; for there is a dignity in
               the Christian character, which demands, and will obtain, respect, and which is
               powerful in its influence, even over dissolute minds.</p>

            <p>None need be discouraged from express- ing amongst them^ a detestation and abhor-
               rence of sin, and a strong view of its dread- ful consequences. Nevertheless, it is
               seldom salutary to make a pointed application of such remarks to the cases of
               individual criminals; for experience proves, that if those persons who visit them are
               harsh in judging and con- demning them, the effect is hurtful rather than beneficial.
               Neither is it by any means wise, to converse with them on the subject of the crimes
               of which thev are accused or convicted; for such conversation is injurious both^ to
               the criminals themselves and to others who hear them; and, moreover, it frequently
               leads them to add sin to sin, by uttering the grossest falsehoods.</p>
            <p>The visiting ladies must show as much con- fidence in the prisoners as circumstances
               will possibly admit; and, in order to this end, it will be at once salutary and safe
               to intrust them with the care of various articles be- longing to the committee. Marks
               of ap- probation and small rewards ought, also, at times, to be bestowed on them, as
               an encouragement to good conduct. To miss these rewards is generally found to be a
               suf- ficient mortification for the correction of the disorderly. Solitary
               confinement^ which is useful in extreme cases, is, in my opinion, a punishment far
               too severe to be resorted to on any light and trivial occasion.</p>
            <p>Finally, those who engage in the interest-, ing task of visiting criminals must not
               be impatient if they find the work of reform- ation a very slow one. Such it will
               almost necessarily be in the generality of cases. Sensible of the natural corruption
               of our own hearts, let us learn patiently to bear with the hardened and the
               profligate, and let us be faithful and diligent in directing their atten- tion to "
               the Lamb of God which taketh away the sins of the world ;" for it is only by faith in
               Hinij that these poor wanderers can ob- tain the forgiveness of their past sins, or
               be enabled, for the future, to lead a life of true piety and virtue.</p>
            <p>The members of the visiting Committee ought ever to be careful to adhere precisely to
               the rules^ of the prison, and to the direct- ions of the magistrates. Interference
               with these gentlemen, or with any of the officers of the prison, (except those whom
               the ma- gistrates may have placed under their care) must be strictly avoided: yet it
               ought to be the constant endeavour of the visiters to aid the eflforts of those
               persons in authority, who ^have the welfare of the Institution at heart. And many
               such persons are happily found among our magistrates, in the present day. Much
               disadvantage will generally accrue from endeavours on the part of the visiting ladies
               to procure the mitigation of the sen^ tences of criminals. Such endeavours ought
               never to be made, except when the cases are remarkably clear; and then through the
               regular official channels. Deeply as we must deplore the baneful eflFects of the
               punishment of death, and painful as we must feel it to be, that our fellow-creatures,
               in whose welfare we are interested, should be prematurely plunged into an awful
               eternity; yet, while our laws continue as they are, unless they can bring forward
               decided facts in favor of the condemned, it is wiser for the visiting ladies to be
               quiet, and to submit to decrees, which they cannot alter.</p>

            <p>Having thas adverted to several particulars, which require the attention of all per-
               sons who enter upon the interesting engage- ment of visiting prisons, I will conclude
               this chapter with the expression of a desire, that the visiters may be at once ivise
               as ser- pents ^ and harmless as doves; and that Chris- tian love and peace may
               influence their whole conduct towards the objects of their care. Then they may
               entertain a strong confidence that their labor will not be in vain in the Lord!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg26">
            <p>CHAPTER IV. ON FEMALE OFFICERS IN PRISONS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>It is absolutely essential to the proper or- der and regulation of every prison, that
               the female prisoners should be placed under the superintendence of officers of their
               own sex. Females confined in our prisons are, for the most part, persons of light and
               aban- doned character. To place them under the care of men is evidently unreasonable,
               and seldom fails to be injurious to both par- ties. Male turnkeys or other
               subordinate officers of that sex ought never, in my opinion, to have access to the
               female depart- ment of the prison, or to hold any personal communication with its
               inmates, except in the presence of a matron or her assistants. In visiting small
               prisops, I have frequently observed one or two unfortunate young women — committed,
               perhaps, for some minor offence, (such as running away from an apprenticeship, or
               purloining a teaspoon) — placed under the sole care of a man, whose key will at any
               time unlock their door, and afford him admission to their society. This I cannot but
               consider a most unwarrantable and deplorable exposure.</p>
            <p>One matron will be able to maintain far greater order amongst a number of female
               criminals than several male turnkeys. Her influence is less exciting, and is at dnce
               safer and more powerful. She may always con- tinue in their company; may instruct
               them in their feminine duties; and, by a circum- spect example, may prove to these
               poor wanderers from the path of rectitude, the excellence of a modest, regular, and
               well- ordered, life. To such a person also the women under her care can freely
               communi- cate a knowledge of their circumstances; and pour forth their sorrows, as to
               a wise and sympathizing friend.</p>
            <p>Since the passing of the late Act of Par- liament, for the regulation of prisons, our
               large jails have been generally provided with a matron and female turnkeys; but it is
               much to be regretted that in many smaller prisons no such provisions have yet been
               adopted. Nor ought it to be concealed that the persons selected to fill the office of
               ma- tron are, in various instances, unsuitable for their post; and in other cases are
               unfitted for its fulfilment, by residing out of the prison. See 4 Geo. IV, cap. 64.
                  <note n="2"><p>Amongst the rules laid down for the management of prisons, in this
                     admirable act, are the following :</p>
                  <p>Second. — A matron shall he appointed, in every prison in which fenuile
                     prisoners shall be confined, who shall reside in the prison; and it shall be
                     the duty of the matron constantly to superintend the female prisoners</p>
                  <p>Seventh. — Female prisoners shall in all oases be attended by female qfficers:
                     pp. 776, 777.</p></note></p>
            <p>A matron placed over female prisoners ought assuredly to be a resident, not only
               within the walls of the prison, but in the same part of it as are the objects of her
               care; and great caution is ever found to be necessary in the selection of so
               important an officer. She ought never to be chosen be- cause the situation is suited
               to her wants, but only because she is suited to fill the situation. She ought to be a
               person of re- spectable, orderly, and active, habits, — plain in her dress, — gentle,
               yet firm, in her demeanor, — of sufficient edacation to enable her to superintend the
               instruction of the prisoners, — and although not grea^^ elevated abave her chaise,
               yet in a station of life so far superior to their own, as to coknmand their respect
               and obedience. Vigilance, im- partiality, and a willingness to submit to those
               persons under whose authority she is placed, ought to be distinguishing features in
               her character. Widows, from their supe^ rior knowledge of the world and of life, are
               generally preferable for this office, to single women. Above all, it is most
               desirable that persons appointed to fill so responsible a situation should be
               decidedly religious them- selves, and heartily engaged in promoting the reformation
               and spiritual welfare of those whom they are called upon to govern.</p>
            <p>Although much may be effected by a ma- tron, in the care of female" prisoners, it is
               evident that, in all our larger jails, or houses of correction, subordinate officers
               of the same sex will also be required; and these officers, like the matron who
               governs them, ought to be selected with peculiar judgment and care. Let the female
               criminal in prison behold, in every officer who exercises authority over her, a
               consistent example of feminine pro- priety and virtue, and great will be its influ-
               ence towards a happy change of habit and character in herself. May the time quickly
               arrive, when not a single female prisoner in this enlightened kingdom shall be found
               un- der the immediate superintendence of any persons whatsoever, except the sober and
               virtuous of her own sex!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg31">

            <p>CHAPTER V.</p>
            <p>ON SEPARATE PRISONS FOR FEMALES, AND ON INSPECTION AND CLASSIFICATION.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Where men and women are confined in the same buildings as is at present so generally
               the case throughout the prisons of this king- dom^ no means must be neglected to
               ensure the complete separation of the two sexes. But^ as this good end is^ under such
               circum- stances^ extremely liable to be defeated^ it is greatly to be desired, that
               male and female prisoners should be placed in separate buildings so as to render all
               personal communication between them absolutely impossible. The good effect which
               would result from such a measure can hardly be estimated by those who are not aware
               from experience in what a degree "evil communication corrupts good manners." At the
               same time that an invincible barrier to all communication be- tween the sexes would
               greatly tend to order and sobriety among the inmates of a prison and as greatly
               facilitate the duties of the officers, it would add considerable weight and effect to
               the punishment of imprisonment.</p>
            <p>In the castle of Lancaster where a new building ha^ within a few years, been erected
               for female prisoners, the object of absolute separation from those of the other sex
               is in great measure secured — and much is it to be desired that, in every prison
               which may hence- forth be built, so good an example may be carefully followed. Not
               only would such a plan be the most effectual for all the pur- poses of prison
               discipline, but it would lead to the saving of expense. For, a prison for females
               does not require the same strength as one for the other sex, neither do their
               employments demand the same space as those of the men. Add to this, that the sums
               required for the remuneration of female ojficers would be comparatively small.</p>
            <p>Now, on the supposition that a prison were to be erected in any populous district,
               for the exclusive purpose of the confinement of females, I would suggest that, in the
               plan of such a prison, and in the arrangement of its discipline, the two great
               objects to be aimed at would be inspection and classification.</p>
            <p>The apartments of the matron ought to be so arranged, in connexion with the cells,
               the day rooms, and the airing grounds, as to en^ sd&gt;le her to see all the
               prisoners while at work, and in their hours of recreation, and to overhear them
               during the night; but, in case of the number of the prisoners being too large for the
               superintendence and inspec- tion of an individual, the matron may in this respect
               obtain all the assistance she requires from her female turnkeys.</p>
            <p>Whether, however, the object be effected by the sole care of the matron, or by her
               joint eare with that of subordinate officers, vigilant and unremitting inspection is
               unquestionably one of the most essential points in a correct system of prison
               discipline. By this means alone can the evil of corrupt communication be prevented;
               and the certain and constant check which is thus afforded on every vicious practice,
               among the criminals, is eminently calculated to produce in them (though it may be by
               slow degrees) an effectual change of habit.</p>
            <p>With respect to classification, it is in the first place obvious, that a division
               must always be made of the tried from the untried prisoners; and both classes (but
               more especially the former) will require subdivision. In effecting this subdivision,
               I would propose that the tried prisoners should be classed not so much according to
               the nature of the offences of which they are convicted, as according to their general
               character ^nd degree of criminality. When one of the oldest and most hardened of
               offenders is found guilty only of a misdemeanor, and a mere novice in crime, is under
               sentence for the same offence, it is obviously very impro- per that two such persons
               should be classed iu one company. It appears therefore very desirable, that, while
               offences for which the prisoners have been convicted are, with other circumstances,
               kept in view, a discretionary power, as it regards classification, should be allowed
               to rest with the officers of the prison, under the advice and superintendence of the
               visiting Committee of ladies: and the visiters may also be authorised to change from
               time to time, the classification of any prisoner in such a manner as may appear to be
               required by a corresponding change in her conduct.</p>
            <p>However large the number of female convicts, in any prison, may be, I should consider
               it quite needless to divide them into more than four classes; and these classes must
               be formed according to character and conduct.</p>
            <p>In the first, or highest, class ought to be placed women, whose crimes are of ^o deep
               moral dye, and whose demeanor and conduct in the prison are comparatively exemplary.
               This class may enjoy, in a variety of respects, peculiar advantages. Their clothing,
               for example, may be somewhat better, and their labor lighter and less irksome, than
               those of the lower classes. ^ Some pecuniary profit may be attached to their
               employment, and the most orderly individuals in the class may be introduced to
               offices of trust; and thus the number of hired officers in the pri- son may be
               gradually diminished. It is wonderful how much confidence may safely be placed in the
               better sort of female crimi- nals, when, by the influence of Christian kindness, a
               good spirit has once been infus- ed into their minds.</p>
            <p>In the second class, the privileges allowed to the prisoners must, of course, be
               some- what less; and, in the third class, must be yet more considerably
               diminished.</p>
            <p>The last, and lowest, class ought to con- sist of the most hardened and desperate
               offenders, and of those persons who have been committed to the prison more than once.
               This class mnst undergo its peculiar privations and hardships. At the same time,
               since hope is essentially necessary to reform- ation, the females who compose even
               this most degraded of the classes ought — with great care and deliberation — to be
               raised step by step into the higher classes, when their conduct merits it. Such a
               system of gradual promotion vrill be found to operate on the whole body of the
               prisoners as a very powerful stimulus to improvement</p>
            <p>Among untried female prisoners I ques- tion whether any subdivision is necessary
               beyond the separation of modest women from prostitutes. There are many obvious
               reasons why females of these two descriptions should never be classed in one company.
               Now, although the provisions which I have ventured to recommend for the inspec* tion
               and classification of prisoners are ex- tremely desirable, we are not to forget the
               lamentable fact^ that a large proportion of our prisons are at present entirely
               destitpte of the suggested advantages. In too many of them no separation is effected^
               except be^ tween the sexes, or perhaps between the untried prisoners also^ and the
               convicts. la such cases much advantage will be found to arise^ notwithstanding the
               want of separation^ from a subdivision of the prisonei's into classes— ^each class
               being placed under the care of a monitor, whose duty it will be to ren- der either to
               the matron or to a visiter, a daily account of their conduct. Every individual in the
               several classes may wear a ticket in- scribed with a number by which she shall be
               distinguished, and which shall agree with a corresponding number in the class list
               That list most be kept by the matrcm or the visiters, and must contain a register of
               the conduct of every prisoner, formed by marks of approbation or disapprobation,
               placed on parallel lines againjst their respective num- bers. The regular keeping of
               such a regis- ter will be found a useful check on every kind of improper conduct, and
               will form the foundation of a judicious application of re- wards to the most
               deserving prisoners.</p>
            <p>It is indeed worthy of remark that, even in the best arranged prisons, and more es-
               pecially in convict-ships, the plan of num- bering the prisoners will never fail to
               be advantageous. If, for instance, a woman, in any particular class, is distinguished
               by a certain number, this number must not only be found in the class-list connected
               with a register of her conduct, but must be inscri- bed on all the principal articles
               which be- long to her — especially her seat at table, her clothing, her bed and
               bedding, and her books. Such a system is found by experience to be very effectual in
               preventing disputes among the prisoners, and in promoting that strict- ness of
               discipline which is essential to the order and regularity of the whole machine.</p>
            <p>In the preceding remarks on the subject of classification I have not mentioned a sick
               ward. This is a provision of obvious importance; and it is almost needless to observe
               that the inmates of such a ward ought not only to be placed, like the other
               prisoners, under the inspection of the matron, but have strong peculiar claipis on
               her kind and constant attention.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg40">
            <p>CHAPTER VI.</p>
            <p>ON INSTRUCTION.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Among the various objects to which the visiting Committee of ladies will find it^ in
               any prison, their place to attend, the instruc- tion of the prisoners may be
               considered the most interesting and important. It is a me- lancholy reflexion, that
               so large a proportion of the inhabitants of this country — a country possessed of so
               many advantages, and so greatly advanced in civilization — are still left in a
               condition of almost extreme ignorance. This observation applies with peculiar force
               to those who are in the habit of break- ing its laws. Of the female criminals who
               come under the care of the Newgate Com- mittee, about one third are unable to read at
               all — and another third can only read a very little. With regard to the truths of
               religion, the ignorance which prevails amongst them is extreme; and diis is the
               natural consequence of the disadvantages under which they have been brought up: for
               many of them have scarcely ever attended a place of public worship, or heard, or
               read, any part of the Holy Scriptures. Much, therefore, most depend on the
               instruction which such persons receive in prison.</p>
            <p>In the first place, they will there have the advantage of a regular attendance of
               their appointed place of worship — for our prisons are now almost universally
               provided with a chapel and a chaplain; and this opportunity will, in most cases, be
               afforded them more than once in the week. When assembled in the chapel, it is
               indispensable that the women should be completely separate from the male prisoners,
               and quite out of their sight. No- thing must be allowed to divert their atten^ tion,
               or to interrupt the solemnity of the occasion.</p>
            <p>The chaplain of a prison will, of course, find it his duty not only to perform the
               ser- vices of public worship, but to communicate with the prisoners individually, and
               to endeavour, by private persuasion and instruct- ion^ to lead them into the paths of
               virtue, religion, and peace* Greatly is it to be de- sired, that those who occupy
               this import- ant and interesting station, should be them- selves persons of true
               piety. I venture to suggest, that they ought to be married men of established
               character, with some know- ledge of life, as well as religious experience* Much as
               the good order of every prison depends on the conduct and character of the chaplain,
               and desirable as it is that he should fully and faithfully perform his duties^ and
               that the visiting Committee should not interfere with him, I well know that there is
               a part of the moral and religious instruction of female prisoners, which cannot be
               com- municated to them so well, so safely, or so efficaciously, as by the ladies who
               visit the prison. The instruction to which I allude is all of a private nature; but,
               besides this, the assembling of the prisoners together, at least once every day, in
               order to read to them a portion of the Holy Scripture, is a charge which will most
               suitably devolve on the mem- bers of the visiting Committee.</p>
           
            <p>This duty is one of very serious import- ance. It ought never to be lightly performed
               as a mere matter of course; but, when we are engaged in it, our hearts ought ever to
               be lifted up to Him who can alone bless our endeavours. The visiters will do well,
               generally, to select for the purpose the more clear and simple parts of Scripture,
               espe- cially from the New Testament and the Psalms. Nor must they fail to direct the
               especial attention of their hearers to those passages which proclaim the salvation
               offer- ed to lost mankind through a crucified Re- deemer, and which are calculated to
               revive the buried hopes of even the very worst of sinners. The 2dth and 5lst Psalms,
               the 15th chapter of Luke's Gospel, and the 12th of Hebrews, among other portions of
               Scrip- ture, will be found peculiarly applicable to the case of these sinful and
               afflicted persons. To pursue a regular course of reading in the Scriptures — for
               example, to read through the whole New Testament, chapter by chap- ter — is indeed
               desirable where the prisoners continue under the care of the committee for long
               stated periods, as may often be the case in houses of correction. But in New- gate the changes which are perpetually tak*
               ing place prevent the execution of any such plan.</p>
            <p>Much good may be effected by instruct- ing the female criminals indwidually in the
               truths of the Christian religion. For this purpose^ every member of the committee may
               have a certain number of them under her care. Judiciously selected tracts and other
               religious books may be lent to them for their perusal in hours of leisure; and they
               may be encouraged to commit to me- mory some of our best hymns — such as those in the
               Olnev Collection — and various impressive passages of the Bible itself. The influence
               of this private religious instructioD is powerful^ and I have long observed that the
               greatest change for the better generally takes place in those prisoners, over whom
               has been exercised the most of this pious Christian care.</p>
            <p>According to the provisions of the late Act of Parliament, prayers are to be read
               daily in all our prisons. It is the duty of the visiters to endeavour to impress upon
               the minds of the prisoners a sense of the seri- ousness of this sacred duty — to point
               out to them what a high privilege it is to hold communion with God — and fully to
               explain to them, that unless this service be performed with the heart and in spirit,
               it can never be a sacrifice acceptable, wcll-pleasing, to God. Some of these poor
               wanderers are so igno- rant as to imagine that, if they do but hurry over a daily
               service of prayer with their lips, they are thereby justified in the sight of God ;
               and that this superficial offering will atone for their daily transgressions. It can-
               not be too strongly impressed upon them^ that true religion and saving faith are in
               their nature practical^ and that the reality of repentance can be proved only by good
               works and by an amendment in life and conversation. It is, however, a great con-
               solation to know, that the simple declaration of the Gospel has a powerful tendency
               to produce these efiects — and actually produces, them, at times, even in the most
               hardened offenders. And although, in some cases, such persons, when again beset with
               tempta- tion — and great are the trials to which they are exposed — fall under the power of it, yet there are many others^in whom the
               eflFects of Christian instruction, given to them when in prison, are not only
               powerful, but durable. Long observation and experience enable me to say that there
               are few engagements from which the pious and benevolent may derive more encouragement
               than the care and re- ligious instruction of poor criminals. And surely such efforts
               as these are highly be- coming for the followers of Him, who came into the world " to
               save sinners" — " to seek and to save that which was lost."</p>
            <p>Some part of the time of the visiters may be very usefully employed in the elemen-
               tary instruction of the more ignorant prison- ers. They ought to be taught to read,
               write, and cipher, as well as to make a ready and profitable use of the needle. The
               prisoners ought also to be supplied with a small assort- ment of unexceptionable
               books, not only of a religious, but of a generally instructive, nature; as it is most
               desirable to turn the channel of their thoughts, to improve not only their habits,
               but their tastes and, by every possible means, to raise their intellectual and morale as well as their religious standard.</p>
            <p>I strongly recommend the plan of mutual instruction^ as practised in the schools of
               Bell and Lancaster. Let the women of the first class be employed (under the
               superintend- ence of the matron or the visiters) in teach- ing the lower classes;
               and let them receive some remuneration, to encourage them in their work.</p>
            <p>One observation only remains for me to make, under the head of Instruction — viz.
               that, in all our religious communications with the prisoners, every thing sectarian
               must ever be rigidly avoided, and the attention of our afflicted hearers exclusively
               directed to the essential and saving principles of our common Christianity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg48">
            <p>CHAPTER VII.</p>
            <p>ON EMPLOYMENT.</p></div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Objections have been made, by some per- sons, to the employment of prisoners, on the
               ground that it may be the means of depriv- ing some of the industrious poor of the
               means of an honest and respectable maintenance. It is to be hoped, however, that such
               ob- jections will, ere long, cease to be urged; for it is abundantly evident, that
               unless the time of these poor females, who have abandoned themselves to idleness and
               vice, be fully oc- cupied while they are in prison, there can he little or no hope
               that their confinement will lead to their reformation. Without this important aid to
               the work of prison discipline, their attention will still be directed to the criminal
               objects which have previously occupied them, and much of their time will probably be spent in contriving plans for
               future evil. We cannot promote the reform- ation of such persons more effectually
               than by making them experimentally acquainted with the sweets of industry.</p>
            <p>Since, then, the happiness and security of the community at large very much depend on
               the diminution of crime, and since the re- formation of criminals is one important
               means of producing such diminution, it is evident that the benefit which society
               derives from the employment of criminals greatly out- weighs the inconvenience which
               can possibly arise to the mass of our laboring population^ from the small proportion
               of work done in our prisons. When, to this considera- tion is added that of the moral
               welfare of the prisoners themselves, (which regular occupation is so greatly
               calculated to pro- mote,) we can no longer entertain any doubts respecting the
               importance and pro- priety of this branch of prison discipline. It is desirable,
               however, that every visiting Committee, in the choice of work for the prisoners under
               their care, should keep the industrious poor constantly in view, and should, as fur as possible, contrive sncfa
               me- thods for the employment of their charge as will the least interfiere with the
               usual occa- pation of the laboring classes.</p>
            <p>No prison can be considered complete, which does not afibrd the means of hard bbor,
               which properly appertains to a refor- ming diseipKm, and forms an important part of
               the system of ptmishtnent. The tread* wheel, and the hand- wheel — (which, in some
               instances is preferable) may, in this point of view, be found useful for the
               refractory, the hardened, and the depraved, even among female prisoners; but this is
               a discipline whidi ought to be applied to women, only under very watchful care, and
               with strict Umitaiians; for the female character is seldom improved by such rou^ and
               labori- ous occupation. I should hope that none need be thus engaged for more than a
               short time. As soon as the women in xrur prisons are prepared for entering into die
               higher classes, they ought to be famished with such employments only as will fit them
               for the duties of domestic life, and will enable them honestly to maintain themselves^ after their liberation.</p>
            <p>Plain needle-work, knittings washing and ironing, house^work, cooking, spinning and
               weaving, may all be applied to the uses .of every large prison; and will form very
               desir^ able and sufficient occopation for the gene- rality of female prisoners*
               Although, in all cases, their employments ought to be constant^ yet, the higher the
               class of any criminal, the lighter and more comfortable ought to be her labor.</p>
            <p>Formerly, patchtoork occupied much of the time of the women confined in Newgate, as
               it still does that of the female convicts on the voyage to New South Wales. It is an
               unexceptionable mode of employing the women, if no other work can be pro- cured for
               them, and is useful as a means for teaching them the art of sewing. The female
               prisoners in Newgate are now, for the most part, occupied either in knitting
               stocldngs for the Foundling Institution, or in making clothes for the poor, which
               many ladies are in the habit of purchasing and dis- tribudng gratuitously among their
               distressed neighbours. It is quite surprising how great a quantity of work these poor criminals
               com- plete in the course of a year, and with what entire safety they may themselves
               be entrust- ed with the care of the materials, as well as of the articles when ready
               for sale.</p>
            <p>The female inmates of our prisons may sometimes procure work on their own ac- count ;
               but, even when they are employed solely on account of the Institution, they ought to
               partake of the fruit of their labor. Some remunei'ation for their work, even during
               their continuance in confinement, will be found to act as a powerful stimulus to a
               steady and persevering industry. The greater proportion, however, of their allotted
               share of earnings must be reserved for them against the time of their leaving prison
               and returning to the world. The possession of a moderate sum of money will then be
               found of essential importance^ as the means of preventing an almost irresistible
               tempta- tion — the temptation of want and misery — to a renewal of criminal
               practices. And if in laboring for this remuneration, the poor criminal has also
               gained possession of the habit of industry y and has learned to appreciate the sweets of regular employment,
               it is more than probable that this temptation may never occur again!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg54">
            <p>CHAPTER VIII.</p>
            <p>ON MEDICAL ATTENDANCE, DIET, CLOTHING AND BEDDING, AND FIRING.</p></div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>The directions of the late Act of Parliament, on the subject of medical attendance,
               are so admirably calculated to meet the necessities of the prisons to which they are
               intended to apply, that it is quite needless for me to ex- patiate on the subject. I
               need only refer to the provisions of the Act, as stated below. <note n="3"><p>* See 4 Geo. IV, chap. 64, Sec. 33. ** Every such surgeon shall, and is hereby
                  required to, visit every prison to which he shall be so appointed, twice at least in
                  every week, and oftener if necessary, and to see every prisoner confined therein,
                  whether criminal or debtor, and to report to every general or quarter sessions the
                  condi- tion of the prison, and the state of health of the prisoners under his care" —
                  ** He shall further keep a journal, in which he shall enter the date of every
                  attendance in the performance- of his duty, with any observations Which may occur to
                  him in the execution thereof, and shall sign the same with his name; and such journal
                  shall be kept in the prison, but shall regularly be laid before the justices for
                  their inspection at every quarter sessions, and shall be signed by the chairman of
                  the sessions, in proof of the same having been there produced."</p>
                  <p>Sec. 10, Rule 13. "Prisoners under the care of the surgeon shall be allowed such diet
                     as he may direct."</p>
                  <p>Sec. 10, Rule 17. "The surgeon shall examine every prisoner who is brought into the
                     prison, before he or she shall be passed into the proper ward : and no prisoner shall be discharged from prison if labouring under
                     any acute or dangerous distemper; nor until, in the opinion of the surgeon, such
                     discharge is safe; unless such prisoner shall require to be discharged.</p>
                  <p>"The surgeon shall attend immediately on notice from the keeper that any prisoner
                     is ill.</p>
                  <p>*'He shall visit the patients in the infirmary at the least once every day, and
                     shall twice in the week see every person confined in the prison, and give such
                     directions as he may think necessary for the preservation of the health of the
                     prisoners, and the clean- liness and proper condition of the gaol. He shall enquire
                     into the mental as well as bodily state of every prisoner; and when he shall Ha-ve
                     reason to believe that the mind or body is materially , affected by the discipline,
                     treatment, or diet, particularly of such as are in solitary confinement, he shall
                     inform the keeper thereof, and enter his observations and directions in his journal,
                     which shsdl be authority to the keeper for altering the discipline, treatment, or
                     diet, of any prisoner, until the next visit of a visiting Justice, who shall enquire
                     into the case and make orders aooofrdingly.</p>
                  <p>"In case of the discovery of any infectious dborder, he shall direct the prisoner
                     so infected to be kept separate firom the other prisoners confined in the prison,
                     until such time as all danger of contagion shall have ceased.</p>
                  <p>"He shall at every court of assize, and also at every quarter sessions, affix, to
                     the calendar of tlie prisoners printed and circulate, a certificate of the state of
                     the health of the prisoners, to which he shall add his signature."</p></note></p>
           <p>Since, however, these salutary provisions do not extend to such of our prisons as
            belong to cities and boroughs under exclusive local jurisprudence, it may not be
            improper to im- press upon those who have authority over such prisons, or who are in
            the habit of visating them, the importance of early medical care in cases of
            sickness among the prisoners. Experience amply proves that this may not onlv be
            useful to the individuals who are suffering from illness, but may often be the means of preventing contagion, and of pro- moting, therefore, the general health of
               the inmates of the prison.^</p>
            <p>When nurses are required for sick women in prison, it is very desirable to select
               them from among their fellow-prisoners; some of whom will mostly be found capable of
               ful- filling the office, and steady enough to perform it faithfully, under the
               superintendence of the matron.</p>
            <p>I am very sensible that the diet, clothing, bedding, and firing, provided for the
               inmates of our prisons, are not, and ought not to be, under the control of any
               visiting committee of ladies; but, since the visiters will often find opportunities
               of exerting a quiet and gentle, yet eflfective, influence respecting matters of this
               description, I may venture to make a few observations on these branches of our
               subject.</p>
            <p>The general principle which ought to be steadily kept in view, with regard to all
               such points, is this — that, on the one hand, indulg- ence is to be avoided, except
               when merited by good conduct, and, on the other, that it is our duty to supply our
               prisoners with such food, clothing, bedding, and firing, as will be sufficient to maintain them in
               health, and prevent their being exposed to sufferings, the infliction of which the
               law of the land has never contemplated.</p>
            <p>First, with respect to food. The diet allowed to the inmates of any prison may be
               very properly regulated by the habits of the laboring poor in the district; and as
               the mode of diet among the lower orders varies in the different parts of the country,
               so it may, with propriety, vary in our prisons. The prison allowance ought in all
               cases to be enough for the healthy support of the prisoners; and in order to this
               end, it will be found necessary to provide an extra quantity of food for such of the
               prisoners as are engaged in hard labor and especially on the tread-wheel. In visiting
               some of our jails, I have found too much reason to be* lieve that the health of the
               poor criminals baa materially suffered from the want of adequate support, while they
               have been compelled to use gi'eat bodily exertion.</p>
            <p>When the prison allowance is ample for the maintenance of health, it may be questioned whether tried prisoners ought to be permitted^ except in some peculiar cases,
               to receive from their friends any farther sup- plies of food : for, in the management
               of prisons, a wholesome and judicious discipline, of a restrictive nature ought
               always to be kept in view. Malt liquor is best excluded from a prison, except when
               rendered neces- sary by close confinement or hard labor. Wine and spirits must of
               course be entirely forbidden, except when used medicinally.</p>
            <p>Although it is highly necessary, in the arrangement of the diet of prisoners, to
               avoid all capricious indulgence, yet a little relaxation of the strict line of
               discipline, in this respect, may be very suitably allowed, when merited hy industry
               and good con- dtLct. Thus, when the women aj^ly them- selves diligently to the work
               provided by their visiters, and receive a part of their earnings as a renmneration,
               it will mostly 1)6 found right and useful to permit them to expend some of their
               little income in harm- less articles of food, and especially in tea and sugar. And as
               their dealing with per- sons out of prison frequently produces undesirable commcuiications it will be found an excellent plan to form a little shop
               in the prison, under the inspection of the visiting Committee, where such articles
               may be purchased at a fair market price. This plan has been adopted at Newgate,
               and, after the trial of several years, is still found very useful.</p>
            <p>Such part of the food of the prisoners as may require cooking ought to be prepared
               in some place appointed for the purpose, and by female prisoners suited to the
               office, and properly inspected.<note n="4">On the article of food. See 4 Geo* IV, Chap. 64, Sec. 10, Rule 13. ." Every
                  prisoner maintained at the expense of any county, riding, division, city, town, or
                  place, shall be allowed a sufficient quantity of plain and wholesome food, to be
                  r^ulated by the justices in genend or quarter sessions assembled. Regard being had
                  (so fiir as may rebate to convicted prisoners) to the nature of the labor required
                  from, or performed by, such prisoners, so that the allowance of food may be ddly
                  apportioned thereto. And it shall be lawful for the justices to order for such
                  prisoners of every description as are not able to work, or bang able cannot procure
                  employment sufficient to sustain them- selves by their industry, or who may not be
                  otherwise provided for, such allowance of food as the said justices shall from time
                  to time think necessary for the support of health. Prisoners under the care of the
                  surgeon shall be allowed such diet as he may direct. Cajre shall be taken that all
                  the provisions supplied to the prisoners be of proper quantity and weif^t. Scales and
                  legal weights and measures shall be provided, open to the use of any prisoners under
                  such restrictions as shall be made by the regulations of each prison.</note></p>
            <p>The regulations enforced by the late Prison Act, relative to the clothing and bedding
               of prisoners, will be found very useful and comprehensive. They are stated below, <note n="5"><p>See 4 Geo. IV, Chap. 64, Sec. 10, Rule 17. " The wearing apparel of every prisoner
                  shall be fumigated and purified, if requi- site, after which the same shall be
                  returned to him or her, or in case of the insufficiency of such clothing, then other
                  sufficient dothing shall be furnished, according to the rules and regulations of the
                  prison; but no prisoner before trial shall be compelled to wear a prison dress,
                  unless his or her own clothes be deemed insuf. fident or improper, or necessary to be
                  preserved for the purposes of justice; and no prisoner who has not been convicted of
                  felony shall be liable to be clothed in a party-coloured dress, but if it be deemed
                  expedient to have a prison dress for prisoners not convicted of felony, the same
                  shall be plain — Clean shirts and shifts shall be allowed to prisoners once a week,
                  and dean sheets once a month.''</p>
                  <p>Rule 18. " Every prisoner shall be provided with suitable bed- ^ng, and every male
                     prisoner with a separate bed, hammock, or cot, either in a' separate ceU, or in a
                     cell with not less than two other male prisoners.</p>
                  <p>"The bedding of the prison shall be frequently hung up ii^ the air. The straw in
                     the mattresses shall be changed as often as the keeper or siu^eon may think proper,
                     but in no case is to be allowed to continue in use beyond one month. The blankets and
                     coverlets to be washed every three months, and in all cases clean bedding to be
                     provided for every new prisoner."</p></note> and little need be said in addition to them. I
               may however observe, that iron bedsteads are preferable to wooden ones, as they will
               not harbor vermin; and that the bedding allow- ed the prisoners, which, 'without
               undue in- dulgence, ought assuredly to be sufficient to keep them warm during the
               night, may, like the allowance of food, be in some degree re- gulated by the habits
               prevailing among the laboring poor in the district.</p>
            <p>A regular prison dress for the tried prisoners, female as well as male, will be
               found an important aid to the purposes of prison discipline. It ought to be perfectly plain
               and simple, in some way distinguished from their usual apparel, and in the case of
               women, of such material as may be easily washed. Some advantage will also arise from
               distin- guishing the respective classes from each other, by some variety in the
               prison-dress — the dress of the prisoners in each class being of course a
               uniform.</p>
            <p>Earrings, curled hair, and all sorts of finery and superfluity of dress, in tried
               female prisoners, must be absolutely forbidden; and the caps worn by them must be
               close, plain, and not of a transparent material. Some variety in the texture of the
               cap may be a suitable method of distinguishing the different classes.</p>
            <p>If the long hair of female felons were cut off after their conviction, and afterwards
               kept quite 3hort during their terms of im- prisonment, it would be found to act as a
               certain yet harmless punishment; and would promote that humiliation of spirit, which,
               in persons so circumstanced, is one indispens* able step to improvement and
               reformation.</p>
            
            <p>A proper allowance of firing, although omitted, at present, in many of our prisons,
               appears to me to be, during the winter months, quite indispensable. It is lamentable
               to ob- serve that in some prisons there is not, in the criminals' wards, even a stove
               in which firing can be placed; and where a stove is founjd, there it often happens
               that fuel is wanting. Thus, during inclement weather, diseases are sometimes
               contracted by the unfortunate in- mates of our jails, which can never afterwards be
               removed. I believe it has sometimes hap^ pened that poor creatures committed to
               prison for trial have left the place of their confine- ment, acquitted of crimen and
               yet, crippled for life. Such things are altogether at variance with justice, and with
               that humane attention which has of late been bestowed on our pri- sons; and it is
               greatly to be hoped, that the regular allowance of firing will soon become as general
               in them as that of clothing, bedding, and food.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg63">
            <p>CHAPTER IX.</p>
            <p>ON THE ATTENTION REQUIRED BY FEMALE CRIMINALS ON THEIR LEAVING PRISON.</p></div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Among the female convicts in onr prisons^ a considerable proportion have received
               sentence of transportation^ and are in due time transferred from the prison to the
               convict* ship which is destined to convey them to New South Wales. Several humane
               regu- lations have lately been made by Government respecting female transports. They
               are, under these regulations, allowed to take out with them any of their children who
               are under the age of seven years; and a mother who has an infant at the breast is not
               compelled to leave England until her child is of a proper age to be weaned. Again,
               when female transports are removed from their prison to their convict-ship, they are
               not to be laden with heavy irons for their JQumey; and since this rule is often
               infringed, it is desirable that the ladies of the committee should be vigilant on the subject,
               and should represent all such cases first to the governor of the prison, and
               afterwards, if needful, to the visiting magistrates. Government, or the cities and
               countifes from which the female transports come, provide them with clothing, and the
               Committee of the Ladies' British Society are accustomed to supply them with a variety
               of articles, intended to afford them, during their voyage, some little ac-
               commodations, and the means of useful and profitable occupation. Much pains have also
               been taken by those members of the committee to whom the care of the women in
               convict-ships has been delegated, to im- press upon them the necessity of continued
               good conduct, both for their temporal and spiritual welfare, and to arrange such a
               system among them as will ensure the maintenance of a salutary order and discipline
               on their pas- sage to New South Wales. It generally hap- pens that such of the female
               transports as obtain, from the surgeon of the vessel, a cer- tificate of their
               orderly behaviour while under his care, are, on their arrival at their place of destination immediately hired as servants by the most respectable families in the
               colony; and very encouraging accounts have been received from New South Wales of
               the manner in which many of these females continue to do credit to the care of the
               British Society.</p>
            <p>The females who quit our prisons as libe- rated persons are peculiarly proper objects
               for the persevering care, and kind attention, of the ladies on visiting Committees.
               Such persons are, for the most part, exposed to a variety of temptations. It is often
               their lot to struggle with much poverty and distress, with the force of habit, and
               with the insinu- ations and persuasions of their old compani- ons in crime.
               Distrusted by the virtuous and respectable, and ridiculed by the vicious and
               dissolute, the Hberated female criminal must have indeed received strong impressions
               from the instruction bestowed upon her in prison, if she is enabled to encounter all
               these diffi- culties, and to persevere in her newly-form- ed habits of morality and
               industry. The vi- gilance therefore of, perhaps, her only friends — I mean the
               members of the visiting Committee — is evidently needful, in order to protect her from the influence of her old as^ sociates, and to mtrodace her, if
               possible^ to some safe and respectable sitaation.</p>
            <p>Snch a vigilance has in various instances, been found very successful. Many poor
               wo- men who have enjoyed, in our prisons, the benefit of moral and religious
               instruction, and who have since been the objects of the continued kind
               superintendence of the benevolent of their own sex, have succeeded in completely
               reestablishing their character, and are now occupying useful and respectable places
               in society.</p>
            <p>It is to be hoped that, as Ladies' Committees for visiting prisons are extended
               through-out the kingdom, such pleasing instances of a valid reformation will become
               more and more numerous. And may it ever be remembered that, as nothing short of the
               blessing of the Almighty can possibly enable any of us to produce these good effects,
               so to him alone belongs the praise of his own works!</p>
            <p>If situations cannot be at once procured for these destitute females, it will be
               found extremely useful to take them into a place of temporary refuge, where the care
               of the Committee may continue to be exerted over them, and the great work of
               reformation go forward, until circumstances may open the way for their permanent
               settlement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg67">
            <p>CHAPTER X.</p>
            <p>CONCLUSION.</p></div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <p>Having, in the preceding chapters, endeavored to explain the method adopted by the
               British Ladies' Society in visiting and superintending female criminals in prison, I
               entertain a hope that, where visiting com- mittees are still wanted, some of my own
               sex may be induced to consider the subject, and to make arrangements for assigning a
               portion of their time to this interesting and important object. Possibly also the
               simple account which has now been given of the views of those persons who have
               already engaged in the work, and of the principles on which they endeavour to conduct
               it, may be the means of removing the fears and doubts which the magistrates, in some
               parts of the country, still appear to entertain respecting the propriety of admitting the visits of women in the prisons under their
               care.</p>
            <p>I venture once more to express my con- viction that these gentlemen — like many
               others who have already warmly supported the introduction of female visiters — after
               a little experience of the plans now proposed, would find that they derive a most
               material assistance from Ladies' Committees, in the care of the female officers of
               the prison, as well as of the prisoners themselves; and that there are various
               details connected with the superintendence of such persons, for which, from their
               domestic knowledge and habits, and from some of the qualities cha- racteristic of
               their sex, women are peculiarly, and indeed exclusively, adapted. </p>
            <p>Where jailers and other prison- officers are diligent in the performance of their
               duties, they are, for the most part, glad to avail themselves of such assistance;
               but, where the contrary is the case, it is very natural that they should oppose any
               plan which involves a daily, watchful, inspection of any part of the institution
               under their care. Thus are they induced, as far as they can to prejudice the minds of the gentlemen in authority over them, against the
               visits of ladies to the female prisoners — a circum- stance which has, I believe,
               prevented the formation of Ladies' Associations in some places where they were
               particularly needed, and where persons entirely suitable for the office would have
               been ready to engage in the work.</p>
            <p>It is surely very desirable that magistrates should be on their guard against an
               undue influence of this description; for gentlemen who only occasionally walk through
               a pri- son — however praiseworthy their endeavours may be to promote a right
               discipline — are seldom fully aware of the evil which might be prevented, and of the
               good which might be effected, by that constant inspection and superintending care,
               which, as far as the female department of the prison is concern- ed, would devolve on
               the members of a ladies' visiting Committee. A trial, at least, might, without
               difficulty, be made of the effect of such a plan; and, in case of its being found
               productive of inconvenience or injury — a result which would contradict all our
               present experience — the visiters, at the desire of the magistrates, would, of course,
               without faesi*- tation, withdraw from their field of labor.</p>
            <p>The reader will, I trust, bear with a few more general remarks before I conclude.</p>
            <p>Let not the interest manifested by so many of the benevolent in the present day, in
               behalf of those who have broken the laws of their country, lead any one to imagine
               that such persons are not sensible of the danger and enormity of crime, or of the
               necessity of its being followed by punish- ment. Their desire is only that punishment
               should be of such a nature, that, while it deters others from the commission of crime
               by the force of example, it should also have a tendency — with as little variation as
               pos^ sible — to the reformation of the offenders themselves. They would not save
               convicted criminals from the necessary degree of pre- sent suffering — but they would
               have that suffering applied on the principles of a whole'- some discipline^ so as to
               be productive of future good, both to the criminals who are the subjects of it and to
               society at large. It is upon this, amongst other principles, that persons who have carefiilly attended to the subject^ and who have personally
               watched the effect of our criminal jurisprudence, both iOn offenders themselves and
               on the multitude by whom they are surrounded, so generally and so strongly unite in
               the sentiment, that the punishment of death — especially as it is applied to crimes
               against property only — is very injnrk^us to the best interests of society.</p>
            <p>It would be out of my province now to dwell on that well*known general fact, that
               when punishment is unduly severe, it be* comes in the same degree uncertain^ and,
               therefore, inoperative. If we would ensure the cordial cooperation of the public —
               espe- cially of prosecutors, witnesses, and jurymen, ?— in the punishment of crime,
               the provisions of our criminal code must be made mild enough to coincide with those
               unalterable principles of justice and humanity which God has implanted in the breast
               of man, and which will ever be supported by the feelings of a free and enlightened
               community.</p>
            <p>Waving, for the present, this primary consideration, I can hardly forbear to
               observe, that the practical effects of capital punishments are proved by observation to be, in various respects, very lamentable, as it
               relates both to the sufferers themselves, and to others who are exposed to those
               temptations which lead to the perpetration of crime.</p>
            <p>First, with regard to the sufferers themselves, it is obvious that the infliction
               of death, although it may not preclude a previous repentance, cuts off the
               possibility of that amendment of life which can alone prove its reality; nor will any
               one dispute that it is a most tremendous expedient, violently to transmit the soul of
               a fellow-creature — prepared or unprepared — from probation to jtuigmenty from time
               to eternity. Some per- sons, I believe, imagine that the cutting off of all hope from
               the criminal, in this world, is a sure method of driving him into an ef- fectual
               repentance and a saving faith. But, while we may entertain a humble hope that, where
               the mercy of men is withheld, the mercy of God is yet near to save, those who are
               accustomed to visit our prisons cannot shut their eyes to the fact, that many
               criminals, when about to suffer death, will cling, even to the last, to the hope of a
               reprieve; and that many others by their desire to dress themselves out finely for the
               last scene, by their pertinacious falsehoods, and even by the commission of actual
               crime — (though death is immediately impending over them) — afford too sure an
               evidence of a heart unconverted and estranged from God. Their evil habits are often
               known to main- tain an almost undivided sway over them until the very hour of their
               execution; and they pacify their conscience with the dan- gerous and most fallacious
               notion, that the violent death which awaits them will serve as a full atonement for
               all their sins.</p>
            <p>Long observation has also convinced me, that our public executions have a very inju-
               rious effect on the minds of others who are themselves in the way of breaking the
               laws of their country. The terror of the example is very generally rendered abortive
               by the predestinarian notion — vulgarly prevalent among thieves — that "if they are
               to be hanged, they are to be hanged, and nothing can prevent it." And, at the same
               time, the frequent public destruction of life has a fear- fully hardening effect on
               those whom it is intended to intimidate. While it excites in them the spirit of revenge, it seldom
               fails to lower their estimate of the life of man, and renders them less afraid of
               taking it away in their turn, by acts of personal violence. There is much reason to
               believe that our public executions have had a direct and positive tendency to
               promote both murder and suicide.</p>
            <p>That they do not strike the populace with a wholesome awe, or prevent the commission
               of other crimes, is abundantly proved by the frequent and indecent levity of the mob
               on such occasions; and by the robberies and other heinous offences which so often
               take place under the very gallows. A young woman, a criminal in one of our prisons,
               was heard, some time since, to say, " Well, if the worst comes to the worst, I shall
               but have to dance far an hour ! Thus is the notion of death lowered and even made
               ridi- culous ! Thus do the dissolute and depraved make light of those terrors of the
               law, which are far too frequently obtruded on their notice.</p>
            <p>Is it not then to be lamented that a prac- tice so inconsistent with the religion
               which we profess, and with the true welfare of the state itself, should still be continued
               in a country blessed with a benevolent sovereign, with ministers who are both
               enlightened and conscientious men, and with a people who have in various ways lifted
               up a moral and religious standard, which other nations have been glad to follow?</p>
            <p>Deeply, indeed, is the continuance of such a system to be lamented, especially since
               it is incontrovertibly proved, that punishments of a milder and less injurious
               nature, are calculated to produce, for every good purpose, a far more powerful
               effect.</p>
            <p>Among these secondary methods of punishment, the foremost is a right application of
               prison discipline <note n="6"> A strict and even severe prison discipline, may often be very proper for criminals
                  — but it is never to be forgotten, that it is wholly inapplicable to persons who are
                  confined in our prisons for debt. I question also whether it can be proper for state
                  offenders — ^persons imprisoned, however rightly, on political grounds. Above all, if
                  the time should ever again arrive, when men shall be consigned to the prison-house
                  for conscience* take, may our systems of disciplinary punishment never be so applied
                  as to add oppression and sorrow to the bonds oj the righteous</note> and I trust I shall be excused, for having touched on the subject
               of capital punishment — (a subject which though near to my heart, was not immediate
               before me ) on the ground that the best of substitutes for it will be found in that judicious management of criminals in
               prison, which it is the object of the present tract to recommend. Let our prison
               discipline be severe in proportion to the enormity of the crimes of those on whom it
               is exercised; and let its strictness be such as to deter others from a similar course
               of iniquity; but let it be accompanied by a religious care, and a Christian kindness
               and let us ever aim at the diminution of crime, through the just and happy medium of
               the reformation of CRIMINALS.</p>
            <p>THE END.</p>
            <p>PRINTED BY S. WILKIN, UPPER HAYMARKET, NORWICH.</p>
            <p>JANUARY 18IA, MDCCCXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
