<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="alltexts_html.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="myTEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Methods of Penal Administration in the United States: Notes of a Personal
                    Enquiry, February and March, 1904</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p> A TEI project created for Z656: Digital Publishing Standards and Systems, Spring
                    2018. (Indiana University Bloomington, School of Informatics &amp; Computing,
                    Department of Information and Library Science.
                    <!-- need statement about source -->
                </p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Edward</forename>
                                <surname>Grubb</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <placeName type="settlement">Suffolk</placeName>
                            <placeName type="country">England</placeName>
                            <date type="birth">October 19 1854</date>
                            <date type="death">January 23, 1939</date>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main"> Methods of Penal Administration in the United States:
                            Notes of a Personal Enquiry, February and March, 1904</title>
                        <title type="apa"> Methods of penal administration in the United States:
                            Notes of a personal enquiry, February and March, 1904</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London </pubPlace>
                            <publisher> Wertheimer, Lea &amp; Co.</publisher>
                            <date>1904</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle rendition="center">
                    <titlePart>Methods of Penal Administration in the United States</titlePart>
                    <titlePart>Notes of a Personal Enquiry, February and March, 1904.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor>by Edward Grubb. M.A. </docAuthor>


                <docEdition> THIRD EDITION. Issued by the Howard Association. Secretary : EDWARD
                    GRUBB, M.A., Devonshirb Chambers, Bishopsoatk Without, E.C. First Edition: July,
                    1904. Second Edition: November, 1904. Third Edition: January, 1906. </docEdition>

                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>London </pubPlace>
                    <publisher> Wertheimer, Lea &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <date>1904</date>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="toc">
                <list>
                    <item> Prisons <ptr target="#pg6"/>
                    </item>

                    <item> State Reformatories <ptr target="#pg19"/></item>
                    <item> The George "Junior Republic" <ptr target="#pg26"/>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Parole System <ptr target="#pg28"/>
                    </item>
                    <item> Probation Officers <ptr target="#pg31"/>
                    </item>
                    <item> Children's Courts <ptr target="#pg33"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>Southern Prisons <ptr target="#pg35"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>State and County Convict Camps <ptr target="#pg36"/></item>

                    <item>County and City Jails <ptr target="#pg44"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>Prison Reform and the Race Question <ptr target="#pg47"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>Peonage <ptr target="#pg53"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>Lynching <ptr target="#pg56"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>Appendix: "Is the Negro Criminal Capable of Reform?" <ptr target="#pg61"/>
                    </item>

                </list>
            </div>

            <div type="notice">
                <p>NOTICE.</p>



                <p>A copy of this Pamphlet will he sent to any person interested in the subjects
                    with which it deals, on receipt of One Penny to cover postage. Apply to: THE
                    SECRETARY, Howard Association, Devonshire Chambers, Bishopsgate Without, London,
                    E.C. </p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>


            <p> IN the course of eight weeks it is quite impossible to obtain anything like an
                adequate view of so multifarious a subject as American penal administration. In a
                vast Union, where each State has its own laws and institutions, — where some States
                are progressive and others backward ; where one will spend money freely in trying to
                reform its criminals, while another thinks chiefly of their labour as an important
                source of revenue for the State ; where some have experimented largely in trying
                substitutes for imprisonment, while others adhere to ancient methods, — the
                conditions vary so greatly that it is impossible in a few sentences to summarise
                one's impressions of the whole. The best method of conveying to others some of those
                impressions will be to deal consecutively with the chief classes of institutions
                visited, and the methods of administration which they illustrate. </p>

            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg6">
                <head>PRISONS.</head>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <p> The prisons of the United States are good and bad ; there is no such uniformity
                    as is found in England, where all are under one centralised management. I saw
                    many varieties, from the palatial edifice that is being con- structed by the
                    Federal Government near Atlanta, Georgia, to the miserable dens that are still
                    thought good enough for petty misdemeanants, and persons awcdting trial, in that
                    and other Southern cities. </p>

                <p>The entrance of an enquirer into these institutions is much more easy, as a rule,
                    than with us. I had only to ask to see the Warden (the. Governor, as we term
                    him,) to be shown in at once ; and mention of the Howard Association generally
                    ensured a cordial welcome and unstinted kindness. The pains taken to facilitate
                    my 'enquiry, by Wardens and other oflScials, far exceeded my power of verbal
                    thanks. </p>

                <p>It is characteristic of American life that the relations between officers and
                    prisoners are, as a rule, more human than in English prisons. There is, indeed,
                    in many Quarters an absence of the outward tokens of respect, and almost a tone
                    of camaraderie iu the address of a prisoner to an officer, and even to the
                    Warden himself, which with us would be thought to indicate bad discipline. But
                    it is not so there ; and these more human relations, if discipline is
                    maintained, appear to me wholly good. There is probably no need for the
                    martinet-like manner assumed by some English Governors, especially when they are
                    retired military officers. Soldiers are less often appointed to these posts than
                    in England, and, even when the Warden has been in the army, there is less
                    difference between soldier and civilian than with us. </p>

                <p><span type="sectionHead">Labour Laws. </span>
                </p>
                <p> One of the difficulties the authorities have to contend with, especially in the
                    Eastern States, is found in Labour Laws, which make it no easy matter to keep
                    the prisoners employed. In New York State the law absolutely forbids the sale of
                    goods made by prison labour. In Pennsylvania, and some other States, it is
                    ordered that not more than a certain small percentage of the labour a Warden has
                    available must be directed to any one industry. Consequently, prisoners are not
                    infrequently kept in compulsory idleness, or the wasteful method is adopted of
                    destroying a good part of what they produce. Manufacture of articles for the use
                    of the State is carried on to a certain extent, but this apparently is not so
                    well organised as it might be, and in Pennsylvania it appears hardly to be
                    attempted. </p>

                <p>Such labour difficulties appear to be the logical result of the theory of
                    Protection. These laws are due, of course, to the cry of manufacturers and
                    workmen to be protected, in their own trades, from the competition of prison
                    labour. These claimants tend to overlook the fact that, if the taxpayers' money
                    were not taken from them and wasted by supporting men in idleness or at use-
                    less work, the spending of it would add to the demand for goods, and therefore
                    to the demand for labour ; and that the demoralisation of character which ensues
                    from idle- ness is likely to cause permanent trouble and expense to the
                    community. </p>

                <p>I have shown elsewhere <note n="1">Prison Industry; a Pamphlet issued by the
                        Howard Association in 1903. (Will be sent on applioation to the
                        Secretary.</note> that, if care is taken in regard to prices, so that
                    private firms shall not be undersold, there is no harm or injustice done to free
                    labour by the competition of prison-made goods. If, for political, or other
                    reasons, the State authorities think themselves unable to resist the cry for
                    protection, they should at least do all in their power to organise prison labour
                    for State account — a method by which the com- petition with free labour is made
                    less obvious, and in which there is no fear of glutting the market with
                    unsaleable goods. It is neither just nor expedient that the curse of idleness
                    should be imposed upon those who have gone astray, and for whose support society
                    makes itself responsible. </p>
                <p><span type="sectionHead">State Prisons. </span>
                </p>

                <p>The State Prisons visited were those of Massachusetts at Charlestown (Boston),
                    the Pennsylvania Eastern Penitentiary at Philadelphia, the Maryland Peniten-
                    tiary at Baltimore, and the Indiana State Prison at Michigan City. Of Southern
                    prisons I propose to speak later on. </p>

                <p>The prison at Charlestown (Boston) is an old one, part of it dating from 1804.
                    The cells in this part have been thrown together, two being made into one, and
                    the windows have been greatly enlarged. Only since 1860 have the blocks been
                    warmed in winter. The cells I saw were very neat, some of them being quite
                    taste- fully ornamented by the prisoners — a practice which is encouraged. </p>

                <p>The records show only about 11 per cent, of previous convictions, but here, as
                    elsewhere in America, the information available in regard to previous sentences
                    served in other prisons is extremely imperfect. Arrange- ments are being made, I
                    understand, for the keeping of national records, available for the use of every
                    State. This appears a very necessary reform. </p>

                <p>Schooling at Charlestown is carefully applied to illiterates, and with the best
                    results. I was informed by the Warden, General Bridges, that in eleven years he
                    has only known one man return to prison after going through the school. A
                    monthly magazine (The Mentor) is run by the prisoners, being mimeographed and
                    not printed, and in connection with it correspondence classes are held. <note
                        n="2"> I have just received a pamphlet, entitled "The Story of a
                        Beyelation," giving a very lively aoconnt of these correspondence classes,
                        which have now been working nearly two years. Teachers as well as scholars
                        are for the most part prisoners, bnt teachers and scholars do not know each
                        other. The work appears to have been extremely successful. No prisoner is
                        compelled to join a class, but about half have voluntarily done so. </note>
                </p>

                <p>The industries, such as weaving, stocking-making, tailoring, shoemaking and
                    saddlery, are conducted with a minimum of machinery in order to make the work go
                    as far as possible. </p>

                <p>I was shown the chair in which the capital sentence is carried out by
                    electricity. Happily it is but seldom used. </p>

                <p>The Eastern Penitentiaiy (Philadelphia) is a large stone-walled building in the
                    northern part of the city The " separate system " was very early adopted here,
                    contrary to the usage of most American prisons. The cells were made of large
                    size, each with a yard attached for exercise. When the number of prisoners
                    increased beyond the capacity of the building, the practice was adopted of
                    placing two (or even three) prisoners in each cell — a plan which appears to
                    have most of the draw- backs, and few of the benefits, of both association and
                    separation. The place appeared to be in poor condition and the maneigcment
                    somewhat loose. It is, however, fair to the present able Warden, Mr. Joseph
                    Byers, to state that he had only very recently been appointed, and that serious
                    trouble had occurred under the previous Warden. Probably the institution needs
                    remodelling altogether, and it is to be hoped the Inspectors will face the task.
                    It might well be removed some, miles out of the city, where land could be
                    obtained at moderate cost. </p>

                <p>Thase prisoners who were at work at all were mostly employed in their cells at
                    stocking-knitting, the weaving of prison cloth, cigar making, and other simple
                    hand trades. The appliances used are primitive, the looms having been correctly
                    described by a visitor as "heir-looms." The dietary is not administered on
                    scientific principles, and there appears to be some waste of food. </p>

                <p>The Maryland State Penitentiary, in Baltimore, is a very different institution.
                    The building is comparatively new, handsome and well-proportioned. At the time
                    of my visit it contained about 900 prisoners (more than half of whom were
                    coloured), including about sixty women. The prison is a striking example of the
                    benefits that may arise from freedom and elasticity, when a man of genius is
                    found to conduct the work. Such undoubtedly is the Warden, Mr. John F. Weyler,
                    who has, more than anyone else, developed the institution on its present lines.
                    In his ofiice is a most artistic testi- monial, which was got up by the
                    prisoners, and designed at their expense, when he had been ten years in office.
                    It speaks in the warmest terms of his justice and his earnest efforts for their
                    good, and there can be no doubt that the expressions of respect and affection
                    are per- fectly genuine. He devotes his life absolutely to his prison duties,
                    scarcely ever taking a holiday even for a single day ; and so far he has been
                    unable to find a man who has the needful combination of qualities to be trained
                    as his successor. </p>

                <p>A noteworthy feature of the Maryland Peni- tentiary is that in it the Contract
                    System is made a striking success, not merely financially but in the lives and
                    characters of the prisoners. There being no Labour Laws in that State, the
                    authorities are free to organise the prison labour as they like, and it is run
                    as a great factory, or collection of factories, with the latest and best
                    labour-saving appliances. There is a power-house, with dynamos working up to
                    1050 horse-power, which distributes power through the workshops. The boot
                    factory is organised on the most modem lines, and turns out an average of seven
                    and a half pairs of boots per day to each man employed. </p>

                <p>The method adopted is somewhat as follows. The contractors supply the materials
                    and patterns required, and pay (say) forty-five cents for making each pair of
                    boots. They have nothing to do with the oversight of the prisoners, for which
                    the Warden is entirely responsible. He plans out the work in tasks, so much
                    being a day's work for a man. The value of this goes to the prison ; but
                    whatever a man can do beyond this amount is credited to him ; and in this way
                    many of the prisoners earn from eight dollars to twenty dollars per month. The
                    financial success of the institution may be judged from the fact that last year
                    (1903) it not only cost the State nothing, but brought some 23,000 dollars into
                    the State Treasury, and that in the same year the prisoners earned about 25,000
                    dollars for themselves. </p>

                <p>Other industries carried on in the prison are shirt- making and iron-founding.
                    There is also marble polishing, but, at the time of my visit, the great fire in
                    Baltimore had temporarily destroyed the demand for marble, and most of the men
                    employed at this were idle — and miserable. </p>

                <p>The chief danger of the Contract System is that, in the attempt to run a prison
                    for profit, the personality of the criminal may be overlooked, and he may become
                    further demoralised. Mr. Weyler's methods successfully avoid this danger. The
                    returns show not more than 16 per cent, of recidivists ; though, as I have
                    previously stated, in the absence of national records this figure cannot be
                    trusted. The men I saw at work showed no signs of demoralisation. Most of them
                    were working as eagerly and strenuously as in any ordinary factory. They are not
                    allowed to talk more than is absolutely necessary for the purposes of their
                    work. Meals are taken in a large room seating 1,000 persons, and no talking is
                    allowed here. They sleep in separate cells very carefully coastructed, each with
                    its own sanitary arrangements and electric light There is a good library of
                    books for reading, but I was sorry to find no school- ing nor lectures. The
                    Sunday services are vigorous and are not in the exclusive hands of paid
                    chaplains. They are mainly conducted by Rev. W. C. Stoudenmire, the agent of the
                    Prisoners* Aid Society, Mr. Qolds- borough S. Griffiths (who, though now over
                    eighty years old, is still keenly interested in this work), and others. There
                    are, also, Roman Catholic services held at another hour. Both the Warden and Mr.
                    Stoudenmire spoke emphatically as to the value to the men of these ser- vices,
                    and of the influences brought to bear on them individually. Many seemed to be
                    genuinely reformed, and hearty tributes are received as to the lasting benefits
                    derived from these ministrations. </p>

                <p/>

                <p>Another prison, excellently managed on somewhat similar lines to the above, is
                    the Indiana State Prison, at Michigan City, Indiana, on the eastern shore of
                    Lake Michigan. Thanks to the labours of Mr. Timothy Nicholson and others, the
                    prison and workhouse system of Indiana has been in the past ten years very
                    greatly improved, and few, if any. States now show better results. The State
                    Board of Charities and Correction, of which Mr. Nicholson is a member, and Mr.
                    Amos W. Butler is the able Secretary, has done much to hasten progress, and
                    their efforts are heartily seconded by the Warden of the State Prison, Mr. James
                    D. Reid, who is a humane and enlightened man. The chief defect I noticed is one
                    for which the State is responsible : thirty- five insane prisoners, who ought to
                    have been in a separate institution, were here along with the rest, numbering
                    about 700. I watched a meal taken by the prisoners in a large common dining
                    room, when the order and discipline were excellent. The number of punishments
                    has fallen in two years to nearly half what it was. Here, as in the northern
                    prisons generally, flogging as a punishment is unthought of; humaner methods are
                    found thoroughly effective. The prisoners are provided with an excellent chapel
                    and library, and a good schoolroom; and they have been allowed to organise a
                    musical banc^. </p>

                <p>The prison labour is conducted much as in Maryland, on the Contract System, the
                    contractor paying, as a rule, so much per day for each prisoner's labour. All
                    the work is, of course, carried on in the prison, and entirely under the
                    oversight of the prison authorities. It is done with the best appliances, the
                    chief industries being shirt-making, the knitting of socks and gloves, wool-
                    spinning and dyeing, chair-making and coopering. The last is very heavy work,
                    but healthy, and was being carried on with much energy. I saw no signs anywhere
                    of shirking or laziness. The Chaplain spoke cheerfully about his work, which is
                    greatly aided by an excellent Parole System, of which I will say more presently. </p>

                <p><span type="sectionHead">The Contract System. </span></p>

                <p>I venture to think that the Contract System, even when well administered, as in
                    these two prisons, has certain weaknesses which may be sources of some danger.
                    It is not easy to see how the charge made to a contractor, whether per man or
                    per piece, is to be so adjusted as to give him no unfair advantage over one who
                    employs free labour. Possibly, if the trades were all as fully organised as the
                    textile industries are with us, this difficulty might be met by consultation
                    with representatives of the associated employers and the workmen; but, while
                    "protective" views prevail, it would seem that the whole system may be upset at
                    any time if those who think themselves unfairly hit by prison competition can
                    get the law into their hands.<note n="3">The prejudice against prison -made
                        goods is often a thoughtless one, and breaks down when the facts are quietly
                        explained. Mr. Durbin, the Governor of Indiana, told me he had taken a
                        number of labour leaders to see the prisons of the State, and the methods
                        employed ; and they fully agreed that employment was necessary for
                        prisoners, and that, therefore, competition could not be avoided.</note>
                </p>

                <p>At the same time, the Contract System, while it lasts, has some obvious
                    advantages. It sets a prison Warden free for his real work. If prison -made
                    goods are to be sold in the open market, the work must almost necessarily be
                    thoroughly organised, that the prison may compete successfully with employers
                    trained to the business. A good Warden can hardly be expected to be also a good
                    entrepreneur : he will rarely have had the special training needed, and his
                    powers presumably lie in the direction of dealing with men rather than with
                    things. The Contract System relieves him of the task of organising the business,
                    while leaving the management of the prisoners in his hands. Also, it trains the
                    prisoners in branches of work which may be a source of employment of great value
                    to them on their discharge from prison. The same cannot be said of the primitive
                    hand methods which are used when they work in separation, and when the object is
                    to make a limited quantity of work go as far as possible. </p>


                <p><span type="sectionHead">Political Appointments. </span></p>

                <p>I found many illustrations of the truth that less depends on the system employed
                    than upon the persons who administer it. If the right man can be found for a
                    post of responsibility, and given a fairly free hand, he may produce striking
                    results, even with an inferior method. But one of the difficulties of getting or
                    keeping "the right man" for the management of American prisons is the practice,
                    which is largely prevalent, but which seems to an Englishman peculiarly idiotic,
                    of making these appointments a part of the spoils claimed by a party which has
                    been victorious at a contested election. Close by the Maryland Penitentiary is
                    the City Jail, containing some 600 prisoners, largely coloured The condition of
                    things here was widely different from that at the other prison, and I was
                    informed that the late Warden, an excellent man for the work, had been compelled
                    to retire on a change in the balance of parties in the City of Baltimore, and
                    that his place had been taken by one who knew and cared little about prisons,
                    but who was glad of a comfortable berth. It is difficult to conceive any plan
                    more fatal to successful administra- tion than this, and it is to be hoped that
                    the common sense of the American people will, ere long, succeed in , altogether
                    eliminating "politics" from these appoint- ments, as it is rapidly doing in
                    several of the most progressive States. </p>

                <p/>


                <p><span type="sectionHead">County and City Jails. </span>
                </p>


                <p> These institutions, designed for the most part for prisoners awaiting trial, and
                    for the serving of short sentences by misdemeanants, are, with little exception,
                    far from satisfactory, even in the Northern States. The best I saw was at
                    Boston. At Indianapolis, and at Cleveland and Mansfield (Ohio), to say nothing
                    of the South, the jails were, for the most part, far from clean, and the
                    prisoners were shut up together, with full opportunity to corrupt each other.
                    Either they had no occupation (at Mansfield they were engaged in playing at
                    cards), or, if employed (as at the House of Correction at Cleveland), they were
                    working in a very half-hearted manner. I was glad to note that at Indianapolis
                    the boys were kept separate from the men, and that the ^omen and boys were put
                    under the. care of a Matron, who seemed a competent person. I fear that even
                    these elementary points of good management are by no means universal. </p>

                <p>A slight attack of illness prevented my seeing, as I had hoped to do, the working
                    of the prisons of New York and neighbourhood, but I was informed by Dr. S. J.
                    Barrows, of the New York Prison Association, that the causes of the
                    unsatisfactory condition of many of these jails, even in the Empire State, are
                    chiefly : (1) The independence of the counties in prison matters, and the
                    absence of any central organisation; and (2) the Fee system, by which sheriff
                    are paid in proportion to the number of prisoners under their charge. Of
                    sixty-one counties in New York State, I was told that twenty- seven have
                    abolished the fee system, and show a diminution in the number of prisoners, but
                    thirty-four still retain it. <note n="4"> The Ninth Annual Report of the State
                        Commission of Prisons (New York) for 1903 gives abundant evidence of the
                        unsatisfactory condition of many of the County Jails in that State. The
                        Albany County Jail, for instance, is declared to be "unfit for human beings
                        at any time," and "an institution for the manufacture of criminals instead
                        of their reformation." Prisoners awaiting trial are allowed to mingle in
                        idleness with convicted criminals of all d^rees of depravity. </note></p>

                <p/>
            </div>

            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg19">
                <head>STATE REFORMATORIES.</head>
            </div>

            <div type="chapter">
                <p> No English institutions, I regret to say, are to be compared to the great
                    Reformatories which the pro- gressive spirit of the Northern States has
                    established, in the faith (which is now a fact of experience) that a large
                    proportion of the criminal population is, by proper methods, reclaimable. I
                    visited three of these — at Elmira (New York), Mansfield (Ohio), and Oowcor^f
                    (Mass.), as well as the reformatory for women, at Sherborn (Mass.). At Mansfield
                    I had the privilege of being accompanied by General R. Brinkerhoff, the veteran
                    prison reformer of the State of Ohio. Apart from minor details, the prin- ciples
                    and methods of these institutions are essentially similar : the idea being to
                    take the young ofienders of the State, between the ages of sixteen and thirty,
                    and subject them to a course of thorough discipline and training, applying every
                    possible inducement that may lead to moral reformation. </p>



                <p>The pillars of the American reformatory system are mainly the Indeterminate
                    Sentence and the method of Release on Parole. The essence of the Indeterminate
                    Sentence, as it is applied in practice, is the provision of a maximum term of
                    detention, which maf/, if neces- sary, be enforced, but which may, on the other
                    hand, be ^eatly reduced if, in the opinion of the authorities of the prison, the
                    individual is fit to be released. In some States, as in Indiana and Ohio, a
                    minimum term is also fixed by the Court, which the prisoner must serve in any
                    case. At Elmira the sentences vary from one or two up to twenty years ; but the
                    average term of actual detention is about one and a half years. </p>

                <p>It is sometimes objected to this method that the imprisonment actually endured
                    has little or no relation to the crime committed. A man who has been sentenced
                    to twenty years for murder may. if he appears to be thoroughly reformed, be
                    released as soon as one who has had a two years' sentence for theft. I put this
                    objection to Mr. Scott, the Warden at Elmira, who replied that prisoners are
                    sent to the Reformatory as criminals to be cured, and not to expiate by
                    punishment a particular offence. His business is to cure, if he can, the
                    criminal tendency, and to let the prisoner go when he considers, in consultation
                    with other authorities, that the cure is complete. On this theory the idea of
                    punishment gives place to the protection of society and the reform of the
                    wrongdoer. Another head of a reformatory (Mr. Leonard, at Mansfield, Ohio) said
                    that the nature of the originaJ offence was taken into con- sideration by the
                    authorities there, in deciding whether the time had come for an inmate to be
                    released on parole. He believed in punishment, but not as an end in itself.
                    Vengeance he considered, hcul no place at all in a true penal system, but
                    suffering was a factor in the natural process by which restoration and renewal
                    were worked out. Punishment, therefore, was a necessary adjunct of the reform of
                    character. </p>

                <p>The practice of these institutions appears to me to be ^ in accord with this
                    theory. I looked carefully for an^Nl^ thing to justify the common charge that
                    Elmira and the other reformatories that have followed it are " senti- mental,''
                    and pamper the wrongdoer, regardless of the victims whom he has wronged, and the
                    society whose laws he has outraged. I found nothing. Life in these places is
                    very far indeed from being a perpetual picnic. Discipline is severe and
                    incessant ; there is virtually no liberty. Anyone who shirks or sulks comes off
                    badly. Flogging, happily, is not now resorted to ; Mr. Brock- way, the first
                    Superintendent of Elmira, used it, and came to grief because of it ?)The present
                    heads find it needless. Mr. Leonard, indeed, told me that he had known a boy's
                    better nature to be reached, and the ^ process of reformation started, by the
                    explanation that it was respect for the manhood that was in him which forbade
                    flogging to be used. A time of solitary con- finement, with or without
                    degradation to the lowest grade, is generally found enough to meet the case. I
                    saw little or nothing of the hang-dog look of the regular shirker ; most of the
                    faces were bright and eager. </p>

                <p>Mr. Scott, of Elmira, pointed out that a large pro- portion of the young
                    prisoners who are committed there are foreign born. They come over to the
                    States, and, being unused to such liberty as they find there, take advantage o^
                    it to secure, in wrong ways, the means of living. They are brought before the
                    Courts, and a touch of life at Elmira soon sobers them. They, and still more
                    their families after them, settle down into J^-mseful citizens. There were clear
                    indications that at least 70 per cent, of the cases sent to Elmira were
                    permanently benefited by it. </p>

                <p>Mr. Leonard (whose conversation was almost "a liberal education" in penology told
                    me that three stages could often be noticed in the career of a youth at
                    Mansfield : (a) He came expecting to have "a good time," and to be able to take
                    things easy; (b) the severity of work and discipline began to pall on him, and
                    he became reckless and defiant; (c) he got into trouble with the authorities,
                    began to find it did not pay, and gradually learnt self-control and good
                    behaviour. During the seven years that reformatory had been going only about
                    ticehe per cent, of those released had violated their parole or come before the
                    Courts again. Some indeed who had won full release had afterwards got into
                    trouble ; on the other hand, some who had been returned for violating a first
                    parole had done well on a second trial. Such violations were by no means always
                    due to bad character; frequently a youth fancied himself stronger than he really
                    was, and found himself unable to bear the strain of temptation. </p>

                <p>At Concord (Mass.), where misdemeanants as well as felons may be sent, and where
                    the sentences and periods of detention are consequently shorter than at Elmira,
                    I was informed that at least 73 per cent, turn out well. In fourteen years about
                    11 per cent, of the inmates had come back ; 13 per cent, had been sentenced to
                    other prisons, and 3 per cent, had been lost sight of. </p>

                <p>The methods employed at these institutions, though essentially similar, vary in
                    detail. At Elmira much time is given, especially at first, to military drill,
                    and the effects are seen in the comely forms and graceful move- ments of the
                    inmates, who (by the way) in none of these places wear ugly ill-fitting garments
                    such as one sees on English prisoners. At Concord there is but little drill, the
                    amount of which probably might be increased, with advantage. Bathing is largely
                    used, the arrange- ments for it being everywhere excellent. Regular lessons are
                    given for some hours of every day to those who need schooling; and a large
                    number of different trades are taught. At Elmira these number about 20% but, as
                    little is done for the State, and nothing may be sold, most of the produce has
                    to be destroyed. At Mansfield the Reformatory was being greatly enlarged y. by
                    the labours of the inmates themselves, while others were employed on contract at
                    brush-making. At Concord some of the produce is sold, but most used for State
                    purposes. "Sloyd" is largely taught, and probably might with advantage be
                    introduced elsewhere. Each institution has a weekly newspaper run by the
                    inmates, who numbered at Elmira about 1,500, at Mansfield 650, and at Concord
                    about 840. </p>

                <p>As regards Religion, the endeavour is made to cul- tivate a moral and religious
                    atmosphere rather than to encourage mere emotionalism or much personal expres-
                    sion, especially in the presence of others. The Sunday services are lively and
                    vigorous, and much is clearly done through personal influence by the
                    Superintendents and Chaplains. Mr. W. J. Batt, the venerable Chaplain at
                    Concord, has his whole heart in this work, and knows of much good resulting from
                    it. </p>

                <p>The Reformatory for Women, at Sherboi*n (Mass.), which is under the able
                    supervision of Mrs. Morton, contained at the time of my visit about 200 women,
                    more than three-fourths of whom were Roman Catholics, being mostly Irish or of
                    Irish descent. The average age was considerably higher than that of the men,
                    being apparently over thirty. It is impossible to estimate the proportion really
                    benefited by the treatment, but it is ^ certainly much lower than with the men.
                    The indus- tries at the time of my visit included shirtmaking, sewing, knitting
                    and laundrywork, and cooking was about to be introduced. Weaving was found to be
                    too heavy work for most women. There is a considerable farm attached, and in
                    summer the women are employed in gardening and in keeping poultry, an industry
                    which is very successful. The Doctor and the Chaplain are both ladies; in fact,
                    hardly any men are employed on the place, with the exception of a joiner and two
                    night watchmen. Discouraging as is often the effort to get rid of criminal
                    tendencies in women, the work at Sherborn is undoubtedly far more enlightened
                    and successful than that which is carried on, for instance at Holloway Prison in
                    England. </p>
                <p><span type="sectionHead">Other Reformatories.</span></p>

                <p> I also visited a Reformatory for Girls near Indianapolis, where about 200 girls,
                    from the ages of nine to twenty-one, are trained in the same building with some
                    fifty women prisoners, from whom they are, of course, kept entirely separate.
                    The accommodation is quite inadequate, the bedrooms, etc., being overcrowded,
                    and it is to be hoped that a separate institution will shortly be provided. In
                    this, as in some other American institutions, care is taken to prevent
                    dishonesty on the part of tradesmen who supply goods by buying on the "
                    competitive bid '* principle, all goods sent in being weighed at the
                    institution. An elaborate system of book-keeping is required, which even in a
                    school of that size takes pretty much the whole time of a lady clerk; but it is
                    probably worth the cost. </p>

                <p>The "House of Refuge," a Reformatory for Boys at Olen Milky near Philadelphia, is
                    a remarkably fine institution. About 800 boys are housed in some fifteen houses,
                    built around a spacious "campus" on a plateau 450 feet above the sea, with a
                    beautiful outlook over the surrounding country. Each house contains fifty or
                    sixty boys, and the home feeling is strong. Everything is kept extremely clean
                    and neat ; I noticed that the boys even have serviettes for use at meals. Half
                    their time is devoted to schooling, and half to technical trailing. The
                    gymnasium, lately given by a generous supporter, is one of the finest I have
                    seen anywhere. The rest of the buildings and plant have also been provided by
                    private donations, but most of the cur- rent expenses are met by a State
                    appropriation. The management is in the hands of a private Com- mittee. </p>

                <p>Under the wise and genial superintendence of Mr. Nibecker excellent results are
                    obtained, 80 or 90 per cent of the boys turning out well. The appearance of the
                    institution is in striking contrast to the starved and squalid features of most
                    English reformatories. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg26">
                <head> The George "Junior Republic." </head>
            </div>

            <div type="chapter">
                <p/>

                <p>At this point, a few words may be said about a remarkable institution established
                    at Freeville, near the centre of New York State, by Mr. William George. At the
                    time of my visit, which was during the long and severe frost of last winter, 113
                    children were present, about two-thirds being boys and the rest girls. There are
                    about eighteen different houses, used for various purposes, all being frame
                    buildings of the cottage type. </p>


                <p>The children have, for the most part, a bad record, many being sent there by the
                    Courts. "Fallen" girls are not received. The original features of the institu-
                    tion are that the motto, "Nothing without labour," is rigidly enforced, and that
                    self-government is carried to a point that, with mere children, would appear
                    whimsical were it not a proved success. The place is, as the name implies, a
                    miniature "republic," with laws, legislature, courts, and administration of its
                    own, all made and carried on by the "citizens" themselves. The Superin- tendent
                    retains, but seldom exercises, the right to veto any law. Courts are held in the
                    evenings, and delinquents, when convicted, subjected to fine or imprisonment.
                    The occupations are schooling, carpentry, printing, and (in summer) a large
                    amount of farm and garden work. There is also sewing for the girls, and a good
                    laundry. The library is a bright attractive room, crowded in the evenings. The
                    tone and spirit of the place appeared to be excellent, and there is much
                    evidence that in many cases strong and independent character is developed in
                    children whose antecedents have been almost hopeless. Sunday services are con-
                    ducted for the most part by students from the Auburn Theological Seminary, and
                    provision is made for Roman Catholic and Jewish children. Personal expression on
                    religious matters is not encouraged, but there is, undoubtedly, a strong
                    religious influence at work. Self- reliance and respect for law are the virtues
                    chiefly sought after. </p>


            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg28">
                <head>THE PAROLE SYSTEM.</head>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <p> I had much evidence of the excellent results of the Parole System of conditional
                    liberation, as practised in most of the prisons and reformatories of the
                    Northern States. There is urgent need for something of the kind in England. The
                    Committee of the Howard Association, in their Annual Report for 1903, said: — </p>

                <p>At present the prodigious gulf between the fixed machine- like routine of a
                    prison and the freedom of life outside, is quite too much for the average
                    prisoner. He may be well-behaved enough inside, he may even mean to do better ;
                    but on his liberation the temptations of his old surroundings too often overcome
                    him at once. It should be one of the aims of enlightened prison administration
                    to cope with this difficulty. </p>

                <p>The American States have learnt how to cope with it effectively. The laws of the
                    different States vary in detail, but in most of them careful arrangements are
                    made for the conditional liberation, under the super- vision of an appointed
                    Board, of prisoners who, in the judgment of the Board, will not abuse their
                    liberty. At the Mansfield Reformatory young men are prepared for such liberation
                    by being allowed to work on the farm at a distance from the Reformatory
                    buildings, where, in the absence of armed guards, they could easily escape if so
                    inclined. </p>

                <p>As a rule the body responsible for the liberation of prisoners on Parole is the
                    Prisons Board of the State. The Board acts on the recommendation of the Warden
                    and Chaplain of the prison, and considers each case separately. No prisoner is
                    released unless he has previously obtained promise of employment, and he is not
                    allowed to leave or change his post without the knowledge and permission of the
                        Board.<note n="5">Facilities are usually offered by the prison authorities
                        for the finding of employment. At Elmira printed forms are supplied to
                        prisoners for this purpose, and one prisoner will sometimes send out forty
                        or fifty of these before he obtains a post. </note> He is obliged to make a
                    written report monthly to the Board or one of its accredited agents, not, as in
                    our system of release on licence, to the Police. In Indiana he is ordered to
                    abstain from the use of liquor in any form and to avoid evil associations and
                    improper places of amuse- ment, to respect and obey the laws cheerfully, and
                    con- duct himself in all respects as a good citizen. Besides the written
                    reports, arrangements are made for visits to be paid to paroled prisoners by
                    agents of the Board. The prisoner is assured that the Board have a lively
                    interest in his welfare, and will do all they can to assist him to regain his
                    place in society. If he violates in any way his promise of good behaviour, they
                    have l^al power to bring him back at once to the prison or reformatory, where,
                    unless again recommended for trial of liberty, he will have to work out the
                    remainder of his sentence. </p>

                <p>At Concord I was present while Mr. Pettigrove, acting for the Board of the State
                    of Massachusetts, interviewed a number of inmates of the Reformatory who were
                    recommended for liberation. In most cases the recommendation wa-s complied with,
                    and the youth released with wise words of friendly counsel. </p>

                <p>At the Indiana State Prison, out of 908 prisoners released on parole, 481, or 53
                    per cent., earned full liberty, 179, or 20 per cent., violated their parole and
                    were either returned to the prison or escaped. The re- mainder were either still
                    under probation or had been discharged from supervision because their term of
                    sentence had expired. </p>

                <p>There can, I think, be no question that this method is on the whole effective,
                        <note n="6">In the first edition of this Report it was stated that the Ohio
                        Parole Law had been repealed. I am glad to learn from Greneral Brinkerhoff,
                        of Mansfield (Ohio), who was the author of the law, that this statement,
                        which was made (as I believed) on good authority, is incorrect. The law has
                        now been working for twenty years, the State of Ohio having been the first
                        in the Union to allow paroles in Penitentiary cases. It has been extended to
                        workhouses, and authorised in a boys' industrial school. "The parole law,"
                        says General Brinkerhoff, "in Ohio is no longer an experiment, and has
                        steadily grown in favour until now it is very rare to hear of an objection."
                    </note> and I earnestly hope that ere long it will be adopted in this country. A
                    beginning has been made in the system of licence, and in the remission of
                    sentence that can be earned through good conduct by prisoners in local prisons.
                    But what is needed is simple legislation empowering the Prison Commissioners,
                    acting through a committee <note n="7">Under the new "Rules as to Division and
                        Classification" for Convict Prisons, such a Committee is to consist of the
                        Governor and Chaplain, and such members of the Board of Visitors or
                        Discharged Prisoners' Aid Society as the Commissioners may appoint.</note>
                    attached to each local and convict prison, to liberate prisoners on parole at a
                    much earlier stage of their imprisonment than is possible at present, — regard
                    being had, not simply to the number of marks earned by the individual in prison,
                    but to all the circumstances of his case, and the use he is likely to make of
                    liberty. Some simple machinery is also required for his supervision and
                    assistance. The Police are unsuited for this work; the local Board, or
                    Committee, should be directed to appoint an agent, or agents, who should be
                    responsible for supervising prisoners on parole, and should be persons who will
                    take a real interest in helping them to retrieve and maintain their character.
                        <note n="8">The Ninth Annual Report of the State Commission of Prisons (New
                        York) says : — " The prisoner who serves his full term, and is then
                        discharged, is more likely to return to criminal practices than the prisoner
                        who is released somewhat before the expiration of his term in care of a
                        parole official. . As a prisoner is not paroled until the Board is
                        (satisfied that somebody is ready and willing to give him em- ployment, he
                        has a much better chance to get along than the ordinary convict. It is
                        almost impossible for an ex-convict to find employment, and, even when he
                        succeeds, he is almost invariably discharged as soon as the fact of his
                        former imprisonment becomes known. If the convicts in our State prisons are
                        to be benefited by their imprisonment, parole before final discharge is
                        almost indispensable." </note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg31">
                <head>PROBATION OFFICERS.</head>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <p> "Probation Officers" are needed, not alone for prisoners liberated on parole,
                    but (under a different authority) for the oversight of persons who have been put
                    upon probation instead of being sent to prison at all. The chief weakness of our
                    "Probation of First Offenders" Act is that no person is officially charged with
                    the duty of looking after the offender and helping him or her to better things.
                    The "Youthful Offenders Act" of 1901 empowered the magistrates, in remanding for
                    trial any child or young person, to place him in the custody of some fit person
                    to be named in the commitment, instead of sending him to priaon; but no
                    officials were appointed to undertake this duty. </p>

                <p>Most of the Northern States have now adopted Pro- bation as a substitute for
                    imprisonment in the case of most young and first offenders. In Massachusetts and
                    New York especially it has been extended to adults : but in the latter State
                    some of the Judges have been slow to avail themselves of it. Massachusetts was
                    the first State to adopt the system, and has carried it further than any other.
                    Everyone speaks of it enthusiastically. According to an Act of 1891 the officers
                    are appointed by the Judges, and for all Courts, lower and higher. Their
                    salaries are part of the Court expenses, but in addition there are, attached to
                    some of the Courts, officers who are either unpaid or maintained from private
                    sources. I had much talk, while at Boston, with Mrs. Tuttle, the principal
                    female Probation Officer attached to the Court House there. She considers that
                    at least 30 per cent, of the girls and women placed in her charge are greatly
                    benefited by probation. Mr. J. M. Ramsay, Chief Probation Officer attached to
                    the High Court at Lowell, Mass., told me he had no fewer than 175 cases under
                    his charge, including some women and girls. He thought at least 60 or 70 per
                    cent, were helped by it, but the time of probation must not be unduly shortened
                    if good results were to be secured. In doubtful cases a year was none too long,
                    and more was often required. He told me of a number of most satisfactory cures
                    effected, especially in cases of drunken- ness. Attached to the Children's Court
                    at Indianapolis I found two paid Probation OflScers, both women — one of them
                    the wife of a Professor, having no children of her own. There are also connected
                    with the Courts there a number of voluntary probation officers, some of them
                    being ministers oE religion. </p>

                <p>Doubtless very much depends on the quality of the men and women selected for this
                    important duty. An unscrupulous officer would have large opportunities of
                    levying blackmail by threatening to ruin his ward's career. Happily, in nearly
                    all cases where it has been used, good men and women have been forthcoming. I
                    need not dwell further on this subject, as it has been recently treated by Miss
                    Hughes, a member of the Com- mittee of the Howard Association. <note n="9">The
                        Probation System, in America by Miss E. P. Haghes. (The Howard Association,
                        1903.)</note>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg33">
                <head>CHILDREN'S COURTS.</head>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <p> The separation of children from adults in Courts of Justice has been tried in
                    several of the States with excellent effects. The moral atmosphere of the Courts
                    is bad for children, and also the publicity of appearing in a crowded Court
                    whether as offenders or as witnesses. </p>

                <p>New York, Brooklyn, and Chicago are the cities where this method has been most
                    successful. Owing to illness, I was unable to see as much of its working as I
                    had hoped, but I attended the Courts where children's cases were being heard at
                    Indianapolis and also at Boston. At the former place, Judge Stubbs is set apart
                    for the hearing of cases in which the accused are juveniles, and takes quite a
                    fatherly interest in them. On the day of my visit three coloured boys were
                    separately charged with petty offences. Each case was very carefully inquired
                    into, with the result that one was discharged, the second was placed in charge
                    of one of the lady Probation Officers, and the third, who had a bad record, was
                    sent to prison. The last course is one that is but rarely taken. </p>

                <p>At Boston separate Judges are not appointed, but the 'Children's cases are taken
                    after the regular Court has adjourned and when the room has been cleared. I
                    thought the Judge and his clerk spoke with some unnecessary harshness, and
                    rather frightened the children ; but the method was undoubtedly an improvement
                    on the open Court. </p>

                <p>At Baltimore the systems of Probation and special Courts for children have both
                    been tried, but not yet (as I was informed by Mr. Stoudenmire) with full
                    success. The Probation Officers, to be really effective, should be well paid,
                    and the Judge of a Children's Court must have full jurisdiction, and not be
                    compelled to refer one matter and another to the ordinary Courts. Owing to these
                    and other imperfections in their existing arrange- ments, he and the Prisoners'
                    Aid Society had not favoured the method ; but they were heartily supporting a
                    modified law which they hoped would remove the difficulties. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg35">
                <head> SOUTHERN PRISONS. </head>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">

                <p>In most of the Souther States the plan was adopted, soon after the War of
                    Emancipation, of leasing out convicts to private persons or firms who work them
                    for profit, and (except where this has been stopped by law or by the practice of
                    the Prisons Boards) take entire custody of them. This leasing system was the
                    outcome of the difficult situation which followed the Emancipa- tion of the
                    slaves in 1865, when large numbers of them left their employment, and when the
                    whites felt it necessary to resort to means by which they should be compelled to
                    work. It is very strongly rooted among Southern institutions, both because it is
                    apparently cheap to the State and because of the powerful private interests
                    which it creates. </p>

                <p>Before going South I spent some days at Washington (D.C.), in order to get as
                    much information as possible that would serve to direct my inquiries into the
                    most useful channels. After calling on the President, who received me cordially,
                    I had several interviews with Mrs. C. O. Keeler, who has long been deeply
                    interested in these matters, and who greatly helped me in some inquiries (into
                    the practice of Leasing) in the Library of Congress ; also with Mr. J. Q.
                    Howard, of that library ; with Mr. Macfarland (one of the Commissioners for
                    Washington), and his wife; with Prof. Geo. W. Cook, of the Howard University
                    (coloured); and with several officials in different departments of the Federal
                    Government. </p>

                <p>In Georgia and Alabama (which I visited) the convict camps are of two classes, —
                    those of the State and those of the Counties. The former contain felons, sen-
                    tenced to long terms for serious crimes; the latter mainly misdemeanants, whose
                    terms are comparatively short. Petty misdemeanants and persons awaiting trial
                    are confined in city and county jails. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chaptertitle" xml:id="pg36">
                <head> State Convict Camps.</head>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">

                <p>The Howard Association has repeatedly, in very plain terms, called attention to
                    the gross abuses that have accompanied the system of leasing out convicts in
                    these States, and I was doubtful what sort of a reception would be given me. I
                    thought it best to go direct to headquarters for information, and was well
                    received even by those who frankly told me that in their view unjust things had
                    been said by the Association, in reliance on untrustworthy reports. The
                    assurance that my Committee felt the weakness of newspaper information, however
                    voluminous, and had encouraged my visit in order to get first-hand knowledge,
                    was usually all that was needed to obtain facilities for inquiry. I did not,
                    indeed, succeed in obtaining access to printed Reports of oflScial inquiries
                    into the Leasing System ; but I was allowed to visit a convict camp in Georgia
                    and another in Alabama, and I questioned permanent officials and members of the
                    Prisons Board in each State (after reading their published Reports), and also
                    obtained interviews with the State Governors, who received me with cordiality. I
                    also secured intro- ductions to a number of influential persons, both white and
                    coloured, and heard their views. I would particu- arly mention the Hon. Joseph
                    S. Turner, Chairman of the Prison Commission of Georgia, who is genuinely
                    interested in prison reform, and General Evans, another member of the
                    Commission, who is a fine specimen of the Southern aristocracy of the past. </p>

                <p>Georgia, — I was told that "the State of Georgia no longer leases out its
                    convicts." But on inquiry I found this means that it now retains control of
                    them, instead of entrusting the contractors with their custody. This is a great
                    step in advance, and there is good reason to hope that, so far as the State
                    convicts are concerned, it has put an end to the worst abuses. </p>

                <p>But the leasing-out still remains, in the sense that the convicts are hired out
                    to contractors who pay about 100 dollars per head per annum, and keep them in
                    camps near their work. (Labour has recently become so valuable that I was
                    informed the price to contractors was about to be doubled.) The industries are
                    saw- milling, the extraction of turpentine, brick-making, and mining. There are
                    about twenty of these leasing-out camps, and, in addition, the State Farm at
                    Milledgeville whither are sent women, boys, and sickly and a^ed men. There is as
                    yet no Reformatory for boys, but it is hoped that this may grow out of the
                    Milledgeville farm. The total number of State convicts is about 2,000, of whom
                    90 per cent, are coloured. <note n="10">In 1902 the nmnbei was : white 257,
                        coloured 2,058, total, 2,315. Of these, no fewer than 566 were in prison for
                        murder, 231 for attempted murder, and 221 for manslaughter The rape cases
                        num- bered 126, and attempts 100.</note> All the officials in these
                    institutions, wardens, guards, and doctors, are appointed by and responsible to
                    the Prison Commissioners, who also appoint inspectors to seethat the rules are
                    observed. </p>

                <p>The camp I was able to see is at the Chattahoochee Brickyards, distant about an
                    hour's tram-ride, through forest-covered country, from Atlanta. About 200 con-
                    victs are kept here, — a few white, the great majority- coloured. Whites are
                    kept apart from negroes, but the mixing of boys with men undoubtedly leads to
                    great corruption. The few buildings, where the convicts sleep and eat, are
                    surrounded by a high wooden stockade, and are all of wood which has once been
                    whitewashed, but now presents a dismal appearance. The principal dormitory (that
                    for the coloured prisoners), like most buildings in the South, is raised high
                    above the ground on wooden pillars, the space below forming a long open shed. In
                    this is a long wooden trough, perhaps 100 ft. long and 2 ft. wide and deep. This
                    is the only bath, and can of course only be used in comparatively warm weather.
                    It looked extremely foul. The bunks, also, in the room above, were very dirty,
                    and placed close together in two long rows down the whole length of the
                    apartment. At one end were two w.-c. pans, with no concealment whatever. In a
                    similar, but smaller, building the white prisoners slept. <note n="11"> In a
                        list of Rules which was handed to me, it is stated that the beds are to be
                        well apart and that a wire netting at least 4 feet high is to be placed
                        between each bed and the next. I called the attention of the Prison
                        Commissioners to the fact that this Rule is not observed, , and was informed
                        that it has been repealed by the Legislature. It is extremely important that
                        physical contact between prisoners at night should, if possible, be
                        prevented. </note>
                </p>

                <p>From the stockade I was taken to the brickyards, where the men were working hard.
                    Most had a light chain reaching apparently from waist to ankle, but nearly all
                    of them wore it under their pants and out of sight. At several prominent points
                    guards were stationed, armed with rifles, to prevent escapes. These, I was
                    informed, are infrequent. The white prisoners were young, but looked more
                    hardened than the blacks, and (I was told) give more trouble. </p>

                <p>Punishment is inflicted by the Deputy-Warden only, with the whip —which consists
                    of a short stout handle to which is attached a broad thick leather strap about 3
                    ft. long. It is used, perhaps, on the average, 20 times a month. </p>

                <p>The convicts are obliged to work a certain time (or in some cases to do a certain
                    task) for the contractor, and then are allowed to work a while for themselves ;
                    and in this way considerable sums may be earned. </p>

                <p>From what I could learn, the convict camp I saw may be taken as a fair specimen
                    of those under the direct control of the State of Georgia. </p>

                <p>Alabama. — The industrial development which is rapidly transforming some parts of
                    Georgia has hardly as yet touched Alabama, and the State is one which feels
                    itself poor. There is a dread of any sort of taxation, which puts a difficulty
                    in the way of those who desire improvements. The Capitol at Montgomery, for
                    instance, though finely situated, is going to pieces for want of repair. The
                    practice of the Legislature is far behind the ideals and policy of many
                    enlightened citizens. </p>

                <p>The State of Alabama does not retain such full control of its convicts as does
                    Georgia, but still in part gives their care into the hands of contractors. In
                    the Pratt mines, however, the State has entire control, and this, I was told, is
                    spreading. As contracts expire the State steps in and assumes the management
                    itself. Some of the officers, thei-efore, in the State Camps are appointed by
                    the Board of Inspectors and some by the contractors, but all must have a licence
                    from the Board. The Board can discharge an officer for misconduct, but it does
                    not always know the character of the licensees. The Board can also annul a
                    contract if the rules are not observed, and this has occasionally been done. </p>

                <p>The Chairman of the Board of Inspectors (Mr. Carmichael) received me kindly and
                    answered my questions on such points as the above. I also obtained informa- tion
                    from the Secretary, and from Dr. Shirley Bretgg, the Physician Inspector under
                    the Board. I was allowed to see the camp of the Alabama Cordage Company at
                    Riverside, about two miles from Montgomery. It is situated in a dreary swamp,
                    amid a network of railway lines, and is surrounded by a wooden stockade and an
                    enclosure of barbed wire, the entrance being hard to find. It is a small place,
                    started with convict labour only about two months previous to my visit, and is a
                    factory for making ball twine with the best machinery. Thirty coloured women
                    convicts were employed there, six coloured boys and one man, and five white
                    boys. For these few prisoners there were six or more armed guards, all men. The
                    buildings for sleeping and eating were of wood, and looked new and clean. All
                    the beds were constructed to hold two persons ea^h, and were hung by strong
                    wires from the ceiling. The bedding appeared clean. The closets had doors but no
                    ventilation. There were separate bedrooms for the women, coloured boys and white
                    boys. In the factory all were working together. </p>

                <p>At Speigner's Farm, fifteen miles from Montgomery, old men; women (white and
                    black), and boys are kept, the classes being separated. Most (I was informed)
                    have to sleep two in a bed, as here. They are supposed to have a hospital, but
                    at that time it was not ready. The only Reformatory is one for white boys at
                    East Lake near Birmingham, which is sadly hampered for want of funds. There were
                    sixty-eight boys and only forty- five beds. A bill was recently passed providing
                    25,000 dollars to equip it properly, but was vetoed by Qovemor Jelks, who cut
                    the estimate down to a nominal sum, barely sufficient to keep it going. For
                    girls, and for coloured boys, there is no Refoi-matory, nothing but the
                    contaminating life of prison. <note n="12">The nmnber of State oonyicts in
                        Alabama in 1902 was: Whites: males 214, females 7; coloured: males 1,491,
                        females 97; total 1,809. Percentage of coloured 88. Of thtfse 308 were
                        sentenced for marder, 172 for murder in the second degree, and 226 for
                        attempted murder. The rape cases were 41, and attempts 34. Since this Report
                        was written I have received from the Hon. Warren S. Reese, of Montgomery,
                        the welcome news that steps are to be taken to establish a Reformatory for
                        coloured boys in Alabama.</note>
                </p>
                <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg42">
                    <head>County Convict Camps. </head>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p/>

                    <p>It is in these camps, situated as many of them are in remote places, where
                        the officers appointed by the con- tractors have been free to use the
                        prisoners much as they chose, unchecked by any authority, that the most
                        terrible abuses have arisen. A coloured woman who has interested herself for
                        many years in the prisoners, especially in the children, told me the saddest
                        part was that the women prisoners " will keep having babies." The fathers
                        are either guards or other prisoners. How far the women are consenting
                        parties it is impossible to say; but when they are coloured "they have no
                        more idea of resisting any orders of the 'boss' than my dog has of resisting
                        mine." That terrible cruelties and even murders have frequently taken place
                        in these camps, without anyone being punished, is certain.<note n="13"> A
                            certain Deputy- Warden, a rough but apparently good-hearted fellow, told
                            me he had often had to flog women. I asked him how he did it. He said,
                            *' By turning her dress back over her head and laying on.*' But he added
                            that in his State a rule had now been made that women should be flogged
                            over the shoulders. In the County Camps, it should be remembered, such
                            rules can rarely be enforced. </note> And the difficculty of reform
                        arises from the independence of the county authorities. The Prison Board of
                        the State can make rules and appoint inspectors; but it has no power to
                        enforce the rules except by annulling a contract — an extreme measure which,
                        as it means ruin to the con- tractor, is but rarely taken. </p>

                    <p>In Georgia there appear to be over sixty of these county camps, and the
                        number of misdemeanour convicts in them was, in 1902, about 2,000. In
                        Alabama I have only found the names of seven, with about 900 convicts. There
                        seems to be much jealousy of interference by the State, and the greatest
                        obstacle to reform lies in the fee system, by which, as in many parts of the
                        North, sheriffs and witnesses get fees for every case. </p>

                    <p>Dr. Shirley Bragg, in his report to the Board of Inspectors for Alabama,
                        says: <note n="14"> Fourth Biennial Report of Board of Inspectors of
                            Conviei$^ Alabama, 1901 and 1902. </note> - </p>

                    <p>Many county convicts are convicted on the most frivolous charges, given a
                        sentence of a few days, with a cost bill extending to the very limit of the
                        law. So universal has this habit become in some sections of the State, that
                        it would appear that many of these poor unforttmates were convicted
                        principally for the fees. </p>



                    <p>He goes on to point out that when a county convict is physically unable to
                        perform the work to which he is set, there is nothing but death or the
                        expiry of his sentence to change his position: — </p>

                    <p>I see monthly many who are totally unfit to perform the labour for which they
                        are hired — women, little boys, and old men. I have seen little boys dying
                        of tuberculosis, and old men, sentenced on ftoine frivolous charge, dying of
                        senile debility and begging with their last breath to go home. </p>

                    <p>The Chairman of the Board of Inspectors, in the same Report, endorses this
                        charge, and says: — </p>

                    <p>These misdemeanants are carried to the mines without any reference to their
                        physical condition, and many of them die with- out ever having done an act
                        of labour after they get there. </p>

                    <p>It will be seen from the above quotations that the authorities in both States
                        are alive to many of the abuses that have occurred and are anxious to put a
                        stop to them. Private influence and the apathy of the Legislatures are hard
                        to overcome. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg44">
                    <head> County and City Jails. </head>
                </div>

                <div type="chapter">
                    <p/>

                    <p>These institutions in the South are under the same authorities as the county
                        camps, and present in some ways an even sadder picture. I saw three, — at
                        Atlanta and Macon in Georgia, and at Montgomery in Alabama, — probably the
                        best specimens the two States have to show. </p>

                    <p>I went to the SheriflF for permission to visit the Fulton County Jail at
                        Atlanta. I found him balancing his chair on its hind legs, with his feet on
                        a shelf, and he talked to me in that position. He readily gave me the
                        permission I asked for, and I went to the jail — a small structure in Butler
                        Street, Atlanta, of stone in front and brick behind. It is four storeys
                        Iiigh, and contained at that time 125 prisoners, the number rising sometimes
                        to 250. I noticed that the front gate of the prison was left unlocked, and
                        did not wonder that lynchings are easy. There is a small square central hall
                        with galleries round it, and from these there open iron "cages." Each " cage
                        " has a passage-way with several cells on each side opening out of it. In
                        these cells the prisoners sleep, but in the daytime they loaf up and down
                        the passage-way in the middle, being allowed free access to one another.
                        They have no occupation, and it is too dark to read. As a special privilege,
                        some are allowed, at times, to come out into the galleries. Blacks are
                        divided from whites and women from men. There is some attempt to separate
                        boys from men, but I saw boys of eleven or twelve mixed up with youths of
                        twenty or over. There were several white women, and a good many coloured,
                        and no woman to look after them. The prison is mainly used for persons
                        awaiting trial, the ordinary Court being held once a month, and the superior
                        Court not oftener than once a quarter. Confinement here for several months
                        is therefore not uncommon. Moreover, after trial, a sentence of two months
                        or even more may have to be served here. </p>

                    <p>That is probably the best jail in Georgia, and Macon was much worse — the
                        jail smaller, the arrangements more primitive. The boys and men were not in
                        separate cells, but in cages open for communication with each other and with
                        friends coming in from outside. They had no employment whatever. The Courts
                        are held about three times a year, so that prisoners may have to wait four
                        months for trial, or longer if the trial fails. I noticed an attractive
                        looking white girl in a cell by herself (for larceny) and only men to attend
                        to her. Close by, and in full view of some of the cages, is a primitive
                        scaffold, which is used for executions several times a year. The whole place
                        gave one the impression of being back in the Middle Ages. </p>

                    <p>I did not see the jail at Tuskegee, Alabama, but am told it is extremely bad.
                        I went, however, to see that at Montgomery. I found the officers all in a
                        flutter, as two desperate " safe-breakers '* from the North had that morning
                        very nearly effected their escape by sawing through the iron bars of their
                        cage — bars about two inches wide and a quarter of an inch thick. I saw that
                        these bars had been cut completely through in one place, and very nearly in
                        two or three others. Happily the attempt was discovered just in time, and
                        the two prisoners had been taken down and locked in some dark cells intended
                        for coloured prisoners. I agreed with a statement which was maxle to me that
                        the upper cells were insecure and the lower inhumane. In these horrible dark
                        dens I saw seven little boys, apparently from eight to twelve years of age,
                        who for some petty thefts were put in with grown youths, and with nothing to
                        do. <note n="15">I called the attention of some Influential persons to this
                            fact, and received a coorteous letter from Mr..W. H. Thomas, Associate
                            Judge of the City Court of Montgomery, pointing out that some of these
                            boys were older than they looked, and had been convicted of previous
                            crimes ; but agreeing: that they ought not to be confined in the
                            penitentiary, and regretting that so far the State of Alabama has
                            provided no Reformatory for coloured boys. (See footnote, p. 42.)</note>
                        Dr. Shirley Bragg told me that in this jail it was not unknown for healthy
                        men to be put in the same bed with consumptive patients. </p>

                    <p>It frequently happens that the health of prisoners is 80 completely broken by
                        confinement in these jails that when, after sentence, they are transferred
                        to the camps, they are totally unfit for the labour to which they are put
                        This is simple cruelty. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg47">
                    <head>Prison Reform and the Race Question.</head>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p> The greatest obstacle to prison reform in the Southern States appears to be
                        the indifference of the Legislatures, and the extent to which they are under
                        the influence of persons whose interests lie in maintaining the present
                        system. The Prison Commissioners in Georgia assured me that they have time
                        after time made urgent recommendations to the Legislature, for the adoption,
                        e.g.^ of the Parole law and Probation, but these are year by year ignored.
                        Judge Jones, of Montgomery, who has made a noble stand for justice and right
                        dealing, told me that, when he was Governor of Alabama in 1890-92, he formed
                        a scheme by which in a few years the system of Leasing would have been
                        abolished in that State, and State Farms substituted; but it was reversed
                        under Governor Oates in the years 1894-6. </p>

                    <p>I found a number of influential persons in both States, even during the few
                        days I was able to spend there, who are warmly in favour of prison reform ;
                        and I endeavoured to interest these (in Georgia by a letter to the chief
                        newspapers, and in Alabama by a private circular) in the establishment of a
                        Prison Association such as has done successful work (under the guidance of
                        Mr. Michel Heymann) in Louisiana. The object of such an association would be
                        to enlighten public opinion and influence the Legislatures. I was glad to
                        note that, while I was in the South, a committee, appointed by the City
                        Council of Atlanta, reported in favour of the adoption by that municipality
                        of a Children's Court, and the system of Probation ; also that Judge Fagan,
                        at Birmingham, Alabama, had appointed a coloured preacher as Probation
                        Ofiicer to his Court. I have reason to hope that, before long, a Prison
                        Association may be established in one or both of these States. </p>

                    <p>The two chief obstacles to reform appear to me to be mistaken ideas (1) as to
                        the true object of a penal system, and (2) as to the inherent criminality of
                        the coloured race. </p>

                    <p>(1) The rooted idea in the South is that a penal system should be so worked
                        as to bring profit (in dollars) to the State, and that he is the best
                        Chairman of a Prisons Board who will show, as if he were chairman of a
                        trading company, the largest immediate return. This idea is, of course, tlie
                        logical outcome of a prison system designed "to make the niggers work." It
                        can only be overcome by getting clearly into the minds of those who hold it
                        (a) that a system which hopelessly demoralises the young (apart from any
                        physical cruelty) is inhumane and unchristian; (h) that a system which
                        creates criminals, and hardens them in lawless ways, is in the long run
                        expensive to the State, whatever immediate profits it may show; and (c) that
                        it pays the State to spend freely in preventing demoralisation. These truths
                        lie at the root of prison reform, and are amply verified by the experience
                        of all progressive States. It would be the part of a Prison Association to
                        make the facts known, and to instil sound ideas into the minds of the
                        tax-payers. Unhappily, numbers of well-meaning people, ministers of
                        religion, and others, are satisfied with the reflection that " things have
                        greatly improved," and with the easy assumption that, in ten or twenty
                        years, all will come right of itself. The experience of other States shows
                        that it will only come right if enlightened reformers are earnestly at work. </p>

                    <p>(2.) The idea that the negro as such is inherently worthless is so much the
                        outcome of the historical relations between the races, that it seems almost
                        hopeless to overcome it. It appears to dominate the minds even of
                        intelligent people to such an extent that facts can, with difficulty,
                        dislodge it. And in so far as it is really held, it means that, in the view
                        of these good people, it is sheer waste to spend money in trying to reform
                        negro criminals. It is professed by many who ought to know better.<note
                            n="16"> I am convince that some of these do know better, but speak in
                            this way of the coloured race through fear of being supposed to lack
                            loyalty to their own people, or to favour 'social equality.' </note>
                        Thus a prominent official in Alabama told me that in Fourteen Years he had
                        KNOWN JUST TWO Cases of Negro Prisoners being TURNED into GOOD CITIZENS — an
                        indictment of the Leasing System stronger than he probably intended to make,
                        and all the more telling for being involuntary. Another avssured me that Mr.
                        Booker Washington's work at Tuskegee was only making criminals. When- ever a
                        "nigger" was educated he refused to work, and began to commit forgery or
                        other crime. No pure nigger had brains that were good for anything, and to
                        teach him made him perfectly worthless. An influential gentleman in Georgia,
                        who had been opposed to the Leasing System, said (more cautiously) that he
                        had come to regard it as a necessity for the lower class of negroes, whom he
                        believed to be incapable of reform, and fit only for slavery. </p>

                    <p>The one sufficient answer to these allegations (if the Christian doctrine of
                        the worth of man as man is scouted as "sentiment") is to be found in facts.
                        The United States census of 1890 gives 33,994 negroes in the United States
                        engaged in professional services. Mr. E. Gardner Murphy, a white Southern
                        gentleman greatly interested in education, informed me that there are
                        730,000 farms in the United States of America operated by coloured people,
                        and 150,000 owned by them. In 1899, the fourth Conference at Atlanta
                        University, Georgia, published a careful study of "The Negro in Business,"
                        giving returns from 1,906 negro business men owning a capital of $5,700,000
                        — over £1,000,000. "The College-bred Negro" is the title of another study
                        made in 1902, under the direction of Atlanta University, and reports 557
                        college-bred negroes known to the compilers as owning real pro- perty,
                        assessed to the value of |1,342,862. Mr. Booker Washington (who most kindly
                        entertained me at Tus- kegee, where the noble institute he has raised for
                        the training of coloured youth of both sexes is beyond all praise) reports
                        as follows: — </p>

                    <p>Not a single graduate of the Hampton Institute, Virginia, or of the Tuskegee
                        Institute, Alabama, can be found today in any jail or State penitentiary.
                        After making careful inquiry, I cannot find half-adozen cases of a man or
                        woman who has completed a full course of education in any of our reputable
                        institutions, like Hampton, Tuskegee, Fisk or Atlanta, who are in prisons.
                        Thfr \y records of the South show that 90 per cent, of the coloured people
                        in prisons are without knowledge of trades, and 61 per cent, are-
                        illiterate. Tliis statement alone disproves the assertion that the negro
                        grows in crime as education increases </p>

                    <p>In Georgia the odicial records show that ilje negroes added last year
                        $1,526,000 to their taxable property, making the total amount on which they
                        pay taxes in that State alone §16,700,000. </p>

                    <p>One of the largest manufacturing concerns in Birmingham, Alabama, keeps a
                        standing order at the Tuskegee Institute to the effect that it will employ
                        every man who graduates from our Foundry department. <note n="17">From Negro
                            Education Not a Failure by Booker T. Washington Address delivered in New
                            York, February 12th, 1904.</note>
                    </p>


                    <p>Of the twenty-eight teachers at our school at Tuskegee who applied for
                        life-voting certificates under the new constitution of Alabama, not one was
                        refused registration, and, with few exceptions, the 2,700 who have been
                        registered as voters represent the best negroes in the State.<note n="18"
                            >From 'The Fruits of Industrial Training' in the Atlantic Monthly,
                            November, 1903.</note>
                    </p>

                    <p>I have felt it needful to give this evidence at length because it is usual
                        for any opinion by an Englishman to be discounted in the South, on the
                        grounds that he knows nothing of the facts. The point I am aiming at is to
                        prove that it is worth while to spend money in the eflFort to train the
                        coloured race, and to reform them when they have gone astray. <note n="19"
                            >For further evidence, see the Appendix.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p><span type="sectionHead">The Leasing System.</span></p>
                    <p/>

                    <p>The Leasing System is defended by some on the ground that outdoor labour is
                        essential for the health of prisoners in the South, and that this is the
                        best way to secure it. The alternatives would be State farms, or the
                        employment of prisoners on the public roads. The first of these is thought
                        expensive, and the latter undesirable, AS giving the convicts too much
                        publicity. There is probably much truth in the view that outdoor work is
                        necessaiy, and this is indicated by the miserable record of the county and
                        city jails. In view of what I saw at Baltimore and elsewhere, I should not
                        like to say that some form of the Contract System may not be so used as to
                        secure the proper care of prisoners, and offer chances for their moral
                        elevation. What is essential is that the State should recognise its
                        responsibility for this, and be willing to place it, as the chief object to
                        be sought for, in front of supposed pecuniary gain. There is no doubt in my
                        own mind that one chief reason why the Leasing System survives is that it is
                        thought to be " plenty good enough for niggers." A prominent gentleman in
                        Atlanta, whom I have already quoted as upholding it, signifi- cantly said to
                        me that <hi rendition="i">there would be no such system if all the prisoners
                            where white.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg53">
                    <head>PEONAGE.<note n="20">"Peonage" is a name for a condition of virtual
                            slavery under the forms of law, rendered possible by the helpless
                            economic position of many of the blacks and "poor whites" in the
                            Southern States. A person is charged with vagrancy or crime; a fine is
                            imposed the accused being unable to pay, some one oomes forward and pays
                            it on condition that the accused signs a contract to work for him for a
                            certain period. He is then to all intents and purposes a slave.
                        </note></head>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p> I made inquiry, as opportunity offered, on the way in which the convict
                        system of the South has recently been utilised by certain unscrupulous
                        persons to obtain what is practically slave labour. The Hon. Warren S.
                        Reese, who acted as prosecuting Attorney for the United States in the
                        peonage trials in Alabama, and Judge Jones, whose charge to the Grand Jury
                        was a model of clear reasoning and fearless application of sound prin-
                        ciple, both gave me much infoimation. No printed report or record of the
                        trials could be obtained except such as had appeared in the newspapers,
                        which I read. No fewer than sixty true bills had been found by the Grand
                        Jury in Alabama in indictments for peonage, but most of those who were
                        guilty appear to have acted in ignorance of the United States law which they
                        were breaking.<note n="21"> It is perplexing to an ontsider to find two
                            different bodies of law and G-oyemment, those of the State and those of
                            the Union, in opera- tion together, especially when, as often happens in
                            the Sonth, the two are administered in a spirit of antagonism to each
                            other. I was told that the State authorities pnt many obstacles in the
                            way of the prosecutions for peonage.</note> Judge Jones, in his charge,
                        showed clearly that the State law, in reliance on which they had acted — a
                        law facilitating the imposition of binding contracts or indentures — was
                        contrary to the Constitution, not alone of the United States, but of the
                        State itself. </p>

                    <p>The practice has probably not been altogether stopped, but the trials have
                        had a good effect, and Aggravated cases, I am assured, are not likely to
                        occur again. The ignorance and weakness of the lower class of negroes and
                        "poor whites" will continue to make virtual slavery possible, especially in
                        remote places. Unscrupulous persons, who desire to exploit their labour,
                        find an instrument ready to their hand in the county camps and the fee
                        system, where Sheriffs and Judges have a pecuniary interest in increasing
                        the number of prisoners. </p>

                    <p>A single case will show what has been possible. At a town in Alabama, two
                        years ago, twelve white men were seized, condemned, and sent to the mines as
                        con- victs, without ever seeing a Judge. The SheriflF, a brutal and corrupt
                        man, was in need of money, and had agreed, so it is said, to share the fees
                        with the Judge. These men were walking through the town, and were arrested
                        as vagrants. Some of them really were tramps, but not all. The Judge, who
                        had never seen them, issued sentences which were put at once into execution.
                        The case happened to attract the attention of a certain architect, who
                        noticed that one of the men was wearing eye-glasses, and reported it to the
                        Montgomery Advertiser, The newspaper took it up, and the Governor sent down
                        an inspector. The men were released, and the Sheriff punished, but there was
                        no legal evidence against the Judge. </p>

                    <p>The position taken by Judge Jones, in the face of wholesale calumny, is
                        worthy of all praise. He fought for the South in the great war, and was
                        wounded ; and charges of disloyalty to his section were felt by all decent
                        citizens to be "too thin." The newspapers happily stood by him. One case
                        will show the stuff of which he is made. When he was Governor (1890-92) the
                        Physician Inspector to the Prisons Board, who was under the influence of
                        certain contractors, refused to obey his orders to remove some convicts who
                        were suffering from typhoid, having discovered that the Governor had no
                        legal power to compel him. Jones replied, " Well, you have me there; but I
                        have power to release any prisoner I choose; and, if they are not removed in
                        thirty-six hours, I shall pardon them all." The prisoners were removed. </p>
                </div>

                <div type="chapterTitle" xml:id="pg56">
                    <head> LYNCHING. </head>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <p> One object of my visit was to make inquiry into the causes of lynching. This
                        I did incidentally rather than directly, as opportunity offered. Besides the
                        interviews with State Governors already mentioned, I was privi- leged to
                        have an interview with President Roosevelt, in which I thanked him, on
                        behalf of my committee, for the noble stand he has made for justice and
                        right deal- ing between the races, and received his assurance of cordial
                        interest in our work. I also had a useful talk with Mr. George P. Upton, of
                        Chicago, who for many years collected all available statistics on the
                        subject of lynching for the Chicago Tribune. </p>

                    <p>In summary form the chief conditions that lead to lynching appear to me to
                        be: — </p>

                    <p>(1.) <hi rendition="i">A scant respect for human life</hi>, especially when
                        coloured. I have previously shown (p. 38) that nearly half the State
                        convicts in Georgia are in prison for murder (actual or attempted) or for
                        manslaughter. In Alabama the proportion is nearly the same. It appears that
                        most men in the South carry firearms, and a little provocation is only too
                        apt to bring these into use. </p>

                    <p>(2.) <hi rendition="i"> Race prejudice, and consequent disbelief in the
                            virtue of the coloured race.</hi> Ministers of religion, even, told me
                        quite calmly that they considered terror to be the only force that would
                        keep the negroes in their place, and show them the futility of their
                        aspirations for " social equality." It is here we find an explanation of the
                        frenzy of passion excited by occasional crimes committed by negroes against
                        white women. Such crimes are believed by many of the whites to be due to a
                        determination on the part of the blacks to be their social equals. </p>

                    <p>Among contributory causes may no doubt be placed: — </p>

                    <p>(3.)<hi rendition="i"> Assaults on white women</hi>. The place given to this
                        in speeches and articles excusing lynching is altogether mistaken. Not rape,
                        but murder, is the crime of the South.<note n="22">For rape (actual or
                            attempted) the proportion of convicts is in Georgia, 10 per cent., in
                            Alabama 5 per cent. </note>
                    </p>

                    <p>Mr. Upton showed me that of 2,849 persons lynched — from the beginning of
                        1885 to the autumn of 1903— 561 were lynched for rape. Adding the cases of
                        attempted, alleged and suspected criminal assault, of complicity, and of
                        criminal assault with murder, we have a total of 697 cases, or 24J per cent.
                        The number of cases in which murder was the crime charged against the
                        victims was 1,260, or 44 per cent <note n="23"> I was solemnly informed by a
                            minister of religion in Alabama, as an indisputable fact, that 90 per
                            cent, of all the lynchings in that State were for crimes committed "by
                            negro brutes upon white women." Mr. Upton kindly took ont for me all the
                            figures for Alabama, which showed that in that State, as in the Union at
                            large, the proportion lynched for crimes against women (white or
                            coloured) is only 24 per cent.</note> It will be seen, therefore, that
                        not rape but murder is the crime that causes lynching. </p>

                    <p>(4.) <hi rendition="i">The slowness and uncertainty of the law.</hi> This is
                        a reason often given for lynching, and doubtless it has a place. But in the
                        South not many coloured criminals escape. Booker Washington states that in
                        Virginia the official records show that in one year one white prisoner out
                        of every three and a-half was freed by executive clemency, while only one
                        out of fourteen negroes received such release. <note n="24"> Negro Education
                            not a Failure^ p, 7.</note>
                    </p>

                    <p>(5.) <hi rendition="i">The bad construction of the county jail,</hi> which in
                        some cases almost invite attacks from the mob. (See p. 44.) </p>

                    <p>(6.) <hi rendition="i">The demoralisation earned by the convict system of the
                            South</hi>, which every year turns out men hardened in vice and crime. </p>

                    <p>(7.) <hi rendition="i">A morbid desire for notoriety caused by reading
                            sensational accounts of lynching.</hi> There is much evidence to show
                        that, just as public executions tended to increase the number of murders, so
                        these flaming accounts of murder, torture and burning by mobs, tend to
                        increase the crimes that lead to lynching.<note n="25"> My attention was
                            specially called to this by Mr. Josiah W. Leeds, of Philadelphia.
                        </note>So far from terrorism putting a stop to them, it appears to do the
                        opposite. True it is that Satan does not cast out Satan. </p>

                    <p>There are, happily, signs that a healthier feeling on this matter is
                        spreading in most of the Southern States. </p>



                    <p>Lawlessness is increasingly felt to be a mark of bar- barism and a cause for
                        shame. An address given at Birmingham (Alabama) in April last, by Bishop
                        Galloway, of Jackson (Miss.), is a fair specimen of many wholesome
                        utterances by religious and social leaders: — </p>

                    <p>I give it as my deliberate judgment that there is never an occasion when tlie
                        resort to lyncli law can be justified. However dark and dreadful the crime,
                        punishment should be inflicted by dae process of law. Every lyncher becomes
                        a law despiser, and every law despiser is a betrayer of his country. The
                        lynching spirit, unrestrained, increases in geometrical progression. </p>

                    <p>The speaker went on to urge the education of the negro as the most hopeful
                        cure for the criminal tendencies which admittedly prevail among those who
                        are neglected: — </p>

                    <p>The horrid crimes which furnish an apology for the too frequent expressions
                        of mob violence, almost without exception are committed by the most ignorant
                        and brutal of the race. I have been at not a little paitis to ascertain from
                        representatives of various institutions the post-collegiate history of their
                        students, and I am profoundly gratified at the record. I believe it
                        perfectly safe to say that not a single case of criminal assault has ever
                        been charged on a student of a mission school for negroes, founded and
                        sustained by a great Christian denomination. </p>

                    <p>The Jackson (Miss.) Evening News recently said: — Where this crime of
                        lynching is going to end, what troubles and disasters this open defiance of
                        law, both human and divine, will bring in its bloody trail, no one can
                        foretell. Every intelligent person in the State knows that this form of
                        lawlessness is debasing the public conscience. </p>

                    <p>And the Baltimore News lays its finger on one of the causes when it points
                        out that the convict system of the South " breeds cruelty and vice.*' It
                        says: — </p>

                    <p>No prisoner should be entrusted to the tender mercies of an exploiter in a
                        remote camp, uiicliecked l»y the siipcrviHion of con- scientious officers of
                        the law. </p>

                    <p>If lynching and the crimes that are held to excuse it are to be stopped, the
                        conscience of the Southern com- munities must be awakened, as those of their
                        best representatives already are, not alone to the fundamental claims of
                        humanity, but to the need for education and prison reform. </p>



                    <p>The End. </p>


                </div>

                <div type="appendix">
                    <head> APPENDIX. </head>
                    <div type="chapterTitle">
                        <head>IS THE NEGRO CRIMINAL CAPABLE OF REFORM? </head>
                    </div>

                    <div type="chapter">
                        <p> In June, 1904, I sent out the following circular letter to a number of
                            Wardens of State Prisons and Reforma- tories in the United States, where
                            both white and coloured prisoners are received, and where reformatory
                            methods are more or less employed: — </p>

                        <p>Devonshire Chambebs, London, E.G. </p>

                        <p>June 23rd, 1904. Dear Sir, During a recent visit to the Southern States,
                            I was informed by some persons, whose opinion is entitled to respect,
                            that for coloured crimiDals, as a rule, any methods of treatment which
                            aim at the reform of character are useless. I should be grateful if you
                            could supply me with the means of testing this statement by answering,
                            if possible, the following questions: — <list>
                                <item>(1.) What number of prisoners were under your care on December
                                    Slst, 1903 — (a) white; (b) coloured; and how many of each class
                                    are known to have served previous sentences? </item>

                                <item>(2.) What is your opinion as to the proportion of white and
                                    coloured prisoners who appear to be capable of receiving benefit
                                    from imprisonment? </item>
                                <item>(3.) Are Reformatories for youthful coloured criminals less
                                    useful than for whites? </item>

                                <item>(4.) Have you any other figures available which would help to
                                    elucidate the matter? </item>
                            </list> Trusting I shall not be troubling you too much by this inquiry,
                            and thanking you in anticipation for your reply, I am, yours faithfully, </p>

                        <p>EDWARD GRUBB. </p>

                        <p>To this circular I received ten replies, in five of which the figures
                            asked for in the first question were fully given. As they must have
                            required considerable time to obtain, my thanks are particularly due to
                            those who have been good enough to take this trouble for me. </p>
                        <p>
                            <table>


                                <row role="label">
                                    <cell role="data">Prison or Reformatory</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">Number of Prisons Dec. 31st, 1903.
                                        White.</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">Number of Prisons Dec. 31st, 1903.
                                        Colored.</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">Known as having previous Convictions.
                                        White.</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">Known as having previous Convictions.
                                        Colored.</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">Percentage Previously Convicted. White.</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">Percentage Previously Convicted.
                                        Colored.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">Connecticut (Wethersfield)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">438</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">47</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">51</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">5</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">11.7</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">10.7</cell>
                                </row>

                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">Indiana (Michigan City</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">631</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">141</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">318</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">65</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">50.4</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">46.1</cell>
                                </row>

                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">Kansas (Fort Leavenworth)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">640</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">278</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">91</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">36</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">14.2</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">13.0</cell>
                                </row>

                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">Massachusetts (Charlestown)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                </row>

                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">"" Reformatory (Concord)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                </row>

                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">New York (Sing-Sing)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">1,087</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">142</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">472</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">22</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">45.5</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">15.5</cell>
                                </row>


                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">"" Reformatory (Elmira)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">-</cell>
                                </row>


                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">Pennsylvania Reformatory (Huntingdon)</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">518</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">95</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">155</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">287</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">29.9</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">29.5</cell>
                                </row>

                                <row role="data">
                                    <cell role="data">Total</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">3,265</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">703</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">1,087</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">156</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">33.3</cell>
                                    <cell role="data">22.2</cell>
                                </row>

                            </table>
                        </p>

                        <p>To Question 1, the replies are found in the following table, with the
                            results reduced to percentages. It will be observed that in every case
                            the percentage known to have been previously convicted is lower in the
                            case of coloured criminals than in the case of whites ; and the total
                            percentage is only two-thirds that of the whites. The records of
                            previous convictions are, as has been pointed out (page 9), imperfect;
                            but this fact would hardly tell in favour of coloured prisoners. <note
                                n="26">The smallness of the proportion of "recidivism " is the best
                                general test of the success of a prison system; it should, however,
                                be noted that, while it appears fair to use it as between white and
                                coloured in the same prison, it would not be fair to compare one
                                prison with another on this basis. For one prison (e.g., Michigan
                                City) may be chiefly used for more serious cases, another for first
                                offenders, and so on. </note></p>

                        <p>Small as the basis is on which these figures are taken, there can, I
                            think, be no mistaking their significance. They seem clearly to prove
                            that the coloured criminal is no more inherently irreclaimable than the
                            white. The expressions of opinion given in answer to Questions 2 and 3
                            are to the same effect. </p>

                        <p> In answer to Question 2, 1 may quote the following : Major McClaughin-
                            (Fort Leavenworth, Kansas) says "My opinion is that, taking into account
                            the history and conditions of the races for the past two hundred and
                            fifty years, colored prisoners are as capable of receiving benefit from
                            imprisonment of a reformation of character as white prisoners." </p>

                        <p> Mr. Charles S. Hart (Massachusetts Reformatory) says: "I think that in
                            proportion to their number perhaps one-third more white prisoners
                            receive benefit from imprisonment than do colored, but this is not owing
                            wholly, or (in my opinion) in any apparent degree, to any inherent
                            stupidity or criminality on the part of the colored race." </p>

                        <p> Mr. Addison Johnson (Sing Sing Prison), says: â€” "The coloured inmates
                            of this prison respond quite as readily to our fonn of discipline as do
                            the white prisoners." </p>
                        <p> Mr. Joseph F. Scott (Elmira Reformatoy) says:-"I do not believe there is
                            any material difference as to the proportion of white or coloured,
                            prisoners capable of receiving benefit from reformative treatment." </p>
                        <p/>

                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
